Hello you beautiful people are welcome to this section of the course on the Linux file system.
OK.
So with this section you're going to be learning a whole load of commands that will show you how to
manipulate files using the Linux command line.
And then we're going to start off by talking about the Linux file system and what files actually are
from the file systems perspective.
And when you understand that you're going to move on to discussing how you can move around the file
system and create files using the command line.
Then you'll learn a whole host of new commands such as copying renaming deleting moving pasting searching
for files across a whole file system viewing files searching for text within files sorting data and
also creating file backups and archives for storage and the commands that you're going to learn in this
section are super powerful and come with a lot of options and ways for you to customize their behavior.
Which is great but is a super useful tip Don't worry about memorizing all the different command options
in this section but instead just learn about the possibilities that exist for each command and know
that these videos the cheat sheets that are provided and the commands manual pages will always be available
for you to use as reference.
So I hope hope you are as excited as I am because after the section you're going to have a whole lot
of new commands to use in your pipelines.
Also be able to interact with your whole computer and do 99 percent of your daily work in a whole new
way and you'll find that with the techniques that you learn in this section you'll find them much faster
more powerful and more effective than the graphical methods that you'll most likely using right now.
And if you're like me you'll likely never go back.
OK so it's good to be a really revolutionary section of the Course feel inexorability is abilities.
All that goodness I'll see you in the next video.