Hello you beautiful people and in this video the time has come.
Over the last few videos you've been learning about the structure of the Linux file system learning
how to navigate the file system using the command line you've been learning about file extensions in
Linux and how they differ from what you might find on other operating systems.
And the last video you've learned about wildcards and how you can use them to turbocharge your workings
with the command line.
But in this video you're going to take your first step from just looking at the Linux file system to
actually modifying it by learning how to create files and directories using the command line.
And in this video you're going to learn how to use the touch and the M-K are commands to create files
and directories.
And by the end of this video you're going to be able to create your own files and folders using the
command line.
And then in the video after We're going to show you how to take what you learn here and turbocharge
it by combining it with wild cards you can create like a jillion files and folders in just one command.
And that's not even an exaggeration.
Let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So the first command we want to take a look at is something called the touch command or the touch command
can create new empty files.
So let's say that I'm going to create a new file called file one on our desktop.
So if I just head over to the desktop and I try to create a file called for one.
All we have to do is type touch file one and we can see here that file one has been created and it's
appeared.
OK.
That's pretty awesome.
Now you don't have to do this in the directory that you're in.
By the way.
So for example if I did something like touch and then said I want to put that in the Documents folder
and make in the file called Distant file in the Documents folder.
Now when I go ahead and take a look inside the inside the Documents folder we can see that Disston file
has been created.
And remember that these files here all completely empty they just blank files when you use them when
you create them using the touch command.
So that's pretty cool.
Right now the files that we create with the touch command are completely empty as I said but if you
want to create files that actually have some content in them that's where we can use the echo command
to redirect content into it.
So I'm on the desktop if I want to use the echo command to make a file called Hello directx T.
I'm going to put the content to just the text Hello in there.
Then I'll just type hello and redirect that into.
Hello Don t XTi now redirection when you redirect to a file that isn't made yet.
The shell will automatically create that file and put put what was going to go inside there.
Inside is if I go.
Echo Hello.
And then redirect that Helder to XTi.
The shell will create the file and when we open it we'll see that halo is inside that far.
So that's another way of creating files.
OK.
So that's how you use the touch command to create files that see how you might go around creating folders
making directories.
OK.
So the way you make directories in the shell if I just clear the screen is with the M-K the arc command
which stands for make directory.
OK so make Foldit and it works basically the same as the touch command.
So if we try to make a folder on our desktop called Folder then it will have to do is type M-K Diyar
and call it folder press enter and we see that a new folder called folder has appeared.
All right.
Again this could happen at a distance it doesn't have to be in your current working directory.
So if I wanted to make a folder in our pictures directory called Holiday OK and I press Enter then you
know I can check that in two ways I could proceed to go back to our home directory going to pictures
using CD.
And when we take a look we'll see that the holiday folders that we can have a look at our graphical
user interface as well.
We've got pictures and we've got a folder called holiday that exists right there as well.
Pretty cool right.
Now you can instead of creating folders one at a time you can actually create entire folder paths all
in one go.
So I'm back on the desktop and let's say I wanted to create this path.
I wanted to create blaw slash thing slash problem.
OK but I can't go ahead and make that in one go because Micheles going to give us an error and it's
going to say that the folder doesn't exist.
This is because the shell tried to go to block the entire thing and then create Shambler them.
Now that's just the most ridiculous sentence in the course so far don't you think.
Anyway if we tried to give the M-K Diyar command the p option so we do.
M K D R P give it the p option.
It would then create the entire path.
Even though non of the folders exists.
So if we do block slash things slash blam it'd be like that and press ENTER we'll see that now we've
got blah.
And inside there we've got thing.
And inside that we've got a problem.
So that's really cool.
We made the entire path all in one go.
How awesome is that right now there's something to bear in mind when creating new files or directories.
And that is to try and avoid putting spaces in the name.
So for example if I create a folder called Happy Birthday file tape if I am KTAR happy birthday.
You see the what actually happened is we created two files to folders sorry.
Happy Birthday and that's because there was this space in between the text and that basically made it
to command line arguments.
OK we gave it one input which was happy and one input which was birthday but we wanted to be you just
one input.
Happy birthday.
Ok just one input so how do we do that.
Well actually the way you do that is you do MKR then surround it in quotes.
Happy birthday.
And when you do that you see we get one folder called Happy birthday but just in general having folders
with files with spaces in them is just a bit of a nightmare in Linux.
OK.
And because of this whole space issue in the command line arguments and all that stuff.
So usually what you want to do is instead of having spaces have underscores instead so instead of having
happy space birthday usually what you want to do is have underscores instead of underscores being this
little this little symbol here.
So here you can see that we have another folder but with an underscore instead of a space and that just
makes it work a lot nicer with table to completion.
OK and just lots of other flybys stops you messing up your command line arguments and things like that.
OK.
Another thing of course I think I've mentioned this multiple times but folders and file names are case
sensitive in Linux if I do.
And Cadia are happy underscore birthday.
That's a completely different folder to Happy Birthday in lowercase whereas on something like Windows
it actually wouldn't be the OK.
So that's a quick overview of how to create files and folders using the touch and Cadia are commands
in the next video is going to break in the next video we're going to take it up a notch and start combining
all this goodness with wild cards and a really powerful beti called brace expansion which is going to
allow us to create hundreds of files and folders all in one command.
So let's go ahead and put it right here and I'll see you in the next video.