All right scenary know how to make files and directories using the touch and M.K. DL commands.
Let's take it up a notch and mess around a bit.
So let's say that you're working on a big five year project and every month because the admin staff
hate you.
You need to write a 100 memo files to keep track of the project and the folder should be named something
like Jan. 2017 FEBE 2017 March 20th of March 2017 and so on and so on for five years and in each of
these folders there should be 100 files for 1 4 2 4 3 all the way until fall 100.
How can you create those files and folders up front.
Well doing it graphically would be horrific.
There's actually just no way around it.
There will be a whole lot of copying and pasting and a whole lot of renaming.
And you're right click finger would be basically in agony by the end of the whole ordeal.
But let me show you how easy it is to do on the come on line so to make this possible.
We're going to use a powerful feature of the shell known as Brace expansion.
And this is totally awesome.
Check this out.
So let's go ahead and open our terminal using our control or anti keyboard shortcut.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to head over to the desktop using our cd command.
I'm going to make a big folder called Project.
And there we are.
It has appeared now in here.
This is this good change into it change into that product folder if we can see that now we're in the
Project for the on the desktop.
And this is where the magic happens.
OK.
We need to make 60 folders.
Right.
And they should all be in the format.
Jan 20:17 FEBE 2017 ma 2017 20:17 OK so three three letters then 2017 all the way up until December
2022.
So DEC 2022.
OK which is when the project evidence.
So what if I told you we could make all of those folders in one line.
This is all possible using the power of brace expansion.
So here comes the command.
And what I'm going to do is I'm actually going to maximize the screen because it's kind of a big one.
What we're going to do is win type M.K. DVR.
OK.
I'm going to open up a pair of braces and the braces are these squiggly brackets here and then we're
going to type without any spaces.
Jan comma FEBE comma March comma.
April May June July August September October November December without any spaces at all.
OK I'm going to double underscore the moment Open.
Open up another pair of braces.
OK then 2017 2018 2019 2020 two thousand twenty one and 2022.
So that's quite a long come on right.
But what's happening here is something called brace expansion.
And here we have some braces so we've got one say here and another set here for the for the years and
the way that the shell is going to expand these braces is similar to how you would expand brackets in
algebra class.
OK.
So what happened first is you get January 2017 then February 2017 then March 2017 and so on and so on
until you get December 2017.
OK then it'll just start all over again you get January 28 in February 2018 then March April May June
July all the way until you get December 2018.
Okay.
And so on and so on until you get all the way until December 2022.
So enough in suspense Let's go ahead and press enter.
Let's go ahead and run that now let's see if it works.
We're going to go into our project folder.
Oh oh my goodness.
Look how amazing that is right.
So we've managed to create folders in that wonderful format there for every single one of the years
and if we highlight them it tells us that the 72 folders actually created.
So from January 2017 right here all the way until December 20 22 which is right there and everything
in between.
Isn't that awesome.
Just as an aside as well if I just maximize this here to say it was a bit of typing we could have actually
instead of typing out each of the dates because it's just numbers they're just numbers right that are
in a in a constant pattern.
We could have just done dot dot.
So 2017 to 2022 that's another aside right there.
Now imagine how long it would have taken to do that stuff using point and click method you imagine how
annoying that would have been.
Well we just did it in one command line a case so that we're sitting here feeling very smug that our
command line has just created like a jillion folders all in one go we've still got a little bit to do.
And that is we've got to create 100 files in each of these folders.
Now how are we going to do that.
Well actually it's quite easy we'll just use brace expansion again.
So we're going to do is we're going to open up our terminals again go onto the desktop go into the product
folder.
OK.
Now I'm here.
I'm actually gonna maximize the screen watch what.
Just watch what I do and then we'll see how it works.
OK.
So don't touch then I'm going to open up the Brace's.
John FEBE March April May June July August September October November December.
Underscore and our years 2017 2022.
Oh by the way it doesn't just have to be numbers.
It could be a to Zed or a to Zed or something like B to F or something like that.
OK so anything is it that has a pattern like you know the alphabet or numbers you can use the dot dot
thing to make that happen.
OK but we're after 2017 till 2022.
OK.
Now inside each of those folders we're not going to make a file called the source file and then has
one to wonder.
Ok so what is going on here.
This is Matt Ziyad Where where has this command come from.
Well basically what I'm saying is for each of these folders from January 2017 all the way until December
2022.
In each of those make file 1 to 100.
OK now this is just a bit of fun.
Ok so don't worry if it seems a bit like what.
It's just to show you how powerful the shell can be.
Let's take a look at it again.
Run that.
Let's close the terminal again.
Let's go ahead and take a look.
Let's open up.
June 2022.
OK.
Because that's a good date.
So if we open up June 2022 we click that oh my goodness we've got file one to 100.
OK maybe that was just a fluke What if we open up December 2020 and hope this fall one to 100 in there
as well.
What if we open up January I say April 2020.
There we go again we've got fall 1 to 100.
OK.
So isn't that awesome guys like you can see the way that we've just used brace expansion to make our
terminal command unbelievably powerful.
And if we've got 72 folders and I say well we're only going to do it for five years we ended up doing
it for six.
But if we have now got 72 folders with 100 files in each we just use one command line to create about
seven thousand two hundred files in one go.
I hope you can see just how powerful the shell is from from that little example right there.
OK.
And by the way brace expansion isn't only possible for the touch and Cadia are commands.
By the way it's actually usable across the whole shelf.
So for example let's take the ls command the ls command.
We can look in every single folder and get a list of what's in there.
So if I do.
John FEBE March April May June July August September October November December and then 2017 till 2022.
OK so I'm saying list out the contents of every single one of these folders basically and I press enter.
Oops.
I'm in the wrong place.
So good desk top slash projects now press up key twice to get back there go again.
Well we can see the contents of every single one of the folders and you can see they all have 100 files
in it.
And we can see that we get the for 1 to 100 in every folder and it might look like the file ends in
fall 99.
But what's actually happening is if you look over here and see a file what it's doing is it's sorting
them alphabetically or sorting them numerically here so you see for one for 10 for 100 because they
all start with one right and then the nines end up over there.
But now we are getting as 1 to 100 in each.
And let's let's say that we wanted to take all of this output right this massive output and we just
got and redirect it redirect all the output into a file called out Dottie XTi.
And now when we when we take a look we've now got a file called out Dr. XTi.
And if when we take a look in there we can see that we've got all of that content in there.
April 2017 it tells us the files that that has and then it tells us what's in April 2018 and it tells
the following that this is all alphabetically sorted in there.
Isn't that awesome.
I'm just showing you here we have an epic file with the contents of 72 folders and in about 7200 files
in just one command line tell me that is an epic and would have took you for ever to do using point
methods now I appreciate this is really is this is really going to be a bit like whoa and that's OK.
All right.
I'm just showing you these basic skills.
Have these basic skills or just creating one file or creating one folder can easily be turbo charged
with very little effort.
As long as you understand a little bit about brace expansion of wildcards cards but I'll leave the imagination
as to why why you would do so up to you.
Because these skills can be applied to many different things and you know just just just to show a much
simpler case of brace expansion.
If we go to the desktop right here and say we just want instead of saying tourch file a text file be
Dottie XTi and file see tickety which will work fine.
We'll create three files brace expansion it makes that a bit easier by saying file you give it some
brackets.
A B C D C C because we're using the break the braces here.
Who's going to file a text file be that text.
Force-Iraq tasty presenter.
Now we are we've used brace expansion to expand that out.
OK.
So Bracey expansion comes into play all over the place.
And because here we are we've got some text which is a follows a very simple pattern we can use the
dot dot here and we're going to get the same result again we could we could maybe say OK I want file
F all the way to the.
We are going to get 4 v all the way to F on the desktop as well.
So here we are here f as V.
So to show you this brace expansion it's not particularly complicated thing.
Trust me there are useful things for what I'm showing you here but I just wanted to show you just how
powerful the shell can be with just a little bit of tweaking.
So that's sort of command line craziness for now let's just have a quick recap of what was actually
important from the last two videos.
So first of all you saw how to use the touch command to create new files and the use also so how to
use the mkdir command to create new directories which is my favorite way of saying the command.
By the way.
And you also saw that the mkdir command also has a powerful p option that can be used to create entire
folder paths.
So this is creating one folder inside of another folder inside of the folder.
All from scratch which is very very powerful stuff.
Use learn creating for files and folders in Linux is case sensitive and you learn that it's kind of
a bad idea to have spaces in your font aims so use underscores instead.
And finally we took file and folder creation to the next level by using brace expansion and embrace
expansion is kind of an advanced technique so don't worry if you didn't understand it.
It's not technically part of the course but you got to see it here anyway.
So lucky you.
But now that we've got a whole bunch of files and folders cluttering up our computer in the next video
you're going to learn how to remove them.
So to learn how to delete files and folders.
I'll see you in the next video.