Hello you beautiful people I'm welcome to this video where we're going to be kickstarting our discussion
of how to delete files and directories using the command line.
So in this video you're going to learn how to use the r.m command to delete files and you're also going
to learn how to use the r in command along with wildcards to make the room command even more powerful
by the end of this video you'll know how to delete files using the command line and then the next video
will move our discussion onto directories.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
All right so let's kick off by creating a file called Delete me in our home directory so we can see
that we're already in a home directory by looking at the shell prompt.
We see the tilda the squiggle up there which means when the shell prompt but to confirm we could just
type the PDB the command print working directory and see that we are indeed in our home folder.
So let's create a file called delete me.
We're going to use the touch command and type delete me and press enter and then if we use the ls command
we'll see that we do indeed have a file called delete me and been created.
We can confirm this of course by opening up our graphical file browser and we'll see a file called delete
me.
Ok so so far so good.
Clearing the screen.
Now that we've created delete me how can we actually delete it.
OK.
Well the way to actually delete or remove that file is using something called the R M command.
Now the r.m command is.
I will r.m stands for remove.
And all you've got to do is give the r.m command a set of paths to files that you actually want to delete
and these could be absolute paths or relative paths.
So if we open up the man page for the r.m command it says that you can give it more than one file.
Ok you see you can give it a file and then it's got three dots after it.
And we know from our discussion of command line syntax or command line layout that these three dots
mean you can have more than one.
And if you need a refresher on that check the cheat sheet in the previous section it's got all the information
there for you.
So let's go ahead and remove delete me so I could because I'm already in the same folder.
I could just you know use the relative path like that.
R.m delete me.
And when I press Enter we'll see that delete me has indeed been deleted.
I could if I create delete me if I create delete me in our documents folder this time.
OK.
So if I look in our documents folder we see delete me has been created at the minute in the command
line.
I'm just in the home folder.
So if I tried to do r.m delete me that won't work because there is no such thing as delete me in this
in this directory.
So delete it.
I have to do all RAM documents.
Slash delete me so I have to give it the path relative to where we are now which is the home folder.
So here I am in Voda to get to delete me after documents then delete me.
OK so documents just delete me and I press enter and then it gets deleted.
OK.
And you can have more than one.
So if I go ahead and create a file called let's say for one directx.
That's in our home directory.
I create a file called Faltu in our documents so fall to take in our documents and a credit for called
for three dot tickety in our downloads.
Like I say I've got one in the home folder.
One of the documents and one in downloads.
OK so nearly all those I can just enter them one after another so I do r.m for one text.
I don't have to do anything because of that.
That will do because I'm already in the home directory the same folder as it documents slash Faltu and
downloads slash file 3.
If I Precentor you see the file one disappeared Faltu has disappeared from documents and 4:03 has disappeared
from downloads.
So DRM command is a very simple command to use for files.
Just think of it as the opposite of the touch command.
If you want to create a file you do touch foreign one you want to delete it already.
R.m far one and it will work just like that.
So whether we've seen how to use the Aurum command in a basic way let's take it up a notch and use it
along with wildcards.
Now wildcards can really level up the power that your commands have.
So let's just see see how we do this using the R M command.
Let's make a few new files.
Let's make a file 1.60 spec Faltu dot PMG and 4:03 dot JP G.
So when I press enter you see that all three of those have been created in our home folder.
OK now how would we delete every single one of them that ended in Datti XTi.
So that's actually just fanatic's make another one file for Datti XTi case.
We've got to the end in directx take and we've got one that ends in PNB and GBG.
How would we delete them.
They're the ones I ended up here.
Well first of all we could do it manually.
We could say our M-file won doctor 60 and for 40 actually that would work.
But I want a bit more of a clever solution than that.
I want to say delete every file that ends in Dot T x T.
Now the way we do that is by giving the command a pattern and anything that matches this pattern will
be added as a command line argument to it.
So if the pattern that I'm going to use is this star Datti XTi.
Now let's break this down.
OK so the star means anything.
Anything could go there.
So this whole thing is our pattern.
OK the start means anything and then Datti XTi.
So what this means is for anything to match that pattern at all it has to do is and in Datti XTi right.
So basically what this is saying is remove everything that ends in Dot XTi and we press enter on that.
You see the fall one and fall for have been deleted because they ended in Dot.
T x t.
OK so let's let's try and see if we could make some other forces make this make file 1.60 again and
fall for the DOT T.
Let's make those back then.
Then let's let's create some of the files.
Is create some called Sublime Dotti x t and the circlets problem one right and then blam to.
PMG and sublime three top JPT.
So we've got some that start with problem and some that start with the Word file.
OK how would we delete the ones that just start with the word file.
Well the way that we do this is we would use the r in command.
Again of course because we need to delete then we need to give it another Potten.
So let's think how would we create a pattern that would match anything as long as it started with the
word file.
Well the way we can do that is we can take the word file and then put a star because this means as long
as it starts with file and then has anything after it it matches.
So all it has to do is start with the word file.
And if I press Enter we see the file 1 2 3 and 4 that text that you know doesn't matter about the file
extension or anything as long as they start with file they've been deleted.
But all of the Shebaa farms have been kept there.
OK.
So let's let's create 4 1 2 3 and 4 again so we're going to create touch for 1.60 Faltu dot PMG for
3.0 JPT and 4 for Dr. XTi we'll make them back again.
OK.
Now we want to delete all of the files that have the number two in them.
So how would we do that.
Well what we might do is we might say OK let's remove.
It doesn't matter what it starts with but it's got to have the two in there and it doesn't matter where
it ends in.
OK so here we are we're saying it could have anything then the number two and then anything afterwards.
Because if we do that we see the Faltu has been deleted and shoeblack 2 has been deleted but all the
others are OK.
What about getting rid of the ones that end in dot Jaypee.
Well to do that used to all RAM ends in Doc Jaypee I press enter for three JPT and sublime three have
been deleted.
All the others and the doctor he XTi are still there.
What about deleting those r.m everything that ends in Doctor XTi press enter.
And they've all been deleted as well.
So you can see here how wild cards can really make the the your commands a whole lot more powerful and
a lot more specific.
There's one more that I want to show you let's just go up here.
We've made back our files and let's make back ash blam problem files problem too doc PMG.
I think and sublime three top JPT.
OK.
Now what if we wanted to get rid of the ones that had two or three in them.
Well do you remember how we got to the one that had two in it.
Right.
We said it could start with anything then have to end in anything.
Well now we want to give it some options.
And this is where the square brackets come in.
So far he said.
OK.
Something like that but saying it could start with anything then have either two or three and then ending
anything.
So they should get rid of four two four three and sublime two and three.
So if hypocenter Faltu and fall three and problem two and three have been deleted.
So wild cards are incredible tools that really allow you to control what's going on when you use your
commands and anything that matches this pattern will be passed as a command line arguments to the command
that you use the wild cards for.
So that's a bit of wildcards in action as well.
So there you have it in this video you learn about the r.m command that the r.m command is the command
that's used to remove stuff from your file system.
And in this video we focus specifically on deleting files.
You also built upon what you learned in the last video about wildcards and saw wild cards being used
in action to delete files.
Now what you saw about wildcards in this video it doesn't only apply to the r.m command.
What you wrote about wildcards and how you might do specific tasks works for any command.
You build patterns called regular expressions with wildcards and whatever matches those patterns is
passed as a command line argument to the command that you're using.
So there you are you've seen some wild cards in practice as well.
Up next what we're going to be doing is we're going to be developing this discussion a bit more I'm
going to move on to looking at how you might delete directories.
How can you delete folders.
So that's a that's a completely next level it can be very smart and stuff.
So see you in the next video.