Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome to this video where we're going to be finishing off our discussion of how to delete files
and directories using the command line.
So in this video you're going to learn how to use the Ahram and are MDR commands to delete folders.
And by the end of this video you'll know pretty much everything you need to know about deleting files
and folders using the command line.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
All right so let's start off by creating a folder in our home directory called Del folder.
So if I use the mkdir command and type Del folder we'll see that we created a new folder inside our
home directory called Del folder.
OK.
So let's remove it.
OK now all we have to do actually to remove it is use the r.m command again for use Ahram and use del
folder and press enter.
We actually get an error.
Now this is because yes we will use the r.m command but in order for the R M command to remove folders
we need to give the r.m command the r option but the r option stands for recursive or recursively.
Now if you delete something recursively that means you'll delete that thing and everything else inside
of it.
So if we try that now our ram slash our and then del folder OK and press enter.
We'll see now that Del folder has indeed been deleted.
So let's make it again make it again make Del folder OK and let's make some more folders inside of it.
So we're going to use brace expansion for this now.
OK.
We can do make make directory Del folder and inside there we're going to make three folders called Delete
me one two and three.
OK.
So if I press enter and take a look at Dell folder we can see we've got the lead me want to get me to
and delete me 3.
So that's how this works.
We made first it made me want inside of Dell for that then it may delete me too.
Then it made delete me 3 comsats brace expansion again.
So let's make some files inside each of those.
So if we touch Dell folder delete me delete me one two and three and then inside of their make file
one two and three.
And now if we take a look we can see and delete me one.
We've got four one two and three and delete me 2 for 1 2 and 3 and then delete me 3.
We've got file 1 2 and 3.
So now if we if we go ahead and if we just look we've got Del folder here we've got Dell folder in our
home directory.
Now if we use our ram with the option to delete that Del folder remember to delete something recursively
means to delete it and everything else inside of it.
So if I use r.m with the option and give it Delphos then press enter will see that folder has indeed
been deleted and so has everything else inside of it.
Now one thing you might notice is that the r.m command when it did that it actually didn't give us any
warning.
It just went ahead and deleted everything inside the Dell folder folder.
OK.
Now because of this our ram dash on em with the corruption is a very powerful command that should be
dealt with very carefully especially when you start using the Star wild card as well.
All things can go wrong and you can find yourself just deleting everything and not being able to get
your files back which is sad sad times.
So for example if I do go ahead and do that now if I just delete that on everything on our system right
now I'm not going to do it I'm joking.
So one way to make the argument safer is actually to give it the option.
OK.
So the option stands for interactive and this will make the r in command askew interactively.
Whether to delete each file or not.
Now at the moment we don't have we don't have the Dell folder anymore.
So to make Dell folder and delete me one two and three all at once.
I'm going to use the make the command give it the option which allows you to create an entire path and
do Del too and Telic create delete me 1 2 and 3.
So if I do that actually not dealt too.
Sorry Dell folder.
OK then I get Dell folder inside there that me wanted me to do it three can call right now let's create
the files inside Besso Dell folder forward slash delete me one two and three and we're going to make
file one two and three and so each of those and so each of those We've got our files back.
OK.
So there we are.
Didn't take too long at all.
We've got our files back by the way.
Can you see just how much quicker this is than pointing and clicking.
We created all those files without ever even needing to enter the folders which created them right from
a home directory.
So.
So cool.
So now if we tried to delete everything again try and delete Del folder by giving the command the R
and R options.
OK it doesn't matter which order you do it.
So we give it Del folder we'll see that.
Now it's asking permission for us to actually delete things so it's saying Can I go into Dell folder.
Let's tell it yes.
OK.
It will now say can I go in to delete me one.
Let's say yes.
And can I delete a file too.
Yes you can can delete 4:03 three.
Yes she can cannot delete for one inside.
Delete me want if she can can I remove the directory delete me one.
Yes she can.
Can I go into delete any three.
You see it's not particularly doing it in any order but it's asking you before it does it.
OK.
So say yes you can do it that you can delete that you can do that.
Now let's leave it let's leave file to inside delete me too.
OK.
So you can delete delete me 3.
Going to delete me too.
No don't delete fall.
Yes delete 5:3 yes to the for one.
No don't delete the entire folder no don't delete folder and that's it.
Kate said if we look inside Dell folder we should see delete me too.
And Faltu still leftover.
OK so that's quite cool right.
You can control what the command deletes But this is kind of tedious right saying yes and no every time
it's a.
If you had a lot of files that would that would really be a massive hassle.
So fortunately there's another command that specialized for only removing directories that are empty
now because this command only removes empty directories.
This means that you can tell it to delete everything.
It will only delete the folders that are actually empty.
Which means you'll never delete a file accidentally.
And that command is called the MDI or the remove directory command set to see the remove directory command
in action.
First let's go ahead and delete everything inside Dell folder remove recursively DLL folder and Ardell
folder has been deleted.
Now let's go ahead and create some folders so we're going to use mkdir with the option to create.
Let's call it Dell folder and then folder one to three.
That's another way of doing it by the way you don't have to type one comma to comma three.
You can just do one dot dot three.
And if we look in Del folder We've got 4 to 1 vote to vote 3 and as put ten folders inside folders one
and two but not in folder one.
9:43 says to touch Delph folder folder one too and then put inside their file 1 to 10 to 16.
So if we look inside for the one we've now got 10 text files we look inside for the two.
We've got 10 text files in folder 3.
We don't have any.
OK so now we've got three folders inside Dell folder folders want to follow to have 10 files in them
but folder 3 is completely empty.
Now if I tried to do remove directory and I say remove directory Del folder slash everything.
OK what we're saying here is delete everything inside Del folder.
Delete the empty folders inside folder.
Basically if I do that will see it failed to remove folder one because the directory is not empty it
failed to remove folder too because the director is not empty but 2:56 has indeed been deleted.
So just so you know this wouldn't have worked if we'd just done remove directory of Dell folder without
putting the star CC we've got the star asterisk wildcard here.
If we just have removed Delph folder the shuttle site.
But Dell folders not empty.
How can I just delete it.
Well what we did is we said remove everything that is inside Dell folder that is empty.
OK so we have to have the star there to make that work.
That's just something to bear in mind.
OK so one final challenge in the last video we created a project folder that had a whole bunch of other
folders inside we'd like a jillion files.
Ok you must remember this for the last few videos.
Now what I want you to do is I want to try and delete all of those folders and directories and files
and stuff in one command.
OK so that's your challenge.
That's natural challenge you've got to try and delete the entire project folder with everything inside
of it all the thousands of files in one command so.
Post the video now and see if you can figure out figure out how to do it.
Then come back and see how you did.
Did you manage it.
If so.
Well done you learn super super quick.
So here is how I do it.
OK now I have the folder was called Project write it was on the desktop such shift there.
It's it's called Project.
So we want to delete everything so we don't want to use the R MDR command because that only deletes
empty directories.
We want to use the r.m command instead because we want to delete directories that have stuff in them.
OK now we want to delete the project folder and everything inside it.
So we need to delete recursively so to do that we're going to use the r option.
OK.
And putting it all together basically means we'll just do remove recursively the project folder.
Or if I was in my home directory like this I would remove recursively desktop's slash project.
OK just given the path to that folder and when I press enter.
As if by magic.
However many folders there were the thousands of files have been deleted.
How absolutely epic is that so that'll just about wrap up our discussion of deleting files and folders
using the command line.
So in this video you learn that the r.m command needs the option in order to delete folders and the
option stands for recursive deleting.
So delete something recursively means to delete that thing and everything else inside it.
And this is what you need to be especially careful when using the option because you can end up deleting
stuff that you didn't want to know one way to make that a bit safer is to use the option for the r.m
command which will allow the r.m command to be interactive when it does it's deleting.
So this is where you can say yes or no to each file folder being deleted but the best thing is there's
not really much you can rely on.
Just be careful when doing your deleting.
OK.
But the safest of all options is to use the R MDR command which will only delete folders that are empty.
So if you just want to do a bit of tidying up and delete folders that don't have anything in them you
can use the MDR command.
And rest assured that you won't delete any data.
So coming up next we're going to discuss how you might copy and paste files and directories using the
command line.
So instead of cutting our file tree we're going to make it grow.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.