Hello you beautiful people are welcome to this video where you're going to learn how to copy and paste
files and folders using the command line.
Now this should be a nice and quick lecture with just one command.
The C.P. command which handles all the copying of files and folders in Linux.
By the end of the video you'll know how to copy and paste files and folders using the command line and
you also see how to use the C-p command with wildcards to make copying and pasting even more awesome.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
OK.
So here we are.
And as you can see by the shell prompt I'm currently on the desktop and on the desktop I have a file
here called File 1.60 and if I opened it says hello there you beautiful people.
I wonder how that got there.
So let's say we wanted to copy that file to another file called file to Dr XTi.
OK because I'm very very imaginative.
So to copy it we use the c p command and the C-p being short for copy.
Now we just need to tell the copy command.
What we want to copy and where we want to copy it to.
So what do we want to copy.
Well we want have to copy file 1.60.
And remember I'm on the desktop already in the shower so I can just write for 1.60 if I was in the home
folder I would say copy desktop sosh for 1.60 just just so that you're aware.
OK.
So let's go to the desktop again.
So we need to tell it what we want to copy and we want to copy it to.
So we want a copy for 1.60 and we want to copy to one or the file called Faltu tactics.
So that's all we've got to type want to copy far one into another file called File 2.6 and when I do
that we'll see we get a file here called Faltu.
And when I open up that also says hello there you beautiful people.
OK.
So that's how you copy a file to another file which is pretty simple.
So how would you copy a file to another folder to the directory.
Well that's pretty simple too.
As I say the copy command all you've got to do is tell it what you want to copy and where you want to
copy it to.
OK.
So let's say I want to copy fall one into this folder called Destination.
So I'll have to do is I copy file one.
So far 1.60 and copy to destination.
And also let's say I also wanted to copy Faltu at the same time.
OK so it's copy for one and file Faltu into the destination folder.
OK so you can see here that the last thing that you put as a command line argument is the destination
and everything else that comes with for that is what you want to copy so I could have many many many
different commands.
And many many different files that I want to copy here but the last one is where I want to copy them
all to.
Correct.
So with that let's go ahead press enter and when I look inside destination we can see that we've got
four one on file two.
They have both been copied into that.
So as you can see this whole copying and pasting business is actually rather simple with the command
line.
And of course you can also do it with wild cards.
So I'm on the desktop at the minute.
Let's say I want to remove everything that starts with the Word file.
So if I do that both the text files should disappear because they both begin with the Word file.
So if I do that are they both disappear.
Now I can copy and paste all the stuff from in the destination folder to the desktop but you're saying
copy destination.
Slash everything.
OK.
To this fold.
And how do I select this folder.
Well if you remember back the there's always a hidden folder in each location and that refers to the
folder is if I just do and that is the full stops so if I just do that dot dot.
What that means is copy everything from within the destination folder into this folder which is the
desktop which is where we currently are the game.
So if I do that if I press enter.
You'll see the file one file to have been copied and pasted to this location which is represented by
the full stop here.
And if you don't remember if I just do ls with the A option you can see here that we've got these two
hidden folders and the one with the one refers to this folder and the one with the doubled up refers
to the folder above it which is our home folder.
OK so I could for example copy everything from the destination folder to the parent folder of where
we currently are which is the home folders.
If I do that and I now look at our home folder we can see the file one file to have been created in
there.
So look wildcards work absolutely great with any command.
Even the copy command as well.
So let's clear the screen.
We have seen how to copy and paste a file into another file.
We've seen how to copy and paste a file into a folder and we've seen how to copy paste files from folders
into other folders.
The only thing we need to know is how to copy and paste entire folders.
OK so we have here.
This copy the folder on the desktop and that's got three files in it.
It's got Faleh Fabi and falsie.
OK.
And we want to copy this entire folder into the destination folder so we don't just want the files we
want the folder as well so we don't just want the chocolate.
We also want the wrapper.
OK.
So the way that we can do this is by giving the C-p command the option which also stands for recursive.
Now if you remember from when we were deleting files and folders in the last few videos with the r.m
option recursive deleting meant delete that folder and everything inside it.
And it's very similar for the copy command.
What we're saying is copy the folder and everything inside of it.
OK.
So to actually copy the copy of the folder into the destination folder we just typed out we say could
we say copy with the option then copy me into the destination folder and if I do that and then we look
inside the destination we will see that the copy me folder has been copied and pasted and all of the
different files are inside there as well.
All safe and sound.
So they have it.
You can now copy and paste files and folders using the command line.
It's quite easy right.
So as a very quick review you saw that the C-p command is what deals with copying and pasting of files
and folders in Linux and the way that it works is you have the C.P. you type c.p.
Then what you want to copy and you can have as many of those as you like.
And then in the end the last command line argument that you give it is your destination.
OK.
So you can have many things you want to copy but the final thing that you give it is the single destination
where you want all of those things to go.
Now if you want to copy entire folders so not just their contents but the actual wrapper the actual
folder itself.
Then you need to give the copy command the option to allow it to copy entire folders recursively.
And now with copying and pasting and way up next what we're going to be doing is we're going to be discussing
moving and renaming files and directories in Linux.
And what's really interesting is that you can actually use just one command to do both those things.
So to learn how to move and rename files using just one command I'll see you in the next video.