Hello you beautiful people and welcome to this video where you're going to learn everything you need
to know all about moving and renaming files and directories using the command line.
Now the interesting thing is both of these functions can be completed with just one command.
So in this video you're going to learn how to use the envie command to move and rename files and folders.
And by learning the one command we're going to cover in this video you're going to gain two very important
abilities for working with your file system.
Talk about efficiency.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
OK.
So let's first talk about renaming files now on the desktop.
I have a file called old name Dotti XTi and I want to rename it to be called new name Datti XTi.
Very imaginative.
I know.
Now to do this do this rename.
It's really very simple to do using the M.V. command.
So first we get to the desktop.
OK so now I'm on the desktop where the files actually are.
And to rename all name to the new name.
All I have to do is just do envy then old name Datti XTi which is the current name of the file and then
give it its nooning which is the new name Datti XTi.
And when I press Enter you'll see that the file has been renamed.
OK.
And we can see that using the LS commands.
Well it's now a new name Dottie XTi simple and the same thing works for directories so I have a folder
here called old folder.
And as we can see old folder actually contains a few files so it's got file one to fall 10 inside there.
OK.
Now to rename.
Old folder to be called new folder and clear the screen.
All you need to do is move old folder folder and when I press Enter we can see that the folder has been
renamed and it's just that simple.
And even though we've just changed the name of the folder if we open it up all the files are still in
there exactly as they were before.
So renaming folders doesn't damage any of the contents inside.
So with that said how can we move files from one folder into another folder.
This is also actually really simple.
All we need to do is give the move command what we wanted to move and then the directory that we wanted
to move them to.
So this is very similar to the copy command with the copy command you gave it a list of all the things
you wanted to copy and then the final command line argument you gave it was where you wanted to move
it to copy it to sorry.
And it's the same idea with the move command.
OK so if we want to move everything from a new folder onto the desktop then all we have to do is say
move from new folder OK move new folder.
Everything in there to here which is the desktop.
OK.
So the doctor Remember means the current working directory.
And this is you can see from the shell prompt that is the desktop.
So what we're saying is move everything from within new folder to the current working directory which
is the desktop option if I press enter.
You'll see that all of the files have been shifted onto onto the desktop which we can see using.
Alas we've got a one to 10.
And if we look inside New Folder we can see that they haven't just been copied.
They have indeed been moved because the folder is completely empty.
OK so let's move all of these files back into a new folder.
So if I move everything that starts with file back into new folder that should take care of all that.
So there we go we've moved them all back into this new folder folder.
OK.
Now how can we move the whole of new folder just as Wonga.
How can we move this into our documents folder for example.
Well that's really easy to do as well.
And it works just like you might expect.
We just do move new folder and where's our destination when we want it to go into the documents folder
which is in our home directory.
So we put the tilter to say our home directory slash and then documents so the documents folder inside
our home directory we press enter and then when we look inside our home directory and go into our documents
folder there we are there's new folder sitting there all intact.
So now for the jackpot how can I move a new folder inside of documents or move it somewhere and rename
it at the same time.
So let's say I want to move it from our documents folder to the desktop and rename it to the jackpot
at the same time.
So how would we do that.
Well first we need to sell it we sell and move on what we want to move.
So let's say we want to move the new folder folder inside our documents folder.
And this is something you should be comfortable with by the way using the tilter to represent your home
folder then documents then new folder.
OK.
The slash at the end is optional but I think it comes with the table to completion so we'll well we'll
leave it there.
OK.
Now where do we want to move it to.
We want to move it to our desktop so we could say the current working directory because as you can see
we're on the desktop.
So we're going to get the current working directory but we're going to call it jackpot.
So jackpot now because the jackpot folder doesn't exist.
New Folder will become jackpot.
If I press Enter we'll see that jackpot has been created.
Inside there are all the content or every single one of the files from new folder.
And if we go back into our documents we will see that new folder is no longer there.
So what happened.
We said move the new folder folder from within our documents folder and put it in this directory which
is the desktop.
But as as a folder called jackpot.
So that is how you can move a folder and rename it at the same time.
Pretty awesome stuff right.
So there you have it.
The M.V. command is a very simple but very effective command for anything that you'll ever need to do
with moving or renaming files.
And in this video you've seen how to move and rename files and directories using the ENVI command.
And this is how it works.
So if you want to move files and directories first you type the M.V. command then you give it command
line arguments.
Everything that you want to move and you can give it multiple of those and then the final command line
argument is the destination of where you want to move all of those things to.
And if you want to rename files and directories we can only do one at a time but you give it what you
want to rename and then the new name and location if you want to move and rename at the same time and
you've seen how to do that in this video.
So just remember that if you have want to move or rename a file the NV command is what you need.
So in the last few videos you've learned how to modify the file tree quite a lot.
You can now create files and directories using the touch and and KTAR commands.
You can delete files and directories using the Ahriman or MDR commands you can copy files and directories
using the C.P. command and you can even move and rename files and directories using the command.
Well in the next video you're going to learn how to actually edit these files using the command line.
Now obviously this is going to be something that you'll do all the time.
So for all that good stuff I'll see you in the next video.