Hello you beautiful people and welcome to this video.
You going to learn how you can edit files from the command line using a really cool command line program
called Nano.
So in this video and the next video I'm going to show you how you can use a command called Nano to edit
and create files using a user friendly command line interface.
And by the end of the next few videos you're going to know how to edit files in nano.
And when you combine this with the commands that you've already learned so far in this section it's
very likely that you'll be able to get many of your file related tasks done with Linux without ever
having to leave the command line and therefore you'll be able to maximize your productivity on Linux.
So this is going to be awesome.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
All right.
So in this lecture we're going to make a file called Diary Datti ex-state using the Nano command.
Now the diary Datti X-C file doesn't actually exist yet but that's OK.
We can also create the file using nano.
So if we type not let's go to the desktop first let's head over to the desktop and then if we type nano
diary Dr XTi OK and I press enter.
You'll notice that our terminal has changed its look and we're actually now editing a file called diry
that takes tape as you can see at the top.
In the Nano editor as you can see here nano version 2.0 eight point six.
Apparently now we can type what ever we want in here.
So for example I could type hello my name is Ziyad and I teach Linux and Python courses and more.
OK.
And it works just like any other graphical text editor that you've ever used before.
And you can just type directly there in the shell.
Now down the bottom you can see that there's actually a little toolbar that tells you some of the things
that you can do in nano and the options are in the white squares and then in the form of keyboard shortcuts
solitaire you have to read them.
OK.
So in nano The little arrowhead that you see here the little hat or the carrot symbol means the control
key on your keyboard.
So for example here we have the GET HELP command over to get help.
I guess option from the toolbar and it's given this this shortcut here it's got the arrow head and then
a capital G.
So if we press control on our keyboard and press g which is exactly what we do is just control Engy
together that executes that command and we can see here that we have now when in the Get Help menu and
we can scroll down and see some help about using nano.
OK.
And we can see here that there's some to close this we would need to press control and X because you
can see the little arrow and then an X server was controlling X Chewbacca there and we're back writing.
OK.
We can also close Nano for example by pressing control an X and it will say do you want to say yes or
no let's just click cancel by control and see that we are both canceled we're still back in.
OK.
So how would we save this.
How do we save this diry directx t in in our home folder glossary on our desktop sorry because you can
see up here shopfront says that we're in our desktop.
Well to do that in nano you would use the right function.
So writing a file is a fancy way of saying saving a file so saving and writing are basically the same
thing.
And so to write a file we need to press control and oh so we've got the arrow the little carat symbol
here which means the control key and oh.
So that means we've lost control.
Oh and now it's asking us what do you want to save as let's save it as diary takes t and we press enter
it will say it wrote three lines but we can see here that we've actually got diry dot TXI takes.
If we open that in any other data we can see that that file has indeed been created.
So I could write something in here I could say like you know something like Jack and Jill went up the
hill.
All right and then press control and press enter.
And if I press control an x x it OK it's gone away.
But if I look inside diabetic's a save that data in that Jack and Jill went up the hill.
So it's the Nano is a text editor that you can control from the command line.
So isn't that incredible.
You can now edit files without needing to load up graphically intensive editors.
And plus working with files like this will work pretty much anywhere even if you have remotely access
to a server that might not have a graphical user interface installed.
Text editors such as Nano will still work.
So what other things can nano do.
Well let's just work our way across the options.
Now we've seen how to get help how to quit using control and X and how to write or save files using
control no.
What about the lead file option down here the control and our well read file allows you to get content
from another file and basically place it inside of this one.
So if I head back to our shell if we exit and we try to create a file that says happy birthday and we
echo happy birthday into a file called birthday party X-C we see the birthday party XTi has been created.
If we are back open up again the diary takes tea and we head down the bottom and we press control and
our control in our is full read file and it's going to say which file do you want to insert.
And notice it says from dot slash.
That means from this directory.
OK.
So let's let's try and sell it.
So the one you actually insert data from his birthday.
XTi.
And if I press enter you can see that happy birthday has just been inserted.
So that started reading files What about the where is option.
Well the where is option is control and W and what that does is basically search for words in your file.
So if we head back up to the top of the file and we press control and W now we can search for words
that search for the word birthday.
So if we type birthday and press Enter we now see that Nano has jumped us right down to where the word
birthday starts.
And so we can edit it from there on.
Now by default the where is option search is forward in a file and it searches in a case insensitive
manner.
So that means that uppercase and lowercase don't matter.
So if I went up here and I searched for birthday or in uppercase.
Actually you can notice that it shows you what you search beforehand.
So I'm just going to put both in uppercase we can see that it actually didn't matter.
And it found birthday even though birth it was all in lowercase So where researches in a case insensitive
manner and or by default search is forward.
But if we had down to the bottom of the files if we shift down here and use control w again you can
see down the bottom if I maximize the screen maybe it makes it a bit clearer that there are actually
other options that pop up as well.
OK.
Now some of these options begin with the the carrot symbol the heart which means the control key but
some start with this.
M minus.
OK you can see em minus C minus or minus B minus J.
So what's the minus mean without minus.
Stands for modify.
And this is usually the alt key on your keyboard so the HLT key so you can see here that we've got the
M and minus C option which stands for case sensitive.
So if our press Alton's see you can see now that it has changed so that we are now searching in a case
sensitive way.
OK so if I now search for actually hold on as well because this is only going a search forward so I
can if I press alt and be to search backwards as well.
When I begin to search case sensitive and backwards for birthday in uppercase I will see that nothing
was found.
You see but if all you do just like the control and you see it saved our settings is going to be case
sensitive and backwards benefices birthday all lowercase we see that that has been found.
OK.
So that that's quite awesome right.
You can also modify the way that these commands behave.
So if you see m minus that means press the old key the HLT key on your keyboard.
And if you see the triangle we have the little arrowhead That's the control key on your keyboard and
that will cover pretty much everything that you'll do in nano.
So let's just head back to our normal menu here.
So in the interests of time we're going to cut the video here and we're going to pick it right up in
the next video.
We will go through the rest of the options that you have in nano.
So I hope this was useful you've seen that nano is a text editor that you can open from your command
line that allows you to do all your file editing stuff without ever leaving the command line.
So I can just say hey we've got dormi that takes day at it to make some changes save it x.
And we're back in the command line so it gives you a really nice way of editing files and getting back
to what you were doing.
So let's just get rid of say the exit clear the screen and we're good to go continue on with our work.
So let's pick this up in the next video to take a look at the other options that Nano has to offer.