Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back to our discussion of how to use the Nano command line text editor to get your work
done.
So we were in the last video we were discussing some of the options that Nano has and we discussed the
Right-O option the read option the where is option and we got up to the replace option.
So let's actually use the read form option to read in birthday doc text again.
So we're going to say birthday Dot text and you see that we've got happy birthday.
Read into the file once again.
And the reason I've done that is so that we can now use the replace command and you can see here that
the replace command although replace option here is activated by pressing control and a backslash.
Now I find the backslash next to the letter Zed on my keyboard but it might be wherever that is on your
on your computer or on your keyboard.
OK.
So the press control and backslash.
And now it's asking me what I want to replace.
So let's replace birthday.
OK.
And we're going to replace it with code day.
And when I press Enter it's going to now go through each instance of where it found the word birthday
and ask if you want to replace it.
Now you can see it on the bottom here is because I do want to place this instance I could say yes I
could say no or I could say all or I could say control and see for cancel.
So let's just press a to make it replace all.
And we see that every instance of birthday has been replaced with the word code day.
So happy code day to you you beautiful person.
So that's replacing text what about cutting text cutting text is the next one.
So cutting is very easy you can see here we've got this line that says Happy code day.
If I press control and K to cut that basically deletes the line and if I want to paste that.
So basically it's just like cutting and pasting just in your normal everyday computer use.
So if I want to uncut it I press control and you and I can do that as many times as I want.
So this is a very very happy code day.
We can also justify the text using control and JS control obvious NJ we'll see that the text has been
set so that it takes up the full width of the screen are controlling you now to unjustified.
But you can see if I press control NJ to justify the text the paragraph that I mean takes up the full
width of the right context for with the screen and for birth control and you can justify it.
So something to bear in mind if you look at control J is justified.
And before you justify control you is uncut text.
But if birth control and J.
You see that control you has now switched to justify kind it tells you here you can now justify controlling
you.
It goes back to the way that it was.
So up next we've got the two spell option which is basically a spell checker.
Now by default a spell checker isn't set up for Nonno.
So if I press control t it will say spellchecking failed error invoking spell like OK.
What that means is that there's a spell checker not actually set up but we can set one up.
So let's just save our file by pressing control in 0 to write it.
Yes that'll do.
And then press control X to exit and clear the screen with control and l see a lot of keyboard shortcuts
going on here.
So to actually edit the text they that's sort of a spell checker that is used for Nonno that's in the
Nano configuration file which is actually located in our ETSI folder in a file called Nano or C so that's
open not really ironically with nano because if we do that here we are we've now opened our nano Ossy
So it's slash ATC slash nano Ossy.
So if I show you that graphically where where we're going we are in our base directory by going to other
location I think.
So this is the slash folder.
Then you go ATC.
So sloshy UTC then somewhere in here there'll be a file called none and none of us see this.
If we click on NORC that's basically what we've opened.
OK but let's make sure that we open it in in here.
OK.
Actually at the minute this file is in fact on ridable because we don't have the Persians to edit it.
So to make that actually editable we need to do pseudo nano sloshy UTC slash nano RC.
OK so this pseudo bare basic alleged to run this command is the administrator but we'll come onto that
a bit more later in the course.
You enter your password that you normally use for logging in.
And now you can edit the file.
OK.
Now there's a line in here that has the word a spell or spell in it.
So let's find that by using the where is Command says where is aspell press enter.
And it found it.
OK.
So this line it says here use this spelling checker instead of the internal one.
This option does not properly have a default value.
OK so to get rid of that actually to make that actually happen we just need to get rid of this hash
symbol and get rid of the leading space.
Now there's no there's no hash just set Spellar.
I spell dash ecstasy just like that.
And we write out and close.
And now if we go back into nano for our diary text if we press control and t to actually stop the spell
checker we now have a spell checker working so it's not quite cool right we just use Nonno to edit Nonno.
It's awesome.
So here we are.
It's going through a spell checker is telling me my name is wrong.
Well that's charming isn't it.
There you go.
That's how you can actually go about setting up your spell checker and you can just enter things in
here.
So if I wanted to change my name to let's say Yoda which of course I do.
Because that's totally awesome.
I just enter five and you see that my name is now Yoda and it's a fact because it's on a video.
OK.
So if I now go I can also close a human to any of these Otterman you can ignore replace Agta dictionary
and replace all or ignore all or whatever it might be.
But let's just press X to exit and there we are we're back into normal stuff.
So once you've edited that all you've got to do it when you get to that so that your spell checker works
you're good to go and it is possible to to also add different dictionaries and stuff like that as well
and you can find that information online as well.
OK so there we are that's how you do spellchecking and control and see is apparently tells you your
current positions if I press control and say they will tell us I'm on line 1 out of ninety five percent
of the way through column one to 70 characters 0 out of 275.
So if I move over here now and I press control and say change I'm now on line 7 column 10.
So for us this is this is good you know if you are working on a file and you want to give it to someone
and you say Oh hey can you change this file at this given position or you're giving people instructions
on how to use a file you say online 7 in column 11 change this text.
OK.
So in fact just to show you let me let me actually save that.
Yes.
If I go to any slash ETSI slash Nonno or C file and I can search for where is that a spell.
Now I can tell you I'm on a spell and if I press control and see I can see here that I'm on line 172.
So if you want to set your spell checker go to line 172 and that's the line that you need to edit.
For example that would be one way to do it right.
So I can close that get back into the direct text.
Now we're getting through the next option is control and under score and that allows us to go to a line.
OK.
So if I press control on the scope and first control the underscore.
Oh sorry I'm pressing the wrong button here.
There we go because it just goes in a bit of a weird position on my computer so controlling.
And he says enter the line number and column number.
So let's go to line 10.
Column 2 and then we are in line 10 column to see if I can actually get this stuff to get a bit bigger.
There we go I've made the font a bit bigger.
So control on the score done it because I have to press control and shift and underscore there we go
on mine anyway.
So so now you're going to do a line number and column numbers or let's say Line 9 column 12.
There we go.
We are in line on Ivan columns aren't separated by spaces separated by letters.
OK.
So here are his column 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12.
That's that's where we are this way we might get two if you want to call it 12 on whatever line.
So if I said to you let's ask Slash ETSI slash non-war was fall and I looked for using using the where
is command.
I do control the B and I search for a spell and I get to this line.
I'm like Huh.
Where is this line.
Control and see which is composition.
It says Line 172.
OK so now on your computer.
OK.
When you open the file you get like ha Z and says Line 172 surplus control and underscore into line
172 press enter.
And I've ended up at the correct line so you can see how useful that might be if you're collaborating
on something with someone.
So let's get back into our diary duct tape.
We've then got undo and redo.
So if I for example cut out all these things here and then I was like oh I don't want that.
Let me undo.
You can see I just undo and it undid all those bleatings I could also press Olt and remember this could
be escape or command depending on your keyboard layout and just the modify key whatever that is for
you.
On my keyboard it's old but if I press alt and we should redo Altan you undo redo Olson.
Alton you.
Yeah yeah.
I've broke it now but you get the point.
So.
So that's how you can undo and redo stuff.
And instead of cutting Could you see if I could.
Now I can uncut instead of cutting.
You can actually just directly copy.
So here you've got to do all.
And the number 6 for press ultimate number 6.
Now I can press control in you and I'll start pasting so maybe if I if I do it here Alton's 6 and then
press control on you.
Now I'm copying and pasting just like that.
So that saves you from actually cutting and Mark text as far as I've seen.
I don't use that one very often but as far as I can tell all that does is allow you to highlight stuff
so yeah it just it just kind of allows you to highlight stuff.
So there we go.
That's basically everything you need to know about using the Nano command so you are you beautiful people
in the last couple of videos you become very familiar with using the Nano command line based text editor.
Now the benefit of using a command line based text editors such as nano is that you can get all of your
work done without leaving the command line which basically maximizes your productivity.
It's a command line editors have lower resource requirements than graphical equivalents so you don't
need as much hardware usage in order to actually run them.
And also if you are remote administering something like a server the techniques you've learnt here would
still work because nano basically comes with every version of Linux at least the most common ones anyway.
So you've learned how to use nano and we've looked at a lot of keyboard shortcut options and you saw
how to use and pretty much all of those.
So you don't have to memorize them don't worry about that now you've got a bit of an idea about how
they work.
Honestly not I was just a text editor.
You can just type text in there you can write code in there whatever you want to do and you can edit
files in there.
But just bear in mind that the tools are the options in there are accessed using keyboard shortcuts.
So if you see this little hat then that means the control key.
And if you see minus that either the old escape or command keys on your keyboard depending upon your
layout to try them out see which one works on your keyboard.
On mine it was all it might be different on yours.
And you also saw that you can edit how nano works by editing its configuration file which is located
at slash ETSI slash nano or C.
So a lot of this stuff is going to be probably for reference for you so you've got it here in this video
in this course to refer back to later on if you want to look anything up.
But really Nano is very simple to use you to type Nano and then they found that you want to edit.
And you know you can just go and edit it like any other text file.
So there you are you know know how to end it follows from the command line and should be feeling quite
a lot more like a computer wizard.
At this point.
So with all this super awesome file creation moving copying and pasting and editing that you'll be doing.
It's possible that you might want to find where certain important configuration files are located so
that you can edit them or where that fall that Ukraine is run off to but you don't want to have to go
through each folder manually to look for them.
So in the next video you're going to learn how to search for files anywhere on your system using the
locate command locate command is one of my favorites and I can't wait to show you.
So for all that good stuff.
I'll see you in the next video.