Hello you beautiful people so one really amazing thing about Linux is the way that pretty much everything
on the system can be treated as a file.
And I saw this earlier when we did the totally awesome magic trick will be redirected data from one
terminal to the other and that was possible because the terminal was treated as a file by the Linux
operating system and can redirect data between devices on your system just like you can redirect data
between files.
Now every one of the files on the system is on a structure known as the Linux file system tree.
And in this video you're going to learn how the Linux file system is structured and you're also going
to get a tour of what some of the most important places on the file system are.
By the end of the video you'll know the map of the land so to speak.
And by knowing what you're actually navigating and how it's laid out you'll be much better prepared
to actually navigate it and modify it.
And that's what we'll start learning in the next video.
So you're going to learn about some very important locations on your computer and also therefore which
will help you navigate even better loads of really awesome stuff in this video guys.
So let's go ahead and get into it.
The first thing you need to know is that the entire Linux file system follows a tree structure.
So if there's no partitions on your hard drive every single thing on the system can be accessed in one
large tree structure.
So let's go ahead and take a look at it.
Here's an image of what the file system looks like.
Now at the top of the tree we have what we call the root directory represented by the slash here.
Now just to be clear in case you haven't come across the word before when I say the word directory I
basically just mean the word folder.
OK so when I say a root directory I'm just referring to the root folder on the file system.
The slash here now that folder is called the root directory because everything on the file system can
be traced back to that.
Just like every branch and leaf on a tree can be traced back to the root of the tree.
Now under that root directory there's a whole bunch of other directories these directories are said
to be subdirectories of the root directory.
Another way to say that is that the root directory is the parent directory for all of these directories.
In orange here now there may be more folders or directories present on your system but I've taken the
most important ones to show here in this image because a slide only has so much space.
Now each of these directories can have all the directories and files inside of them and the directories
inside those directories can have their own directories and files and so on and so on and so on.
So the whole system does eventually look like a really big tree with hundreds and hundreds of branches.
Now one of the most important directories on this tree is the home directory the home directory holds
individual directories for each of the different regular users on the system.
We can see that the system has three regular users.
We've got Alice Bob and Charlie and each of those users can have their own files.
So for example if we take Bob we can see the Bob has folders in the home directory for their desktop
documents downloads music pictures and so on.
And each of those folders can have files and folders inside them Alice will have a similar structure
and so will Charlie.
You can access your home directory by clicking on this file's icon over here.
And what opens up by default will be your home directory.
Now everything that we've been doing in the course up until now so just playing with pipeline's redirection
and stuff and creating files they've all those files have all been in our home directory and you can
see that in our home directory We have a desktop documents downloads music pictures and so on and so
on just like Bob did in the diagram.
And if you are navigating around your file system you can always get back to your home directory by
clicking on this home icon here or by finding it in the path that appears at the top you can think of
everything on the file system as being in two major parts.
And this is a bit of an oversimplification but you can think of everything below the users home folder
as being specific to that user.
And everything that's above the users home folder tending to affect the whole system.
Now what good would it be if regular users could modify or even delete files that the whole system requires
to run.
Not very good at all.
And that's why special files and folders that tend to affect the whole system usually require elevated
administrator or root privileges.
The root user on the system is similar to the administrator in windows on Linux.
The root user has absolute power over the entire system.
Now I'll show you how you can perform actions of the root user in a later video.
But for now just be aware of their existence.
For now I just want to discuss what these folders at the top here do.
Now there's a lot of them.
So to save you from memorizing I've made a cheat sheet that you can download from the resources section
in this lecture.
Let's go ahead and go through it together now.
OK so as I said you can get a copy of this cheat sheet from the resources section in this video and
what it basically contains is a list of the different folders that are right underneath the root directory
written with a slash and a bit of a description about what they do so that you can have a bit more of
an understanding of what each of the folders does on your system.
Let's just do a quick whistle stop tour of each of them and then you can look at it later in more detail
for yourself.
OK.
So we've got the slash directory to zoom in a little bit make it make the thing a bit bigger.
There we go.
So you've got the slash directory which is the very top or the root of the factory and this directory
holds everything else there is nothing higher up than the slash directory.
If you get here you are at the very top of the tree.
You've got the bin directory which stores common Linux user command binary b.n binary is where Ben gets
its name from for example the date command.
Come on now commands that are all stored in the binary is sex in the binary folder.
You've got the boot folder boot is for everything that is required to boot the system so bootable linux
kernel and boot loader configuration files over the dev folder.
So this is these are files representing devices.
Now there's many different files in that folder.
If the filename starts with T.T. why that's a terminal.
If it's also with F.D. that's a floppy disk.
If it's starts with SD or Haiti that's a hard disk.
If it starts with RAM then it's RAM and if it's also a CD then it's a CD-ROM.
You've got slash ATC which is administrative configuration files.
No ATC or ETSI as it's normally said is a very common folder.
You'll be using it a lot if you ever want to edit configuration files and how you edit those configuration
files is where Section 5 of the Linux manual comes into play.
Which is all about file formats and things like that so for editing many of the configuration files
are in the ETSI folder you'll be able to find a man page that'll show you how to do it.
Then you've got the home folder and the home folder is where the home directory is.
For regular users are stored so under the home folder you have a home directory for each of the different
users so for example I have one at slash home slash Ziyad.
I have my home folder inside the big home directory so if I had 3 other people on my computer called
Alice Bob and Charlie they'd be slash home slash and slash home slash Bob slash slash Charlie.
But in my case just slash slash Ziyad.
So that's where your home directory is stored in the home folder.
You've got slushed media which is where removable media such as us be stick's external hard drives and
things are mounted and anything that is removable from the system unlike hard drives like actual hard
drives.
Anything that's removable usually gets mounted on slash media slash lib is where shared libraries so
lib being short for libraries needed by applications in the slush business last Espen folders to boot
the system.
So this is where all that stuff is all loaded basically loads of installed stuff cause it's slash lib
slash.
MT is a place to mount external devices you don't use it that often.
Usually slash media is used instead slash misc.
Being short for miscellaneous is a director we use to sometimes automate filesystems it's just there
just in case the system can use it.
Slash OPEC or Opt. is where you can store additional or in other words optional software.
So anything that you install any programs that you install usually the files go in slash O.P. to slash
prok is about system resources as more administrative kind of stuff slash route.
Now this is the home folder for the root user.
So this is sometimes a point of confusion.
You've got the roof folder which is the slash sometimes called the slash directory and you've got slash
root and slash root is the home folder for the root user.
So it's a bit of a confusing terminology but just just bear in Bear that in mind.
OK the slash is the root directory.
It is the very top of the file tree and slash route is the home folder for the root user or the super
user or the administrator.
Similar city administrator if you are on Windows that's the home directory for the administrator almost
there now you've got slush Espen which contains administrative administrative commands or Beiner is
for the root or super user.
So Espen being super use a binary is OK so these are commands that can be run by the super user or the
root user.
You've got slashed VMP which contains temporary files run by applications sometimes when programs are
running they create temporary files to make them more efficient to run.
That's where those are stored.
The DMP folders usually cleared out very regularly or when the program's shut slushing us our last user
contains files pertaining to users that in theory don't change after installation and slash var contains
directories of variable data or data that changes a lot.
That can be used by various So for example system log files are usually found in here and log files
change a lot.
That's why they're in the slash or slash variable slash var being short for variable.
So they are these are the different folders.
The only at least the most common ones that are directly underneath the slash folder so have a look
at this Jiechi read through it once again and you know maybe with my video with my voice playing in
the background you don't have to memorize this.
The cheap seats there just in case you don't have to memorize this stuff you very quickly become familiar
with the most common ones that you'll use.
Most likely you'll just stick to using ETSI which is where configuration files are the home folder and
maybe media if you plug in a USP drive or something like that and maybe slash user if you want to and
it's something to do with programs.
But usually those are the most common ones you'll be you'll be dealing with but you'll become very familiar
at where files are.
We'll be using a lot of these different folders as we go through the course or don't worry if it all
seems like a bit we're right now that information is there forever.
Just take it take it one step at a time.
Don't be overwhelmed by it.
It's going to be fine and you'll very quickly become accustomed to it.
OK so there you have it.
You should now have a much better understanding of the Linux file system and how it's structured.
So as a quick recap we discussed that the Linux file system follows a tree like structure starting at
a base directory which is represented by the slash.
Now you lumber everything on the file system can be traced back to that base directory.
You also learned that there's a special user on HLN next system called the root user the root user is
similar to the administrator on Windows and the root user has absolute power over the entire system.
They can do anything that they want.
You learn that the home directory or the slash home directory holds individual home directories for
all the regular users on the system so that they have a place to store their personal files.
And you learn that the slash route folder is the home directory for the root user for the administrator.
You also have to look at a bunch of really important folders that are right underneath the base directory
and there's a cheat sheet that you can download in the resources section.
Well all that information is summarized for you.
OK.
Brilliant so that you understand the whole structure of the file system which is totally epic in its
own right.
I've also put a link to a series of blog posts in the resources section to learn more about the Linux
file system.
If you want to but for now we're going to go ahead and jump into using the command line to start navigating
the file system which is going to be really exciting.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.