Hello you beautiful people.
So in the last few videos you've been learning how to create and modify files and directories in all
kinds of different ways.
And when you're working with files in your computer it's really easy to misplace one or two and wonder
where an important file that's new to you such a configuration file might be hiding.
So in this video I'm going to show you how you can use the locate command to actually search for files
by name and find them no matter where they might be hiding on your computer or with the command line.
Pretty cool right.
So we're going to break this up into two parts in this video you're going to learn how to use the locate
command and some of his options.
And you're also going to appreciate some of the limitations that the locate command can have.
And then in the next video the one after this one you can to learn how to overcome those limitations
and also how to access administrator privileges on the system in order to update a database.
So this is all going to be very cool stuff very very exciting.
It's going to give you superpowers basically So let's just go ahead and get right into.
OK so the locate command is actually really simple to use but it's very very useful.
Now the first thing you need to know about the locate command is that it works by searching a database
file that's on your system.
Now this database holds location information about every file that's on your system and the way that
the locate command works is that you will give it some pattern to look for and then locate will search
the database for every path that matches that pattern and give it back to you on standard output.
Then this is actually really easy so let's just jump right in and get a feel for how this works.
OK so for example let's try and find every file in our system that ends in dot c o and F..
OK.
Now Dot CNF is a file extension that is common on Linux to indicate that this file is a uneatable configuration
file.
OK.
Because file extensions don't really matter to Linux.
Linux users and developers usually leave meaningful file extensions like dot com so that you can understand
what the form might be about just from reading the file extension log is another common example and
it's use for log files that store error messages from programs and server applications.
So you know you can look at these log files later on in case anything breaks and see where the stuff
went wrong.
OK we're going to look at files end in dot com.
OK now to search for all the dot com files on our system.
One way to do is type the locate command and then give it the paten we want to search for.
Now you should start remembering what we did about regular expressions and wildcards.
So just think for a minute how would you make a pattern that matched any file that ended in dot com.
Just think about it for a second.
And you might remember that perhaps you need to have the star wildcard and then dot com.
This says anything that matches this pattern here and that means it can start with anything and then
end in dot com.
OK so this pattern will check for files that end in dot com.
And that's actually all we need to do right.
So if we do that and press ENTER wo right you'll see like a whole bunch of different fall paths come
out.
But you'll see that every single one of these files ends in dot com.
Now it's worth noting that by default Linux is case sensitive.
But you can make searches using the locate command case insensitive by giving the locate command the
option.
So for example if we just click the screen and we do locate and just say dot com but spell everything
in uppercase now you'll see that we actually get no results because Linux searched case sensitively.
It had to be exactly everything in uppercase.
OK.
But to make locate search in a case insensitive way we could give the locate command the option and
what this does is say hey don't worry about the case I'm just looking for these letters and when I do
that we get again files that end in dot com.
OK.
So that's something to bear in mind there.
And you can also limit the amount of results that you get.
So we have hundreds of results coming out this one look how many there are a lot of configuration files.
But if we click the screen we code say OK let's search in a case insensitive way but let's limit it.
Limit the outputs to just three results.
OK.
And you can see here I am using the long form.
Limit options.
We got the two dashes then the word limit and then we give it's command line argument which is three.
So this limit option has an input of three.
So when I do that you can see that we are just limiting it to three results if I change that to 5 we'll
get five results for change to 10.
We will get 10 results and so on and so on.
So this is useful.
You know if you just want to get the first few results you only want to find a few results you can limit
it like that as well.
Now the key consideration to have when using the locate command is to understand that it uses a database.
In fact you can actually find out information about the database using the capital S option.
So if I clear the screen and we use locate and give it the capital ask the uppercase s option I can
press enter and you'll see that we get some information about the database itself.
So it tells us the path to the database file as well as some size about the general saw some information
about the general size and complexity of the day base.
So I'm actually going to save this information using a redirects if I use locate acet I'm going to save
that into something on our desktop.
Let's call it database before texting.
So we've got Farkle database before that day on our desktop.
With all the information saved in it.
OK.
So you can see redirection is actually a very useful skill and you'll just use it all the time and you
should be proud.
Now you understand how to use it as if it's nothing.
Right.
So this database just like any other day base is only useful if the information in it is up to date.
OK.
And the database by default is updated just once a day.
So this means that anything that happens in the mean time is not logged in the database files could
have been created moved deleted and unless the database is updated then the locate command will start
to give incorrect results.
Now there are a few options that come with the locate command to help minimize this issue.
They can't make the database list files that haven't been added to it yet because that's impossible.
But they can prevent the locate command from showing files that have been deleted.
In the meantime all things that no longer work.
For example there is the option that requires the locate command to check that the file is existing
before it reports it back.
So for example if we did locate with the option of everything that ends in dot com then this would check
the database for all files that ended in dot com but also do a check to make sure that those files actually
existed before reporting them rather than just taking it from the database directly.
It will take them from the database but also do a check to make sure that they are there.
So it gives you that extra bit of assurance there is a long form option for the options instead of typing
a dash 8.
You could type Double Dash existing.
OK.
And that does exactly the same thing.
So it's very very useful stuff.
And sometimes there are shortcuts and links on your system called symbolic links that might be broken
if files get moved around to check whether these shortcuts and links are still valid before the locate
Command reports them back.
You can use the capital L or the follow option like this so locate follow everything ends in dot com
for this.
So if there are any symbolic links are there any links to files it will check that they aren't just
dandling they actually arrive somewhere arrived at the right place for reporting it back.
That's another assurance and of course you can do both at the same time so existing and follow gives
you basically the maximum assurance you can get there.
And again you can combine it with case insensitivity and limited to just show 5 and you can combine
all these options showing you here just how powerful the Linux command line can be to have multiple
different functions going at the same time.
Now these safety features are all well and good but what we really need to solve our problem is to have
a way to update the database whenever we like and there is it's called the update D-B command.
And for the purposes of time we're going to cut the video here and pick up learning how to update the
database in the next video.
So I'll see that.