Hello you beautiful people so in this video we're going to be finishing off our discussion of the locate
command and in particular you're going to learn how to update the database using the update d be command.
And you're also going to learn in the process how to gain super user privileges.
So administrator privileges using the sudo command.
So this is going to be a very important lecture touching not only on how to make the most out of the
locate command but also giving you an absolute nugget of information on how to gain administrator privileges
which is such a useful thing to be able to do more higher level things on your system.
So by the end of this video you're going to know how to update the database at the locate command uses.
So the locate command always gives you accurate and correct results and you also know how to run administrator
commands using sudo.
So this is going to be a very important lecture.
Let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So let's start learning about the update D-B command which is short for update database Hebel name right.
So let's create a new file on our desktops and move to our desktop and we're going to create a new file
called Find me Dr. XTi so we can use the touch command find me Pontiac's T.
And there we are we have a file called Finding activity on our desktop.
Now if I try and run the locate command because this find me file has been created before our database
has been updated and the locate command won't be able to find it in the database if I try and locate
find me not here.
We'll see if we get absolutely nothing back.
OK.
Even though the file exists it's not been entered into the database yet and therefore it the location
can't find it by searching the database.
OK.
So to update the database were added to the database we need to update the database.
And that's where the update D-B come command comes in.
So if we try it will notice that we actually get an error and the error says that the shell cannot open
the actual database file.
And the reason for that is the update D-B command requires administrator privileges in order to run
and we can see this by looking at the man page for the update D-B command and we see at the top of the
update D-B command that is in the system managers section it's in Section 8 of the manual.
And that means it requires elevated privileges in order to run and you can see here what I was saying
about Update D-B being run daily.
So you can read more about that if you like.
But the important thing here is that it's in Section 8 of the manual and therefore requires administrator
privileges in order to run and refer back to the Chichi about the manual structure.
If that if you need a bit of reminder of that and what the sections of the manual do.
OK.
So how can we get the administrative privileges in order to run this command.
Well to do that you use the pseudo command I'm not sure if it's pronounced sudo or su do but am I.
I like sudo so we'll stick with that.
So the sudo command is very simple you just write it before any command you want to run as the administrator.
So I'm going to type update debate and that's it.
OK.
Now when I do that because we're trying to get administrator privileges and the sudo command is going
to ask us for our password to enter my password which is the password I just use normally to log in
to the next computer.
But you know it's that we don't see any password being typed out.
Now this is a security feature that's built into the shell that stops people from knowing the length
of your passwords.
And the reason is that if people know the length of your password it makes cracking it so much easier.
So don't worry that you don't see any feedback.
Just type your password type the password is being accepted by the shell when you've done that press
enter and we'll see that the shell will pause for a bit as it updates the database.
And then we have a shell prompt backed ad which lets us know that the command has completed.
So now that we've updated our database they find me file should be in the database now.
So let's try and see if the locate command can find it let's type locate find me find me that text.
When I press Enter you'll see that yes it did find it this time it tells us it's on our desktop and
it's called Find me not text and we don't have to be on the desktop.
We could be in our let's say in our documents folder.
We can press Primack and directory.
We see that in our documents.
But if I do locate find me anything like that and you say it comes up with slush home slashes the odd
slash desktop slash find me dot XTi So it tells us where the where the actual file is.
Now if we take a look at the database file as well let's just head back to our desktop for a minute
and let's take a look at the database file so we use locate with a capital S option.
We can see that actually this is changed if I save that as data base after Dr. XTi.
So here we are we've got a database before and database after if I open up a database before we see
that we have what sixteen thousand eight directories one four thousand eight hundred fifty three files
and whatever else.
Now if I try to open up afterwards we can see here that we've got this before.
Forty four thousand eight hundred fifty three files afterwards.
Under-vote four thousand eight hundred forty eight.
So it looks like some files have actually been deleted or something from the System 7 have what seven
million five in 2008 and 26 bytes afterwards.
Yeah it actually looks as though since we last updated the database some files have indeed been deleted.
So maybe there was some temporary files in operation or something like that but you can see that the
size of the database does change when you update it.
OK.
But if I do that again if I do database after two and take a look there should be absolutely no difference
between these two.
So this is day base after and I look at database after two and will see that they are actually exactly
the same.
OK.
So when you update the database it does indeed change now because the update D-B command needs administrator
privileges or root privileges in order to run.
You can see why the existing and follow options exist for the locate command so you can see why these
ones exist existing and follow them so that when you're waiting for your administrator to update the
database you as a regular user can still get on with your work even if you know you don't have administrator
privileges.
You could just get on with your work while the administrator is you know probably catching up on emails
or something pretty clever right.
So you've learnt a lot about the locate command in the past few videos.
So let's just take a quick recap of what you've learned to make sure that you've got it all.
First of all the locate command search is a database that stored on your computer for the first four
files matching the pattern that you give it returns a list of results and using a database is a very
fast method of searching but it requires that the database be updated in order to give you a complete
and correct list of results.
Now you can protect yourself against errors using the existing and follow options for the from the locate
command.
But that's not really the best solution the best thing to do is just to update the database using the
update DB command.
But this is done automatically daily as well.
Now in order to do that it does require administrative administrative privileges or privileges or super
user privileges whatever you want to call it.
And therefore you need to use the sudo command the sudo command in order to actually gain those privileges.
Enter your password and then the command is ran as the administrator.
So in order to update that base you don't just type update debug you type sudo update DBI enter your
password and then the database is up dated and then you can use the locate command from that point on
and know that your results will be 100 percent correct and up to date.
So Lowkey is a fantastically useful command and I use it all the time.
It's really quick to use but there's another command that doesn't require a database and it can actually
be way way more powerful.
It's called Find command and we'll be covering that in the next video.
So it's amazing.
It really really is cool you can do such powerful things with it in a calm way to show you.
So for all that good stuff.
I'll see you in the next video.