Hello the beautiful people and welcome to this video what you're going to be learning about one of the
most useful and most important commands on all of Linux.
The find command now the find command is used to execute sophisticated search tasks on your file system
and there is so much stuff that you can do with the fine command that we're going to break about discussion
into a few videos and in the next few videos what you're going to learn is you're going to learn how
to use the fine come and see what the fine commands default behavior is.
You can learn how to control the search depth that the find command search is on your file system.
You can learn how to search by type So how to get the file.
The find said come on to only return files or directories.
I've had to search by name so if you know exactly what you're looking for you can search by name and
how to search by file size so you can say hey fine come and find me all the files that are bigger than
5 megabytes or smaller than 10 kilobytes for example or something in between.
I'm one of the really cool things about the fine command is that once you get this big list of results
as you'll see in the videos you can execute other commands or other pipelines on each of those results.
We're going to show you how to do that and you're going to have a really powerful tool in your Linux
toolkit for manipulating loads of files at once it's going to be awesome.
So by the end in general you're going to be able to perform sophisticated search tasks with the fine
commands that that's it in a nutshell and you to want to pay attention to this section for sure because
this may be very useful for your assignment.
Hint hint.
So I hope you enjoy it.
Let's go ahead and jump over into a buntu and start playing with the find command.
All right so here we are in our home directory.
So let's just go ahead and see how the find command will work by default.
So the default behavior of the find command.
If we just go ahead and run a find is to list every single file and every single folder there is lower
down in our file system than the current folder that we're in.
OK.
And everything inside the folder that we're in.
So good because we're currently in our working directory.
If I just hit if I just type find and press and we see a big long list of every single file and every
single folder there is in our home directory and below it.
OK so it will go into every folder every hidden folder and expand and expand and expand out and list
everything.
So for example here we've got our pictures folder.
OK.
It will not just show our pictures folder.
It'll also show that we have a folder inside the picture folder called holiday.
Have a file inside the picture folder called Find Me 6 Dr. X Take for example we got our desktop we've
got find me 1.60 and our desktop itself.
Videos and videos slash find me 3.0.
So Orlistat the folders and everything side them.
And if there are folders inside those folders then it will do exactly the same.
It will go into those folders.
Expand those out and if there's other folders that it will go into those folders and expand out to an
infinite depth.
It will just go as deep as possible into your file system from starting where and starting in the current
directory.
OK.
So this is an immediate difference for us between the locate command and the find command.
So the find command will list out files and folders but the locate command will only list files and
the find command does not need a database in order to work the find command just works right there and
then so it's always up to date because it operates directly on our system it doesn't use a database.
So it's always up to date.
But the one downside of that is it's slightly slower than using a database.
So that's a tradeoff to bear in mind.
OK.
So because the find command will list every single file below where you give it you can actually also
for example give it the slash folder in the base folder for the entire system.
And this will list every single file and every single folder on the entire system.
So that's a fun thing to try if you're bored and you potentially want to smash your computer.
But you know if you give it find slash ATC then it will list everything on the system below ATC and
you can see it's giving us files and folders.
If I give it a find slash home slashes Ziyad slash documents for example it will list everything below
the documents folder.
OK so we can see that it's given us the documents folder and the find me 2.6 inside there.
OK.
And if I if I make it on documents folder if I make another folder let's call it blah blah let's just
call it that and copy and paste into there we're going to call it.
We're going to call this one.
Test DOT takes t.
OK.
Now if I do find again with the documents folder OK for home slashes Ziyad I should do this.
Do the Tilda.
OK.
What's going to happen here is you'll see that it's done the down the block folder as well and it's
gone into the folder to find test RTX take.
OK.
So it said we sold it.
Look in the documents folder it listed out find me too and it's all under the folder here called blah.
And I opened it and listed everything inside there.
If I make another folder called blah blah.
And inside there I copy and paste it so it says test to Dottie XTi.
And now I just say find everything in the Documents folder you'll see that it's also listing out blah
blah and test to find kind of searching deeper and deeper and deeper into the file system to an infinite
depth.
OK.
So that's something to bear in mind.
And it starts either with the current directory.
So I can start at the home directory which is where we are at the minute.
OK.
All you where ever you give it.
So if I'm start tell to start at the Documents folder it will start there and continually dig deeper
into the file system until it showed you every file and every folder no matter whether they're hidden
or not it doesn't matter.
So every file in every folder deeper than that point on the file system.
So just to make this clear if I go to the documents folder because I'm currently in the Documents folders
you can see by the PWT command if now I would just run the find command and because the find command
will start by default at the folder we're currently in.
If I do that you can see now that it started listing out the same stuff as up here it's side.
So with that we've got the blog folder the blog slash blah blah I am going into showing this test to
and test and find me to exactly what we were getting in our documents folder up here because we were
in the Documents folder when we ran the find command.
So you can either be in the directory that you want to start searching from or if you're not for example
we're not in the sloshy DC folder.
We can start the search from there and it will search from the EDC folder and continue to go to an infinite
depth from that point.
OK.
So that's what the find command is it doesn't use a database it operates directly on your file system
so it's a bit slower than the locate command but it's incredibly powerful.
So I think you've understood the basics of what the find command does in the next video we're going
to show you how you can customize some of its behavior starting with how you can control can control
the depth to which it searches and what it searches for.
OK.
So the find command search is from where you get it or from the current directory by default and the
next video we're going to take a look at how you can can control some of the way that it searches so
see you in the next video.