Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back we're going to be continuing our discussion of the find command and how we can control
the search depth.
The find command searches too.
So if I open up our file Explora I've made a few few new folders.
So in our documents folder I have made a folder called Level 2.
And inside there I've got a file called to text.
And then a folder called Level 3 and it's either I've got a file called 3 that he actually then Level
4 for 4.6 state level 5 and 5.10 60 where it ends.
OK and we're going to be using this to take a look at how we can control the search depth that the find
command searches too.
So all of that stuff is in our documents folder and you can see here I'm going to change into our documents
folder and use an ls and you can see that level 2 is in there.
So this is what we're seeing at the minute.
This is what we are currently in.
Like I said Clay the screen and start a discussion.
If I just run the find command from here the find command will search to an infinite depth.
It will list every file and every folder.
From this point in the file system.
OK so from here and downwards so if I run that you'll see it shows us Level 2 and it will show us everything
inside there.
So you'll see we get to up to 60 and it shows a level 3 3.6 16 level for 4.6 level 5 and 5.20 everything
is shown in there.
But we can control the depth of the come on searches too by using the max depth option.
So let me show you how we do that.
So if we type find We're going to again start from our current working directory we can actually specify
that to make it a bit clearer by using the dot by the way remember dot means this directory.
So I'm actually going to use this from now on I'm just going to always start by saying OK start from
this directory by using the dot.
OK.
So the max depth option you type 1 dash and then max depth and you can specify the depth here so let's
say we put 1.
So the first thing you might notice is Ziyad Why is that just one dash of what you said for long form
options.
These have two dashes.
Well that's right.
But for the finite amount you only have one dash for these options.
OK because so many of them the so many long form options I guess they tried to save you typing by just
reducing it to one dash.
OK.
So here we are we have just one dash max depth and then one and this is say on research to a maximum
depth of 1.
Really.
So if we see that we'll see what happens.
You see here that we only see the level 2 folder.
So a max depth of 1 is just like seeing what you see here it only shows you what is in the current directory.
OK now if I do max depth of two that's like showing you what's here and what's one level down.
OK so if we if we take a look here what we should see is we should see Level 2 and then it will go inside
and it will show you 2.6 T.
I'm the level 3 folder because if we run that Muxtape have to level 2 which is here it's showing us
the level 2 folder.
This is where we start shoguns level 2 Walda going in there.
She goes to the up to 60 and level 3.
So we see the level 2 folder to 60 and level 3.
OK.
Now if we want to go to max depth of three that's going to go down another level into Level 3.
Ok so for Rama we'll see that we see three that takes T level the level 4 folder shown as well.
If we keep going deeper we do Max up the four.
We're now starting to take a look inside level 4 we're seeing 4.6 T and the level 5 folder.
And if we do Muxtape the 5 it's going to go down even further all the way until we see 5.6.
And you can give it like you know a max depth of 100 and it will still work because all you're defining
is a maximum depth.
OK.
It doesn't mean it will go all that way.
That's just as far as it could go if it was possible.
Get there by default.
And there is no maximum depth.
So it will list everything here.
We don't have to specify a maximum depth if you wanted to go all the way into the factory but if you
want to limit how far it goes that's when you use the max depth option and you say hey I only want you
to show me what's in this folder.
That's when you use max depth of one and it's incredibly useful for listing out what's in the current
folder.
Now if we just clear the screen there's another really great option that the find command has which
is the type option.
So if we just go all the way back up to our documents here the type option allows you to search for
just files or just directories notice by default the find command lists both lists both files and directories
but the type that you specify just one.
So if I start here and in our documents folder I list everything starting this fall you see that we
list out the folders and their files.
But if I said OK I just want to list out the files what I do is type the type option with again noticing
just one dash.
And if I just want files I would type f f file.
OK.
So if I press Enter now now you'll see that we just get 4.6 take 5.6 take 3.6 D and 2.6.
We just get the files.
Likewise I could just get the folders by pressing instead of having f have D.
Like I say if I type D you know when I just get the folders so level 2 folder level 3 folder level 4
folder and the level 5 folder.
OK.
Starting at this directory here.
And you can combine this of course with the max depth option.
OK.
So if I do max depth of one now all we're doing is we're going to a maximum depth of 1 and just showing
the folders.
Now I did this on purpose to show you that if you put them this way around you'll get a warning and
it says warning you have specified the max depth option after a non option argument type but options
are not positional.
OK I'll tell you what this means shortly.
Really quickly.
OK what this means is just put max depth first.
That's what you've got to do.
And that warning goes away.
So if you're going to specify multiple options you put the max depth first if I could if I clear the
screen you'll see that warning goes away.
So I was searching to a maximum depth of one and showing all the directories.
That's go to a maximum depth of two.
When I was seeing the level 3 folder for this maximum depth for let's say not 42 max depth of four I
see three types of the maximum of three we're going to level three.
And we're seeing the level four fold up and if we go into the level four folder we'll see a level 5
folder and if we go into the level 5 go to Level 5 it won't make any difference because all that's in
Level 5 is another file which isn't being shown because all we're looking for is directory's OK.
So if I go and change that to an F..
Now you'll see we list all the files and it works exactly the same.
So these are really good options to combine together and there's loads of things that you can do to
customize the way that the find command actually searches.
But just to quickly summarize that the type option has two possible inputs you could give a F for file
or D for directory.
And if you're going to use it with the find command.
Make sure that you give it the max depth option first.
OK.
And if you're going to specify where to start from.
Make sure that comes as well so if we're going to do in ETSI folder I'm going to list every single file
in the SC folder.
Let's say but only to a maximum depth of 1.
There you are.
This is every single file that is in the ETSI folder.
And you just clear the screen and do that.
This is every single file MENC folder without any directories.
And if we just want to see the directories then here they are.
So that's a very useful combination of commands to have there.
And it will come very useful in your assignment.
So I'm going to break this video here keep it nice and short and sweet and the next video we're going
to pick up with some more awesome stuff you can do with the find command.