Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back.
We're going to be continuing on our discussion of the find command in this video by starting off showing
you how to search for things by name.
So let's say we want to find this file here called $5.60.
And we're back in our home folder.
OK we're not in our documents folder anymore we're just in our home folder and we know that this file
you've got here he is somewhere in our home directory somewhere below this point in the file system
but we're not exactly sure where and we're going to use the find command to find it for us.
OK.
So if we clear the screen let's say if we can the find command.
We're going to start from this point in the file system by the way this is just a matter of personal
preference actually having the dot.
You don't need it.
But I like to put it there just to make it a bit more complete.
OK.
So there we are find was starting in this position the file directory and we want to search by name.
So we give it the name option again just with one dash and then in speech marks so in double quotes
we want to say we were going to put the pattern that we're searching for we're going to put 5.6.
And it does need to be in quotes otherwise the find command plays up sometimes so make sure you put
in speech marks in these double quotes.
And you know that that will be that will be much better.
OK.
So if we do if we do that and press ENTER we see that the command has indeed found for the $5.60.
And it's given us the path all the way to it starting at the current working directory.
OK so what if we want to define 3.6 t that will work as well.
So is find a path to 3 up to 60.
You can build regular expressions in here.
If I put a store it will find every dot text file from this point in the file system so we see we've
got one music we've got fined me for that actually which I forgot I'd created earlier in the in the
in the course.
We've got some in some hidden folders.
We have them all over the place.
We can actually also limit the depth that we search to.
So if we go to a maximum depth of let's say to remembering that we're going to put the max depth option
as the first option.
OK.
Otherwise we get a big warning don't we.
So if I do max depth to name any name that ends in directx team will see that we found all the files
and you know two actually but only going to depths in some really really cool right.
You can search by name like that and you can also have.
You can also have wild cards so I could do file.
And then a number that takes XTi and nothing comes up.
What if I did.
What if I did something like questionmark.
Nothing comes up but if I go to a big depth of like let's say 10.
Now we see that we just get four it takes 60 5.6 a 3.6 and 2.6.
But these Find me one find me to find me four etc. are ignored because they don't match this world.
This regular expression.
So that is a really powerful ability just by building upon your knowledge of regular expressions and
wild cards.
You can really tailor the find command to your needs.
And the one thing I should note here is that you can't do brace expansion inside and inside the name
command because such is something to bear in mind.
OK.
At least at least inside double quotes.
Let's just leave it there.
OK.
So the other thing is that you can search in a case insensitive way by searching dot on name.
So if I change this here to dot THC all in uppercase I believe the screen takes an upper case that will
now match up.
I did that wrong way round.
I do like this.
Just search name.
OK.
Now you'll see nothing matches because now it's search in case sensitive.
But if I change it to name so is case insensitive searching for the name so uppercase and lowercase
don't matter now it will match because it doesn't care that this T T is in uppercase So that's good
if you're not sure why you put up a case in the file name.
It's good to search with a name to make that search just a bit more general.
Now another interesting way to search for files with the find command is by file size.
So let's say that we wanted to search the entire file system for every file that is larger than 100
kilobytes.
OK so let's clear the screen.
How would we do that.
Well what we do is we try to find code and then we need to give it of course a place to start searching
from.
So let's start from the very base of the file system because we want to find every file on the system
so let's start at the very base of the system we want to search for files that are larger than 100 kilobytes.
So let's say that we want files so let's specify a type of f..
So because we're just looking for files not folders.
I mean what size so we're going to give it a size option.
Again one dash.
And now this is how you'd say greater than 100 kilobytes.
OK so you see the plus meaning greater if it was less than you'd have minus so that's much less than
100 kilobytes.
But we want more and so more than 100 than a lowercase K for kilobytes.
So if I press Enter you'll see that we get a whole bunch of it as we look for all the files that are
bigger than 100 kilobytes starting at the very base of our file system.
But one thing you might have noticed if you had a quick eye if I scroll up to the top is that we got
a lot of permission denied errors.
If I can show you by scrolling all the way up back up there we go.
You can see that we've got a lot of permission denied permission denied permission denied.
And the reason is that's because we started at the base of our file system.
And remember the fine command would try to enter every folder but it couldn't because it didn't have
the required privileges to enter some of the folders in our base directory that are only accessible
to the root user to the super user to the Administrator account.
So to fix that we just prefix the command with the pseudo commands when it goes sudo and then do the
rest of it and we'll get a whole lot less errors.
OK because we're not going to have those access areas before.
Now we can count the results that we actually got out of this by piping the entire thing into the word
camp come on with the option.
And what this will do is it will count the amount of lines in the output that you give it.
So if you notice when we run this you get one result per line.
OK.
So if we pipe all of that into the word can't come out and give it the option this will count how many
lines.
And if we do that we get three thousand one hundred and forty four results which is a whole bunch of
results.
Now one thing that's interesting is you can train together and different sizes.
So here we're saying it needs to be greater than 100 kilobytes.
And this is how we'd say it has to be less than 5 megabytes.
OK.
So here's what we're doing is we're chaining together all these different requirements we're saying
it has to be a file and the file size has to be bigger than 100 kilobytes and the file size has to be
less than 5 megabytes.
And if we count how many of them there are we see that we get quite a few less.
Now we're going to get 3000 and 30 files instead of 3000 144 So there's about 114 files that aren't
being shown anymore because they they were bigger than 5 megabytes.
So if I click the screen one thing that I really want to highlight here is the way that we're chaining
together different requirements.
OK.
So here we're saying it has to be a file and the size has to be greater than 100 kilobytes and the size
has to be less than 5 megabytes.
In order for it to be contained in our requirements.
OK so how would we say something like OK I want to find all the files that are less than 100 kilobytes
or bigger than 5 megabytes.
OK.
Well the way that we do that.
I mean first of all if we wanted to say less than 100 kilobytes we do that and if one say greater than
5 megabytes we need to change that to a plus.
But at the minute here.
Let's see how many results we get.
We're going to get zero results because it's impossible for a file to be less than 100 kilobytes and
greater than 5 megabytes.
You can't be bigger than five megabytes at the same time that you're less than 100 gigabytes.
That's not possible.
What we want to say is it needs to be less than a hundred kilobytes or greater than five megabytes and
it needs to be less than a hundred good words or greater than 100 great and five megabytes.
The way that you do that if you type a dash 0 in between the two requirements.
So what we're saying is it's going to be a file and it's size needs to be less than 100 kilobytes or
greater than five.
So if we do that you can see now that we got a whole bunch of results.
One hundred ninety nine thousand one hundred and twelve results.
You can go quite wild with this.
This anding and oring but I think that will do.
I think that will do for now.
You can also do not and loaded all the different logical operations.
I mean if you're familiar with Boolean logic but I'll leave that up to you if you want to find more
by looking at the man pages it would be a bit of a mess to show by video.
So we've covered quite a lot in this video.
We've seen how to use the name option for the find command to search for things by name.
So you'd use Dasch name and then gave it in double quotes a certain regular expression that you wanted
file names to match.
So I could do anything ending in Dot text for example using the Star wildcard and that would give us
all the files that ended in Dot text.
And you can make the search case insensitive.
So the uppercase and lowercase don't matter by using the by using the name options and they're there
even though we have said Dotty XTi uppercase it doesn't matter because we're using the name option.
So the first thing we look to how to find files by name.
Then we took a look at how you could find files by their file size and you saw that you use the saw
option and then you give it a certain file size and the plus means above the minus means.
Below you can actually give it just exactly for example 500 megabytes that's exactly 500 megabytes.
This is above 500 megabytes.
This is below 500 megabytes a capital G.
By the way is gigabyte.
And you can find more on that in the man page for the find command.
But in the next video we're going to be doing is we're going be jumping on some very exciting stuff.
And what we're going to be showing you is how you can use the find command to not only give you a whole
bunch of results but in the same command also execute another command or even another pipeline on every
single one of those results.
This is this is a turbocharger for your work on the Linux command line and I hope you're very very excited
so let's cut the video here and jump over into the next one where we're going to learn how to gain even
more superpower's.