Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back.
Now in this video we're going to be discussing one of the most powerful features of the find command
and to be honest of the command line in general a nice how you can once you've gotten your big list
of results from the find command how you can take those results and perform another command on each
of those.
This is an incredibly powerful ability.
So I hope you're very very very excited.
So you can see here that I'm on the desktop using the PWT command.
And we're going to make a directory called copy copy here.
OK.
Noticing that I'm having an underscore to represent the space that's good practice as I've mentioned
to you before to stop a command line messing up.
OK.
So what we're going to do.
OK let's say that we want to search the entire file system for every file that is bigger than 100 kilobytes
and less than 5 megabytes.
So what I want you to do is I want is you just have a go at writing that command.
So how would you starting from the very base directory find every single file on the system and that
is greater than 100 megabytes and less than 5 megabytes.
OK.
So put that video now go have a go at it and then come back to see how you did.
How did you get on.
Did you manage it.
If you did I'm so proud of you.
That's like a technique that you're going to use so often when you work with the command line.
I'm really really proud that you've got that skill if you haven't.
Practice makes perfect don't where you get plenty of practice.
As we as you go with your assignment later on.
But this is how I go about it.
OK.
I'd use the find command starting at the base directory.
So we're going to press can type a slash.
We're going to specify that we want only files by using the type option.
We're going to say the size has to be greater than 100 kilobytes and the size has to be less than 5
megabytes.
Now because we're starting at the base directory here to make sure that our foreign command has the
ability to go into every folder we're going to prefix this entire command with a pseudo because otherwise
we get permission access errors and we don't want those.
So let's just run the whole command as the administrator.
OK.
So if we if we run that.
We're going to find a big list of results but I give in my password.
We'll find a massive list of results comes out OK.
And by the way one of these things are running.
You can actually cancel it from running any come on the command line by holding the control key and
pressing C OK.
I'm not will that will stop the the command running.
OK.
And if you know it it's taking too long will you type something wrong and you realize it and you don't
have to wait until the thing finishes.
OK but we're getting a whole bunch of results.
Actually we can tell you how many there are.
When you see see by piping into the word count Come on you can see we got 3000 and 31 results.
That's quite a lot results.
OK.
Now let's say that we want to copy every single one of those files every single one of those 3000 and
it one results that matched I find Command's criteria to this copy here folder.
OK.
How would we do that.
Well the way that we would do that is using another option if I clear the screen using another option
for the find command called the exec option or the exact option stands for execute.
And I am I'm going to do it I actually going maximize the screen and so it has a bit easier to see.
So we're saying OK once you've done the search here on each result execute something.
Now here you just type the command as you normally would.
So we'd we'd say copy because we're going to use the CPE command to copy which is you know like we normally
would.
Now if you remember how the copy command works first what you do is you say what you want to copy and
then you say where.
OK.
So you say what you want to copy and then you say where.
Well we know where we want to copy it which is going to be on a desktop.
OK.
And it's going to be in the copy here folder.
So that's our path to the copy here for us rush home slashes the slash desktop slash copy here.
We can rather the other shorter by just putting the tilde there as well that would be fine.
OK but what do we want to copy.
Well we want to copy every single one of those files.
The way to represent that is by using a pair of square squiggly brackets.
OK so you type some squiggly brackets.
And that what fills that space is every single one of those files.
Ok so in turn it will say copy whatever file one was to this directory then copy Faltu to this directory
and copy 4:03 to this directory.
So we've got all 3000 results now.
When you build out these these expressions you can have multiple of these.
You know if you needed to in your command for whatever reason but once you have created it like we have
so we're saying OK find every file that's greater than a hundred kilobytes and less than 5 megabytes.
And once you find all those execute the copy command on it and copy it to our copy here directory on
our desktop.
And then when she finished all of that to end the command you don't just press enter.
You've got to tell it when you've finished your execute option and the way you do that is by pressing
a backslash and then a semi-colon.
OK.
So you see the backslash in the semi-colon and that is the command completely finished.
So if you go ahead and run that's OK.
And we wait just a little while until our show comes back what it is doing is it is copying and pasting
every single one of those options into our copy here folder.
OK.
So I guess if I stop that for now and then close this and go to the copyright holder there we go you'll
see that we actually have every single one of those files copied and pasted into our copy here directory
or at least as many as it did before I stopped running the commands.
It's awesome but we've managed to just use the find command and not only find what we want.
On the whole system but also execute a command on each of the results.
So just as an aside depending upon what type of hardware that you're running bringing this command in
it's entirety might give your computer a bit of trouble.
So if you're finding that your virtual machine crashes just try and run the whole command to just a
maximum depth of four to save it you know finding every file on your files.
This should reduce it quite significantly the load on your computer anyway or try and maximum depth
of three.
I'm not sure that that should stop any problems if you find your virtual machine is crashing.
But first we don't want to do at the minute is just take a look at this command.
Isn't that awesome.
I mean considering that you haven't you maybe didn't know anything about the Linux command line just
a few videos ago.
Now you're looking at this command and you're probably thinking wow if I actually come that far and
this is the thing the links come on line isn't it at unbelievably complicated.
It's just a few concepts.
If they're explained to you badly or you don't quite understand what they mean it can be an absolute
nightmare.
But once you understand them it's very easy to take you know just a few building blocks here and build
something incredibly powerful.
So here you are you found a way to search for every filing system in between 100 kilobytes and five
megabytes in size and copy them all to a specific folder in just a command.
And yet now you know how to do that so I think that's amazing and I really wanted to pause in this video
just to say I'm very very proud of you for making it this far.
And you're going to get many more congratulations on this in the conclusion section 4 for this section
of the course.
Now what I want to do is I want to move on just a little bit to talk about this exact option here.
This exact option is awesome as is to execute a command but it's not the safest of all things.
OK so if you can do if is instead of using the exact option you can actually type the OK option.
OK.
And what this will do is it'll do exactly the same.
It works exactly the same you don't have to change anything.
But instead of just doing the action directly.
If I if I try this it will noce ask me every time that it tries to copy something whether it's OK or
not.
If I type y it will continue and I type Y it'll continue for time.
No it won't.
And so on.
So I have a choice here about what it does for each file.
Now this would clearly be a massive pain if you have thousands of files but it's a good thing to bear
in mind if you are doing something for a few files and you're doing something destructive like deleting
or moving files instead of just copying like in this case and you want to make sure doubly sure that
nothing goes wrong you can use the OK option.
So then the exec option in order to do exactly the same stuff.
So the OK option is exactly the same as the execute option you don't have to change anything else from
it from here on just just bear in mind that you know it's it's it's a bit safer than using the exact
option but it's you know it's a massive pain if you've got thousands of files to do.
So as I was saying I'm really really proud of you for getting as far as you have in this section in
this video.
And by the way you can cancel your way out of the O.K. option by pressing control and see like you see
I've just done here.
And of course you can clear the screen by pressing control and Al.
But what I want to do in the next video is we're going to take this to the extreme.
OK we're going to really really show you how powerful the find command can be by doing a little finding
the needle in the haystack kind of activity in the next video we're going to create a folder called
haystack that contains 500 other folders and in each of those folders we're gonna make another 100 files.
This will be very easy.
Using our knowledge of our knowledge of brace expansion.
But inside one of those folders at random we're going to create a file called needle t XTi and then
we're going to use the find command to find the needle in the haystack and move it into our home directory.
OK so out of about 50000 possible files we're going to find that one and copy it exactly where we need
and it's going to be so easy to do you won't believe it.
OK.
We can do is we'll shift over into next video and I'll see you there to find the needle in the haystack.