Hello you beautiful people and welcome back.
So let's go ahead and make our work with the find command totally extreme.
OK.
So let's just go ahead and create a folder on our desktop called haystack.
So there it is that appeared.
And what we can do in here is we're going to make five hundred folders.
Now I want to see if you can remember how to do this if you can remember how to use brace expansion
to create 500 folders that are called you know folder one folder to folder three all the way up until
folder.
Five hundred.
So go ahead and post a video now.
Try to use brace expansion to make folder one to folder 500 inside of the haystack folder and then come
back to see how you got on
Had you get on.
Did you manage it.
If so great memory.
If not don't worry.
It's been awhile.
Let's actually try and see if we can do this right where we're going to do is we want to make directory
haystack slash folder one dot dot 500.
OK.
So this is saying make folder 1 to 500 inside the haystack folder.
When I press enter and we look in haystack we've got 100 folders in there and I probably should change
the layout.
There we go.
Folder one 2 folder 500 tried to end up with your mouse and pointing and clicking it will take you for
ever.
So there we go.
We've done that now in each of those folders we need to make 100 files a hundred files in 500 folders.
That's right.
And it's actually not difficult to do at all.
So Challenge number to see if you can remember how to use the touch command with brace expansion to
create 100 files called file one file to file three all the way until file one hundred in each of the
five hundred folders.
OK so go ahead and give that a go.
And then come back to see how you did.
All right how do you do that.
I was a bit harder.
Hopefully you got it.
If not don't worry.
This is how I've gone about doing it.
OK.
So I'd use the touch command because that's what we use to create files.
And I'd say OK in haystack folder in folder one to five hundred I want you to make file 1 to 100.
OK so if I go ahead and do that we shall see that.
Inside each of these folders now we should have 100 files so there be others folder one now has for
1 to 100.
If I pick another one have folder 26 for one to 100 and so on if we go all the way down to folder 402
that's got its own 100 files.
So you can really start seeing now how powerful the shell is when you've got all these different pieces
that you can use together.
OK.
Now what we've done is we've made a folder called haystack 500 folders in each of those 100 files.
So about 50000 files if my math is all right.
So now what we're going to do is I'm going to just type something here it's a it don't worry about how
it works but I'm going to type a bit a bit of code here that's going to create in one of the run in
one of the folders.
OK.
One of the folders from one to 500 what we're going to do is we're going to find a file that we're going
to make a file called Neidl Dr. XTi.
OK.
So what this is saying is touch inside a random folder.
It can be folder 1 to 500 any random number in the file called needle that 60.
So we've created a file called needle that takes t in somewhere in the haystack but we don't know where
and it's our job now to use the find command in order to find it.
OK.
So how can we find the needle.
Let's have a think through this clear the screen and maximize it.
So let's just take a look how we might do this.
So first of all we can use the find command.
OK.
And we're going to start where are we going to start.
We probably start with the haystack folder.
OK we know it's in the haystack so we're going to start searching from that point.
And we know that it's a file right.
So we don't need to look at all the directories but remembering that the find command will by default
list out files and directories.
So we need to worry about searching through all the you know searching and returning folders let's just
look for files.
And we know that its name is Nido Dottie axium way.
OK.
So if we do that and Precentor and see if it works and it has OK it's found needle that takes the inside
folder.
Four hundred and forty nine.
How awesome is not right we've managed to find the needle in a haystack but now let's try and move it
to the desktop.
OK.
So to do that now that we've got the result we will use the exact option to execute something on it.
Now to move something.
Remember you would type move than what you want to move and where you want to move it to.
And remember of course we've got to end everything with a backslash semi-colon.
This is how you and the exec option.
So we are going to move something to somewhere that we want to move it onto our desktop.
So just put a tilter slash desktop.
OK.
So that is our desktop.
That's where we're going to move it.
And what are we going to move.
Well that file.
So we put a square set of squiggly brackets and it works the same for one file as it would for 100000.
So fingers crossed if we go ahead and do that we press enter.
And now if I just close the terminal and have a look on our desktop we've actually done it we've managed
to move needle directx t all the way from somewhere inside that haystack of potentially 50000 files
find it and move it to move it to our desktop so that's just how awesome what you've learnt in the past
few videos can be.
So what you've seen in the past few videos is that the find command is a total beast of a command.
You've seen so many so very many things with it.
But the main key point I'm just going to go through in a quick summary.
OK so the fine command can be used to execute sophisticated search tasks.
You also see how you've seen how to use the locate command and that's very good for just quick quick
like you know searches.
But if you want to do something very sophisticated find command is what you're going to want to use.
First of all it doesn't use a database whereas the locate commando's the fine command works directly
on your file system which means that it's always going to be correct but it might be slightly slower.
So that's just something to bear in mind.
And the find command allows you to build up search queries where you can search by the name of the file
the type of the thing that you're searching for the size and so much more.
OK you can see examples of those in the man page just type man then find and you'll be able to read
the manual page for the find command.
There's just so much that it can do.
OK.
And once you've got this big list of results you can use the exec option to execute another command
on each of those results.
Just remember to end that with the backslash than a semi-colon.
And if you're working with a small number of files and you're doing something potentially destructive
like deleting or removing or something like that or moving files then you know use the OK option instead.
Because then it will prompt you to say is this one OK or is this OK or is this OK and you've got to
authorize it every time.
Because that's something to bear in mind as well.
Now after what you've learned from the last few years about the find command everything else that you
can learn in the next few videos is going to seem really like a breeze.
OK so in the next video I'm going to be showing you how to open files on the command line and read what's
inside them.
And also be making plenty of kitten jokes.
So for all that good stuff.
I'll see you in the next video.