Hello you beautiful people.
And in this video you're going to begin to use the command line to move around your linux file system.
Very very exciting stuff.
Now once you learn the techniques that you'll learn over the next few videos and begin to use them for
your everyday tasks you'll begin to find that they are faster and more effective than the graphical
point and click methods that you are most likely using right now.
So in this video you're going to learn how to use the PWT and the LS commands to know where you are
and your file system and what is around you.
And by the end of the video you'll know where you are on your file system and what's around you using
the command line and you'll be ready to start moving around using some other commands that I'll show
you in the next video.
So I hope you're very very excited let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK so here we are in the terminal.
Now the first thing we'd like to know when navigating the system is where we currently are.
And the shell already tells us this over here on the left you'll see a bunch of text that is known as
your shell prompt and the show prompt is everything up to this dollar sign.
OK.
Now let's break it down to show you what each bit means.
First of all it tells you the user who is logged in which is Ziyad on this computer.
Then you can add some more.
Ok then you've got the name of the computer which is VB.
We called it when we set up and installed a virtual machine and VB is short for Virtual Box.
Then you've got a code which is these two dots on top of one another.
And then you have this squiggle that's called Tilda.
OK.
Now in the bash shell which is the shell that we're currently using that Tildy that squiggle is a short
way of representing the current user's home directory.
So whenever you see that tilde or when you see that squiggle It just means the path to the current user's
home directory.
So I show prompt is basically telling us that we are in the home directory for the current user which
we can tell is Ziyad.
OK so we can actually confirm at any time what directory or what location our shell is currently operating
in but using the PWT command and the PWT command stands we'll print working directory.
The PETER BEATTIE command will just tell us the folder that our shell is currently operating in.
So if I type PWT and I hit Enter we'll see the full path to my home directory appear which is slash
home slash Ziyad.
Now the path starts all the way from the root directory the very base directory which is the slash and
works its way down until we get to the home directory for the user Ziyad which is me.
Now we can actually see this if we click on our files and that opens up.
If you click on other locations then click on computer.
This will open us up in the very base directory.
OK this is the this is the base directory for the system.
And if I click on home up here then click on Ziyad that is where we currently are in the show at the
moment.
OK.
Now because the path starts all the way from the base directly from the slash.
It's known as an absolute path.
So now that we know where we are and we know that our shell is operating inside of our home folder how
can we take a look around and see what's in the home folder.
Well first of all we can do it using a graphical user interface we could click on our files here and
that's automatically going to open us up in our home folder and we can see the folders such as a desktop
documents downloads pictures and so on and so on.
OK now to see something similar on the command line.
We need to use the l s command now the LS is short for the list and the ls command will list of files
in a directory.
OK so if we take a look at the man page for LS The manual page for ls will see the LS can take a path
to some folders it says here.
File says list information about the files which is the current directory.
By default it was a side note.
Ls does not accept standard input so you can't pipe to it and instead you need to give it everything
as command line arguments.
That's just an aside.
Like I said let's try and use the rest of us go on to see what's going on in our home directory.
There are multiple ways to do this.
I could do it the long way and I could give it the full absolute file path.
I could type LS slash home slash Ziyad Mackerras the long way to do it all because I know that the tilda
represents my home folder.
I could give it a shortcut I could do ls and give it the tilda and that's exactly the same thing.
Matilda is just the home directory for the current user.
It's just a shocker or even better because I know ls will by default list out the contents of the folder
that I'm currently in.
And because I'm in my home folder I can just type LS Ok.
Ls will by default listo the contents of the directory that your cell is currently in.
And because we're in our home folder I can just do ls without any command and arguments.
So let's go ahead and do that.
There we go.
So in there.
Now what's come out we can see several blue words not by default blue text from the US command indicates
folders.
But to make that clearer we can we can give the ls command.
The uppercase f option.
So we put a dash in uppercase f and f is meant to mean classify a guy with emphasis on f..
OK so now when I do that for the LS at f.
Now we can see that the items that have a slash at the end of folders.
Now if I just make a file in our home directory by echoing the word hello into it.
I'm going to call it file RTX state.
So here we're using redirection to create the file there it is like you because it has been made.
If I knew don't if I now do ls dash f we can see that the folders all have Slash's after them and are
in blue.
But the file itself doesn't have a slash after it and its text is in white.
So you can see that the ls command allows us to see the difference between files and folders files and
directories.
OK.
But certainly to bear in mind is if I take that ls dash f output and put that into another file called
List Dotti x.
Ok then I open up a list RTX day.
You can see that there is no coloring but you can see the difference between folders and folders and
files just by looking for the things that end and slashes things and then slashes all the folders and
the things that don't all of the files.
So you know this is really good if you want to save information to a file and be able to tell at a glance
or make a program tell at a glance what's a folder and what's not so you can selectively operate on
specific files or not.
So just to it little shortcut.
OK.
Now a much more useful option than the f option the option for the ls command is the l option.
Now if I do ls dash l let me clear the screen first.
If I do ls dash l this puts everything in the long form format and you can tell me that we get a lot
more information about our files and directories including the file permissions over here on the left.
OK.
Anything that starts with a D is a directory.
And then this file permissions so for the user read write execute for the group the user is in the group.
Being here is this column the user is this column.
So the user read write execute for the group just read and execute no writing and for everyone else
just reading and executing.
Then you've got the user the the that the file belongs to the group the file belongs to how large the
file is when it was last edited and what the file is actually called.
OK so this is a this is the dash element is a command that you use probably very very often because
you can get a lot of information about your files much more than just using the normal ls command.
The other thing I should mention is that this column here with all the numbers in the file sizes this
shows the file size in bytes and to make that a bit clearer and you can give the ls command not only
the l option but also the hate option and the hate option stands for human readable it makes the file
size a bit easier to read.
So if we do ls Dasch El-Hage we can now see that it's telling us that the desktop thing is about four
kilobytes.
This is about four kilobytes.
This one is just six bytes.
This is ninety three bytes and these are four kilobytes if you have things that are megabytes in size
it would.
It would say an EM.
If you had things that were you know gigabytes in size it would say a G.
And in general it just makes the stuff a bit easier to read.
The case of the LS dash with the option you've got the permissions on the file.
So it begins with a D.
It's a directory it begins with a dash.
It's just a file.
The first three things are the permissions for the user read write execute the next one is for the group
that the file is in.
In this case it just has read and execute but no right.
And then this third column is for everyone else.
This is the No.
So just read and execute in that sense.
This is the amount of hard links to the file but don't worry about those.
This is the use of the file belongs to.
This is the group the file belongs to.
This is the file size in bytes.
This is the date the file was last edited and then this is the file itself.
OK so I'll make sure that the information is available on the Chichi at the end of the section.
But now you can start to see if I clear the screen.
We can now use the PWT command to see where we are on the LS command to see what's around us.
All that's left to be able to understand is how to use the CD command to actually change where we are
on the file system so that we can move about.
But I think in the interests of time we're going to save that until the next video.
So in the next we're going to be covering how to use the CD command to actually change where you are
on the file system and also be going through a few examples to see how these three commands work together
to help you navigate the file system much faster than would be possible using just pointing and clicking.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.