Love you beautiful people know in the last few lectures you've been doing so much stuff with files.
You've been you've had how to create them move them around copy them delete them paste them rename them
and search for them.
And so much more.
OK.
All from the command line.
But even though we can now manipulate files on a grand level we haven't really seen how to take a quick
peek at what's inside them and manipulate their contents yet.
Well that's what these next few videos are for over the next few videos are going to be learning five
new commands that will allow you to manipulate file contents.
So this is stuff such as reading files reversing files and even sticking files together as well as reading
them in some paging programs.
So what this is can allow you to do is to get most of your work done from the command line without ever
having to need to open up external editors which is going to be a massive productivity boost and it's
going to help you keep you inside the whole command line work process ecosystem.
So this is going to be very very you.
So it's kind of like a missing piece at the minute and after it or after the end of the next video you're
going to have to perform a whole bunch of useful functions on the contents of files which when combined
with what you know about manipulating files in their entirety is going to make you you know the farm
manipulation master.
So let's just go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So the first command that we're going to take a look at is the cat command.
Now do you remember those kitchen jokes that I was talking to you about earlier.
Well mirro So now you've actually seen the cap come on before.
So this will be a rather nice refresher.
OK so you can see here on our desktop we've got a few files.
We got 4 1 4 2 5 3 4 4 and 4 5 directx T.
So let's take a look at what's inside the first file.
But instead of opening it we're going to look in our terminal to see what's inside the file.
OK.
So if we type cat and then follow on it to be on the desktop don't I.
So I'll change the desktop I the screen and then type cat and file one text me.
OK I want to press enter.
We'll see that the contents of the file have been written to standard output.
And we can see that the file contains the word Hello.
Now if I press if I you know double click that and open that graphically we can see that yes all that
file contains is the word Hello.
OK.
So using the command we managed to get the contents of the file printed to standard output OK.
So let's try and see what's in for number two.
OK.
So if we do cat file to that takes t we can see the word there is inside.
I guess you can imagine where this is going right.
So if I go for three it says you see 4 4.
It says beautiful and I bet we can all guess what's in for number five.
So if I press 5 It says people are OK.
So if you put all the follow files together it says hello there you beautiful people.
Well what a coincidence.
I wonder how that happened.
So in fact you can actually use the Capcom and to stick files together.
OK.
And that's actually usually what it's for cat is short for the word concatenates which is a fancy word
for sticking together.
OK.
So what cat does is stick together all of the input files and then pass that stick together stuff to
standard output.
OK so if we do OK the screen if we do cat fall 1.60 Faltu that takes the fall 3.50 fall for that 60
and file 5.6 tape and press enter.
You can see that hello there you beautiful people has been made by sticking together the five thousand
that has been printed to our standard output.
But we can of course redirect this to a new file called Beautiful Dotty XTi on our desktop which we
see has been created here.
And when we open we now see that we've got a new file that says hello there beautiful people that has
been created by sticking together five other files.
Now we can actually see the holes in this command line here is quite long right.
What we can actually simplify that using our knowledge of wildcards.
So instead of having CAS for 1.60 fell 2.6 fall 3.6 for 4.6 and 5 5.6.
You can just use a wildcard like this cat together for one to five text into a beautiful server ideally
beautiful that tasty and not wild card.
And it's been created again and we can see here but yet we get exactly the same result.
Hello there you beautiful people.
But a lot less typing.
So that's pretty cool right now.
Come on when you want to stick files together like this it's useful for sticking to the text files obviously
but it can be very useful when working with Odeo or MP 3 files for example.
So if you can have multiple different single MP three files you know different songs for example but
you can actually concatenate them together stick these different files together to create one long file
that has all the music in it.
So that's pretty epic.
So the cat command is used to stick files together.
Actually if you want just read the contents of a file so we can just do cat.
Beautiful dot text.
So Cat beautiful that text and we can see the contents of any of any file which is really really useful.
But another command that I want to take a look at is the TAC command.
So let me just clear the screen here.
So the TAC command is just cat spelled backwards and it's used to reverse whatever it receives as an
input.
So if we make a file called Alpha TXI by echoing let's say ABC to our fidelity x t and we're going to
also echo DPF to Alpha and notice the way that we've got to Aros here because we're going to append
to the same file rather than overwrite it.
OK so now if I look in alphabetically we've got ABC on one line and DPF on another.
OK so if we read the file we read the file using cat with Sue cat alphabetically we get ABC then D E
F.
OK.
But I'll see what happens if we read it using tack.
So instead of cat we read it using Ptak which is the pet cat spelled backwards and we see now that we
get d f then ABC.
So you can see that the TAC command actually reads the whole file in reverse but leaves the file.
The lines the same so it just wrote the last line first and then the first line last.
Right but it didn't affect any text on each line.
So if we stick together and the various different files here the file to 4:59 using cats if we do file
wan to $5.60 you see that we get the output there.
But now I want you to think what might happen if we pipe that into attack.
OK.
Now TAC will reverse the file line wise so the last line will be printed first and the first line will
be printed last.
So what do you think might come out of this.
Take a couple of seconds I mean think about it.
So what might happen is the last line which is people would come first and the first line would come
last so what might come out is people beautiful you there.
Hello.
Like I said Have a look.
There you go yeah people beautiful you there.
Hello.
So think of the TAC command as reversing a file vertically.
OK.
So it just flips it upside down.
It doesn't affect any of the lines.
It just flips it upside down.
And of course because this is all being printed to standard output you can of course redirect it into
the file called reversed.
XTi And here we are his reverse text.
When we open up we see that we've saved the output in that file.
So the good thing about the tuck command where it can be used is again if we take the example of an
MP3 files I don't know if you've ever seen those videos online where people say aw look what the song
says when it's played backwards and like you know they try to say it's got some hidden messages in the
file.
Maybe you've seen those videos.
Well maybe they were made using the tax command because if you run an MP 3 fall through through the
tax months if I did something like tack my father in P3 and save that into another my reversed file
time p 3 then this file.
This one here will be the same song but played backwards.
Like I said something to potentially give a go if if if you would like.
OK so that's the tack.
Come on the Takamine will reverse files vertically.
There's one other that I want to look at which is called the Rev command.
So the command allows you to reverse the content on each line.
So if I clear the screen OK and we cut together the various different files again we get hello you beautiful
people.
But if I pipe that into the Rev command OK.
Look what happens here.
It's still saying if you can read it it still says hello there beautiful people so the lines are vertically
the same but horizontally they've been reverse so the last letter of each line so here is the O.
Has now become the first letter.
And you know it's reverse them along the lines but the order of each line is the same.
If that makes sense if we if we put the the attack command you can see that people is the first line
whereas here people is the last line but the letters have been reversed.
OK.
So this is the way you can think of ref and tac tac reverse as a file vertically and rev reverses a
file horizontally.
OK.
Now you can really jumble up files by piping it through both of them.
So if I pipe it through Takk it's going to reverse vertically.
But then if I pipe that also through Rev you've now got a vertically reversed and horizontally reversed
fire which is a good way of jumbling up stuff if you ever find that particularly useful.
But yet just to make it easier just think of tack as reversing phials vertically in columns and you
can think of Rev as reversing falls horizontally across the rows.
So all of these commands whether it be cats or it be Takk or a be you know Rev all they're doing is
they are taking a file reading it into standard input doing some processing and then you know just spitting
that the output to standard output.
Like I said they're a good way walk that is a good way of reading files and you know the others are
a good way of jumbling up stuff.
But the problem is when you read files to the terminal like this if a file is particularly long it can
readers clog up your screen and it's not very useful and you find yourself scrolling a long long way.
So if we try to find a file that's quite large so if we say for example let's use the find command search
our system up to let's say a maximum depth of four.
We're going to go too far for any configuration files or a name that ends in dot com.
And the size that lets say over 20 kilobytes.
OK so we are we only get we only get two really.
But there's one here called cops browes dot com.
And this is to do with like printing services.
And it's apparently a lot rather large file.
So if I copy it.
Copy that and try to catch it.
OK.
So if I try to cut that it up.
So you see it just happened right there if I try to cap that and press enter.
You see that we've just shot down.
She put him out of lines.
Can you see now.
If I wanted to have a look at it and I ended up scrolling all the way through here it's not very good
right.
So that's a problem when you're dealing with stuff on the command line and we want a more elegant solution
to dealing with relatively large files.
And sometimes you know if I if I just wanted to read out of how maybe I don't want all of the farm maybe
only want a certain snippet of it maybe I only want the top 10 lines or the bottom 10 lines or something
like that.
And we need to have a better way of being able to deal with file contents on the command line.
So in summary So what we're going to be covering in the next video but in summary of this video we've
seen that they can't come and can be used to actually read out files.
If I look beautiful on our desktop if I read how beautiful that he actually can read that out if we
want to reverse files vertically we can use Takk if we want to reverse files horizontally we can use
Rev and but all either way all of these are what they're doing is they are just reading the files content
and spitting out the standard output where you can then of course pipe it into other commands to do
the processing.
OK.
Or you know while you're working on the command line if you just want to see quickly what's in a file
you can just you can just use cats come at the cat command and then see that really quickly and get
on with what you were doing.
OK.
So there we are though does the cat tack and ref commands but in the next video we're going to take
a look at how you can level up this ability to do more sophisticated things so I'll break the video
here and see you in the next video.