Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back.
So in the last video you learned how to open files and read their contents by using several command
line commands So for example the cat command will open up a file and allow us to read its content.
So if we use for a 1.60 we can see that it contains the word Hello.
And when we open files like this what happens is everything is shown all at once.
So no matter how long the file is it will all be spat out right into our terminal and that can be kind
of pain.
So for example if we try to open up a really long file such as the file that I showed you in the last
video which has something to do with printers and stuff on your system.
So if I typed that in so cops browsed dot com.
OK.
And I try to print.
You can see that we've just shot a whole bunch of information.
And if we want to read it we've got to scroll up and down like this right in our command line.
It's a bit of a pain right like this not really a nice way.
You want to be able to deal with the long files.
So to help with this there are programs on Linux called pager programs that allow you to page through
large output to make it easier to read.
And the one that we'll be covering in this video is called the last command.
So if we just do instead of cat if we do less and then give it the father we want to read you can see
now what's happening is we are we sorted first of all at the top of the file and by just using our keyboard
keys or arrow keys up and down we can scroll through this content and read it and bicycling up and down
a lot easier than if we had it just on the command line and if I press Q You can see it on the bottom
Hey we got these two colons if I type q it closes.
And they were back on.
Come on my with no mess that we have to scroll through.
So that's a nice way of doing it.
And actually you can pipe to the last command so instead of opening it directly about I could use that
to open the file and then pipe into the last command and it will give us the same result.
Now this ability to pipe to the last command is incredibly useful because it doesn't just have to be
files that you are that you are dealing with.
For example if I said OK let's come into our into our home directory and let's find all the text files.
Ok so we're going to find by name everything that ends in Dot TXI.
OK.
And we see that we get a whole bunch of information here and this could be quite long.
It could it could be quite a lot of stuff.
But what we're going to do is we're going to instead of that actually the end of just attacks is to
try and find everything OK it's printed out a whole bunch of stuff that we've got to scroll through.
Instead of that we can just pipe it into less.
And now we can scroll through line by line.
So this last comment is a really useful one when working with the command line because it saves you
from having a lot of mess filling up your screen.
OK.
And piping to it is is really really really useful.
The cases that we can to rescue and all the mess has gone now.
Sometimes you don't want the whole hour or the whole file and you only want to operate on a piece of
it.
OK so perhaps you want to take a little piece from a file and pass it through your pipeline instead
of having the whole file on your screen and you just want to peek at a little piece before getting on
with your work.
So for this purpose we can use the head and the tail commands that the head command will allow you to
see a little piece of the file starting at the top or the head of the file and the tail command will
do the opposite.
It would like to see a little piece of the file starting at the bottom or at the tail of the file.
OK.
So for example let's concatenate together the following files again I'm going to get to our desktop
and clear the screen and I'm going to cut together files oops clips being kept together files one to
five.
OK.
That takes two.
And we see that we get five rows out.
OK.
Now if I just pipe this into the head command we just get the same output.
So why is that.
Well that's because the head command were by default so we the first 10 lines of a file and since there
are only five we'll see it all but we can edit this behavior by specifying how many lines that we want
to see.
So if I just press the barricades to get what we want I can give the the hate speech that had come out
of the option and specify how many rows we want to see so we're just going to see the first two lines
and you'll see that we go we just see Hello in there the first two lines of the output.
Now the head command is very useful in pipeline's again.
Let's say we were doing the find command and we're back in our home directory and we run the find command
we get a whole bunch of output and let's say you just wanted the first five of these options you can
just pipe it to the head command give it an option and say Hey I just want five lines.
Let me press enter.
And you see there we go we get the first five results and then you can take those and pipe them down
down the then the pipeline for whatever reason you wanted.
So maybe I wanted to you know then Paso's into the task command and reverse the order that they're in
or whatever it might be.
OK.
So that's a really useful application of the head command that works the same for the tail command but
the tail command will show you from the bottom rather than from the top.
But I want to show you that actually you don't need to just pipe to the head come on you can operate
directly on files.
So we had that really long fall didn't we we had it was slush at C cups cups browsed dot com.
And you see we got this really really long file.
Now if we can actually see how long that is by piping that to the word count command and giving it the
option like you've seen a bit earlier in the course you can see we've got 673 lines that's quite a few
lines.
But what if we just want the first 20 lines with a set of piping it.
We don't have to do that.
What we can do is we can just say head get the option of the first 20 and then give it the foreigners
operate directly on and we will get just the first 20 lines and we can confirm that we do indeed have
20 lines by pressing the up arrow key here and piping right to the word count command with the option
to count the amount of lines and we'll see that up.
We do now only have 20 lines of output.
So that's perfect.
Now the tail command works basically the same way as the head command except it starts from the bottom
of a file.
So if we do our casting again we get back to the desktop and we Cateau file 4:59 docked here.
And we'll see that yet we get hello you beautiful people.
And if we pipe it into the tail commander and say we just want the bottom two lines then we'll just
get beautiful people.
So the bottom two lines.
OK.
And if we again we're operating on the really really long file so instead of having cash instead of
having head let's have tail get rid of this word count at the end.
Now if we if we press ENTER you can see that we just get the bottom 20 lines and we can again pipe that
into word count and see that yes we do indeed have 20 lines.
So head and tail to cut either the top of a file or the bottom of a file respectively to control exactly
what you want.
And you can use these together to kind of filter out specific lines.
OK.
So let's say we did let's go back to our head example and let's say that we cut out the first 20 lines.
These are the first 20 lines of that big long file.
And then if I pipe that into the tail command and Gates said OK give me just one line from the bottom.
OK then this blank here is going to be the 20th line of the file.
Maybe it's not that exciting let's say if I get say three OK.
That's going to give me lines 18 19 and 20 of the file.
And you can use the commands in this way to cut out specific lines.
OK so that's that's quite a useful combination right there.
But really where these things come into coming to their real use is when you are building your pipeline.
So the example I've been using and leaning on is the find command because it gives us a lot of output
but you know if you wanted to just get a specific set of lines say I wanted the last three lines I could
just pipe those into the tail command and just say OK just give me the last three lines and then continue
to pipe that down or even export it lets say into export the text on our on our desktop and then you
can save up and keep just the lines that you want rather than having to have a whole bunch of output
that you don't need.
OK so it's like a filter.
The head and Turkomans are best seen as filters that allow your pipelines to get you just what you want
to work with.
So we've got quite a lot of stuff in the past few videos right.
But fortunately none of it is particularly complicated but it's all very useful.
So as a quick recap you've seen how to join files together or concatenate files using the cat command
which is a great tool for not only joining forces but also allowing you to take a false content and
putting it right into standard output so that it can be used in your pipelines.
You've also seen how you can reverse files vertically.
So using the TAC command and you've also seen how to reverse files horizontally across their lines using
the ref command and using both of those together is a real good way to jumble up your files.
Now some files that you want to read are very very long and just viewing their contents with the Capcom
and for example is a bit of a mess and it gives you a lot of stuff you've got to scroll through.
So you saw how to use the less command to page through massive amounts of output or large files from
the command line without needing to make unnecessary files just to view the output and piping from commands
to the last command is a great way to keep your terminal tidy and make your workflow more effective
and just make dealing with large amounts of data a lot easier to handle.
And finally you saw how to use the head and tail commands to cut out just what you want from a file.
And you know if you would like then pass it straight on down your pipeline.
So these are really really useful tools that will come in handy quite often when working with file content.
So now you not only know how to manipulate files as a whole so copy a whole file move a whole file delete
the whole file but now you know how to operate a bit more on their contents.
But there's so much more that you can do with file contents and simply just looking at them or sticking
them together.
So in the next video you're going to learn how you can sort a command files contents either alphabetically
or numerically and being able to sort content's is super useful.
It makes finding what you're looking for easier and works perfectly alongside commands such as the head
and tail commands that we've seen in this video to make really powerful combinations forgetting just
what you want out of a file.
So this is going to be epic sorting files is just a really really useful ability.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.