Hello The Beautiful People are welcome to this video.
We're going to be learning about the super useful sort command and now the sort command is one of those
commands that you can kind of use anywhere to sort data and make it more ordered and easier to manage.
And over the next few videos I'm going to be showing you how you can use the sort command to sort data
in a variety of different ways and also be showing you some use cases of when this can be really useful.
And we'll be building a superpowerful pipeline that will allow us to sort data in tabular format.
So by the end you're going to be amazing at sourcing data and really going into something of how to
use the sort command to sort data in Linux no matter where no matter whether it's text numbers modified
numbers or even in tables.
Ooh.
So this is going to be a very useful section of the course.
Let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So the first thing I should probably say is that I've put three files on my desktop I've got words not
text me which contains 100 random words sorted in no particular order they're just 100 random words
that are just in that file.
We've got the numbers 0 to 9.6 T which is a file that has loads of numbers and nothing 100 numbers each
between 0 and 9.
And we've also got this other file here called Numbers top tier XTi which is I think another 100 random
numbers but they do they're in no particular range and they're just 100 random numbers with no specific
limits on them.
And I've made these files available in the resources section as well as some information about how I
created them so you know if you want to grab those you know try this stuff out for yourself then you
know you can go ahead and download them and give it a go.
OK.
So let's start off by taking a look at these words Datti XTi which is the file that contains 100 randomly
generated words.
And as I said like if we just open them up again it's just got 100 random words in there in no particular
order no particular just 100 randomly generated words.
OK.
So first of all how can we sort that file so that it's sorted alphabetically so everything that starts
with an A is at the top and if that starts with Zed is at the bottom.
Well that's actually the default behavior of the sort command which is the perfectly named command for
this kind of thing.
So it's really simple to use as well if we just type sort words not here.
But we've now got a list of sorted of sorted words from eight years and so you can see that all the
words start with a or at the top and all the words that start with why are at the bottom and it doesn't
look like we've got anything that starts with Zed So they've all been sorted alphabetically so that's
pretty cool.
And of course we can write the standard output to a file or you know to a T command and we can use that
as well.
Ok so like you know we could say say another the here called sort of dotty XTi and that's going to be
put there and we can pipe it down the pipeline that you know it's just written on standard all the same
rules apply.
So what if we wanted instead of sorting it out.
What if we wanted to sort it in reverse.
How would we sort.
So Zed was at the top.
Well two options come to mind.
First of all what you could do is you could just sort the words like just like normal.
But then Python into the TAC command.
And as you can see here what's happened is the letters that there was a start with a are now at the
bottom and the words that start with close to Zed are now at the top.
And the reason for that is that as we know the TAC command will sort of flip outputs vertically.
So what would be at the bottom is now at the top and what was at the top is now at the bottom.
So that's effectively as though we've just reversed the sorting right but a better way to do it up I
suppose a more built in and efficient way to do it would be to just give the sort command the option
and the option stands for reverse.
So if I do that we can see again we've got the letter saw him with a toss of the word starting with
a towards the bottom sorry and the words starting with close to Zed are now at the top.
Now you may notice that when I'm showing you this output that I'm scrolling up and down the shelves
quite a bit.
So this is where the last command would come in I could just pop into a less command to make the output
a bit easier to view because now I'm using the arrow keys instead of scrolling with my mouse pad.
So that's you know a bit of a nicer way to deal with things in a press Q to come out of that.
So it's building upon what we did before.
So awesome know is how you have you now have enough building blocks that you can solve the same problem
in multiple ways.
You know that you could now use the option to reverse it or if you didn't want to do that.
You could also pipe it into the top.
Come on.
This is one great thing about Linux.
It gives you multiple different ways to solve the same problem because you've got so many different
building blocks so there's plenty of room for creativity in the way that you approach these problems
as no necessarily one right way to do it.
So there we are now how about sorting numbers.
Well I have a list here of 100 numbers called Numbers Datti Eckstine.
If we take a look there's a 100 numbers in there that don't have any particular size limit.
They can be any number but there's 100 of them.
OK.
So how would we sort those.
Well sorting with letters so sorting out is Ed sorting alphabetically is different from sorting numbers
which is sorting numerically.
So if we try to do sort numbers start s t like that you say it didn't really work that well what kind
of happened here is if you if you notice that we put this into the last command so we can make it a
bit easier to see all the numbers.
It started with one.
I've come to the top and then it kind of you see now we get in all the numbers that start with two we'll
get in on numbers that start with three and so on.
OK.
But we're not four five six seven eight nine OK you can see it's sorting by the first digit but it's
not sorting by the value of that number.
For example 160 sixteen thousand twenty nine is much bigger than 1641.
So why is it above it right.
There's no real sense of the size of the number.
It's just the fact that it starts with a number 1 and it's sorting numerically as it goes sorting and
as it goes along by just looking at the numbers it's not looking at the value of the numbers just looking
at the digits.
But if you want to sort using the value of the number you need to give the sort command the an option.
So the option allows it to sort numerically maybe take a look at that.
Now you can see that we're getting the smallest numbers at the top so we're starting with 123.
And then what the numbers are getting bigger as they go down.
So that's something important to bear in mind sorting just by the digits is different than sorting by
the value of the whole number.
And if you want to search the value of the whole number you need to give it an option.
And of course you can reverse this so that the biggest are at the top by using the giving the option
as well for reverse.
So now we see that the biggest numbers are at the top and as we scroll down the numbers get smaller.
So it's very very nice.
So you've seen how to sort and text alphabetically and you've seen how to sort numbers numerically but
one thing that's very useful is to only show unique results rather than the same result over and over
and over again.
So we've got a file here called numbers 0 to 1960.
I mean that is 100 rows of data but only the rows only contain one of the numbers from 0 to 9 so you'll
necessarily have some duplicates.
For example here we've got 0 0 0.
OK.
It's not just unique results there are results that are repeated.
So if we take a look in here and we try to sort the which are the sort saw numbers 0 to 9.6 it is piped
into last.
You'll see that all the zeros come first then all the ones and all the twos and threes and fours the
fives the six the seven eighths and the nines.
OK and that's that's a bit annoying.
Ok maybe we just want to just have the results once.
Well to do the what you do is you give the sort option sort Kamandi you option and the option stands
for unique.
And when you do not know you'll see that we only get the results once.
OK.
So let me just set up nine to less.
There you go.
You can say you only get the results once 0 to 9.
This is useful sometimes you don't want to have the same result repeated over and over over again.
You only want the results to appear once and that's when you would use the you option which allows you
to sort of uniquely.
And of course this still works with other options such as the reverse which you know now we're sorting
backwards and you can still sort numerically and whatever else you might need to do.
But that's just how you can make sure that you only get each of the results once.
So in this video you've had a bit of an introduction to the sort command and you've seen that you can
sort data using the sort command.
Now the command tends to sort smallest first so it'll tend to sort from a to Zed or from 0 to 9 by default.
Ok but you can reverse this by using the options so there are options for reverse.
And if you're ever sorting numerical data and you want the sort going to take into account the actual
value of the number rather than just the digits that it contains then make sure that you give the sort
on the an option to allow it to sort numerically.
And if you only want to get unique results out of the sort command provide it with the you option which
will filter out just the results that appear once.
So that's what we covered in this video.
But in the next video we're going to take it to a next level and show you some advanced sorting techniques
that will allow you to sort data that comes in table format.
So I'm also going to be building a really cool pipeline that will do some of this as well.
So let's just go ahead and get right into it in the next video and take your sorting skills to the next
level.