Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back.
Now in this video we're going to be discussing how you can take your sporting abilities to the next
level by looking at how you can sort data that is in tabular format so data that comes in tables by
showing you how you can sort of open down various columns.
Now this is super cool because it means that you can do all this kind of data sorting right from the
command line you don't need to open up a spreadsheet software.
You can do it right there in the terminal and save all that juicy juicy processing power.
So let's go ahead and jump right into it and see how this works.
All right so sometimes you get a lot of data out of your commands.
And one example of this is the ls command with the l option so the LS dash L command.
So for example if we did the on the ETSI folder.
So this is the fall that contains all of the system configuration files and you can see that we just
get a whole bunch of results.
It's like you just get loads and loads and loads of stuff coming out of that.
OK.
But you know just to make this a bit easier to see let's just pass that into the head command and get
the first 20 lines.
And that we are there the first 20 lines of output.
OK so what if we wanted to sort this data by the column.
So what if we wanted to sort by certain columns you can actually do that in the sort command using the
K option.
So for example if we wanted to sort by now I guess this column which is about the file size is so you
see this one here that this column is all about file sizes so maybe want to sort by date for example
and we wanted to sort by date which would be these few columns or whatever.
You can do all that in the sort command.
So let's just see how we might go about doing this.
So how we do it if I just clear the screen is you'd pipe it into the sort command all the data into
the sort command and you give it the k option.
Now after the K option you need to tell the sort command how to sort this input using what the sort
command calls a key definition or a key def.
OK this is all in the man page by the way.
But let me show you how it works.
First you tell it what column it should sort by.
OK.
So if I just scroll up a little bit you can see our results that we got before.
We want to sort by the column with these big numbers here.
OK.
Now those numbers as I said are actually file sizes in bytes.
So let's say we want to sort of files from largest to smallest.
OK so first we need to give the key def the column number we want to sort by say if we count here's
column 1.
So that's one column too that's column 3.
That's column 4 and that's column 5.
OK so the column number is five.
So if we come back to I know.
Come on I'm going to type 5.
OK.
Then you need to tell it and then you basically can pass it.
Any other options that we like.
For example if we want to sort numerically we would type an AK and you can pass any options you like
so if you wanted to sort reverse you type in awe there as well just like you've seen in the last video
you wanted unique type of you and that's it.
That's how you make your key definition of let's just have the end for now.
So what we're saying here is a ok listo everything that's in the Anssi folder take the first 20 lines
and then sort it by the fifth column.
OK.
And when we press Enter we'll see that yes actually the data has been sorted by the fifth column you
can see that we're starting with the smallest files first.
I'm working all the way up until the biggest.
But actually we wanted it the other way round didn't we we wanted the biggest files first.
So if we wanted to make that happen we'll just type in are there.
So we're saying sort numerically but in reverse order.
So largest to smallest instead of smallest to largest.
Remembering that the sort can by default go small to big.
Now we're going big to small.
So when we do that we see that yep.
Now we're starting at big four thousand ninety six and getting smaller as we go down.
So that's supercool right like we've just taken a big set of data and sorted it by columns which is
an amazing ability to be able to just do from the minute we didn't have to open anything like Microsoft
Excel.
We just sorted the data straight from the command line.
But one thing that you might notice especially with the LS output is that these file saw these file
sizes are kind of hard to interpret right.
These are all in bytes and I don't know about you but I tend to read things in kilobytes or megabytes
or some of them either I don't tend to read it directly in bytes.
So as you know the ls command has an option that allows you to read that you know to give the data in
human readable format.
So if we do that with a human readable format you can see now that what's happening is we're getting
it setting up the amount of kilobytes that said this is for kilobytes focalize we'll get about three
kilobytes 2.2 kilobytes and then the rest are just in bytes and it would say megabytes gigabytes whatever
it was for files that we're dealing with.
So it's the hate option for the ls command that gives you human readable output but you may have noticed
this is just completely messed up.
Assorting right.
It's just like before we were sorting perfectly like we were sorting biggest are the top smallest at
the bottom.
But now it's just doing whatever it wants.
And the reason is the saw come on when you tell it to sort numerically with the option.
That's a completely different thing to sorting with human readable data.
OK.
So to make it actually sort with human readable data you need to give it the option you said and you
give it the option and you can't have both at the same time.
OK so finally the screen and instead of having the option we now have the page option and we press enter.
Now you can see that it's working and we're getting the largest sizes of the top and the smallest at
the bottom while still getting the data in human readable format so we get the best of both worlds really.
So remember if you want to sort by human readable data you need to give the sort command the hate option
in its key def or just in general if you've only got one column to deal with.
But here we had to add a key there.
So we type the option there.
Now you can also sort by month.
So let's see how we might sort by this column here which is all about you know the date and the the
file was last edited.
So let's clear the screen.
Let's take a look.
So we're saying print out a list for us in long form format with human readable file sizes.
Everything in the ETSI folder was just the top 20 lines and sort for us by the Fifth Column human readable
reversible.
I got it reversed.
Well actually the date is the column after this one so we need to have instead of the fifth column we
want the sixth column.
So we're going to do it in our code if we're going to change the 5 to 6 and instead of human readable
which is going to put a capital M K that this is going to allow us to sort by month.
And if I press Enter now you can see that yes we have indeed sorted by month and we got January at the
top and we've got then may August and then October coming all the way down the bottom so that's really
really cool right.
You can also as well combine this with ops you can combine it with reversible by putting an R in there.
And now we'll find out if I clear the screen and again you see that October is at the top and now January
is at the bottom.
So.
So there you go.
Like once you understand these several different options it's really not that much more difficult to
sort by certain columns all you've got to do is sort it's just in the kida tell it which column that
you want.
Now here's a challenge for you.
I want to see whether you can tell me how you might sort by this column.
So that's the you know the smallest numbers come first.
OK.
So how would you sort by this column which is Yoshino has these numbers here.
How would you sort by that column so that the smallest number was were first go ahead.
Pause the video videos now and then come back to see how you did.
How did you get on.
Did you manage it.
Well if he did well done really really quick learning his highway would have gone about doing it at
that time.
So what I do is we keep everything the same.
LS El-Hage with the ATC taking out the top 20 lines and now the only difference is Akki death.
OK.
So the first question would be the k option 2 the sort command What's the first question is what's the
column number where the code number.
This is the first column.
This is the second column right.
So let's put two and we want to sort this numerically.
Right.
So we're going sort of numerically now by default the sort command was saut smallest first right.
So that means we don't have to reverse anything.
It will start with the smallest number first by default if I clear the screen and try that.
Now we see that it has been sorted by this column with the smallest numbers coming first.
If we wanted to reverse that we just give it the an option and it would reverse that.
So now you're getting the eights at the top and the and the.
And then the smallest numbers the ones down the bottom.
So there's loads of different ways that you can you can do this.
But there you are.
That's that's how you would use the sort command in order to sort data in columns and in as usual one
thing that I should note is here we're having an R.
It doesn't matter if I wrote that or in and it doesn't matter at all like what order you write stuff
in these key definitions.
Just think of them as normal options that you just put right there in the key definition so order doesn't
matter.
So we've covered a whole lot of stuff in the last two videos about sorting data and in this video we
took a look at how you would saw data that is in a table format using the command line.
And so the key to this was to use the sort command with the k option.
Now you need to give the option something called a key def and a key that follows like this kind of
structure.
So first you'll give it a number and that number is the column that you'll sort by.
So for example we have the number three here and that means sort using column 3.
Then after that you can give it any other options that you want like you've seen in the last video for
example you could give it the option to sort numerically and the option to sort in a reverse manner.
So largest to smallest instead of smallest to largest and so human readable data you'd use the hate
option not the an option.
And those are incompatible you can't use both at the same time.
So if you've got human readable data then use the hate option instead of the an option.
Like you saw with the ls command that we used in this video and you can also sort using months using
the capital M option and because the Sort commands sort smallest to largest You will find that January
comes first and then December comes last.
But of course you can reverse that using the option as well and the order of options in the key def
don't matter.
As usual just like you were entering them normally on the command line it doesn't matter if you put
in and then or instead of R and then and it doesn't matter the order but just make sure that you don't
have incompatible options such as the numerical sort and the human readable sort.
At the same time because that won't work very well.
So you now know how to sort data using tabular sort tabular data using the command line and now you
should be really the master of sorting data using the command line.
So Welden you.
So in the next video what we're going to do is we're going to take a look at an incredibly versatile
command called the grep command.
Now because one thing that is super useful when working with the command line is being able to search
through data to find what we are looking for.
OK and pick out just the bits that we're interested in the grep command has got to be one of the most
commonly used commands of all time and it's going to be such an awesome addition to your Linux toolkit.
You've probably already come across in some form or some form or another if you've ever done some you
know searching around on the internet for anything to do with Linux you probably come across the grep
command.
So I can't really wait to show you this and show you how to use it properly.
So if all that good stuff I'll see you in the next video.