Hello you beautiful people know when you're using files or when you're using data from standard output
it's very likely that you won't want all of the data but rather you just want a specific piece of it
and you'll want to cut out all the rest.
Now the way that we do that in Linux is using a command called the grep command.
And if you've ever searched about Linux on your own maybe just been you know using a search engine having
a look around you'll know that I've already come across the group come on just how useful it is.
So in the next few videos we're going to be showing you how you can use the grep command to search through
files and standard output so that you can filter out just the data that is important to you.
And by the end of the next few videos you're going have a very powerful new tool that will allow you
to do what you want much faster help you find things in data much faster.
And we help you cut out a lot of the fluff that you don't want so that you can get the results that
you want.
So let's just go ahead and get right into it.
OK.
So as a quick heads up the first thing I want to talk about is what the grep command actually does.
OK before we start discussing how it works.
So the grip command will search whatever input you give it for lines that contain a particular piece
of text that you tell it to search for.
OK.
So for example I have a file here called haloed optics on our desktop.
And if I head over to the desktop and use the cat command to take a look at what's inside it.
Surprise surprise it says hello there beautiful people with each word on its own line.
Now let's use the grep command to find all the lines in there that contain the letter e.
OK now the way that we do that is we would type grep.
Then what we're searching for.
So the letter A.
And then what we're looking in.
So we'd say hello dot text.
Ok so here what we're saying is hey grep find every line in Hello dot text that contains the letter
E and now by default the grep command is case sensitive.
So uppercase and lowercase do matter.
OK so if I press Enter you'll see here that we're seeing the lines that contain the letter E and even
the letters themselves have also been highlighted.
So that's pretty cool.
Now interestingly in 1939 there was a person called Ernest Vinson right who wrote a novel called Gadsby
that was about 50000 words long.
Now the special thing about Gadsby was that even though it was 50000 words long.
Not once was the letter he used it was not incredible especially if you consider that the letter E is
apparently the most commonly used letter in the English alphabet.
So that's really quite an achievement to write a 50000 word book like a story without using the letter
A.
And I just so happen I don't know how this happened to have a copy of Gadsby here in this randomly created
folder on our desktop called Gadsby right here so we want Gadsby manuscript Dotti XTi.
Now the book is so old now that it's freely available in the public domain and you can get access to
it to using the link that I'll put in the resources.
Now Anyway the reason for this is that we can use the come on to count the number of lines a certain
piece of text appears.
OK.
So for example we see that when we search for the letter E in Hello 0.60 we get four results right.
So we get hello there beautiful people.
OK.
So we can actually confirm this we can take a look by giving the rep come on the C option and this will
tell you how many lines it'll just give you the number of lines that it finds and it tells us that we
get four.
OK.
So it says hey I found four lines that had the letter E in them in Hello T S T.
Now we have the text file called Gadsby manuscript Dottie XTi.
OK.
And if we open it you can see that there is so much stuff in here.
Is the fact the book is about 43 chapters long with over 50000 words and actually I can tell you how
many lines is in there by going into the Gadsby folder and using the word count with the command on
the Gatsby manuscript and tells us that it tells us that there's one thousand nine hundred and fourteen
lines which is quite a lot of lines.
OK so let's try and search for the word Gadsby in the book Gadsby because if I do grep Gadsby inside
Gadsby manuscript Dottie XTi you'll notice that nothing shows up.
And the reason that nothing shows up is because Gadsby starts with a capital G and we spelt it with
a lowercase g here.
Now we can search in a case insensitive manner.
So the uppercase and lowercase don't matter at all by giving the group command the option.
OK so when we do that we'll see that it shown us it shown us a different amount of results here and
there's quite a few times that Gadsby has appeared in the book.
Gadsby has as clear the screen.
You can also search for the letter A in the Goldsby book just by putting the letter A here and we'll
see that we get a whole bunch of lines where the letter A is used.
OK.
And we can count that as well if we want by pressing the C option and we see this 951 lines that contain
the letter.
So that's quite a lot.
So now let's try and see how many times the book uses the letter.
OK so that we do that is we don't care whether it's uppercase or lowercase we don't want any e's.
So we're going to keep it case insensitive.
And would it count how many lines there are.
And we're going to put there the latter.
And if we go ahead now and press ENTER we can see that the answer is zero.
So the Gatsby manuscript doesn't use the letter E and this has been approved Linux approved that it
doesn't use the letter.
So download the manuscript in the resources section and try it out for yourself.
Now you can actually also search for full sentences as long as you surround them in quotes.
So one phrase that is quite a bit in the book is the is the line our boys so we could search in there
for boys and we're going to put that in quotes to make sure it goes in as one argument.
And when we press ENTER you can see those nine lines that contain it but let's just take a look as well
to see them so you can see there's quite a few results for the text.
Ah boys.
Now you can also search for lines that don't match a specific piece of text.
OK.
So you can see how many lines there are in the whole Gatsby document using the word count commands if
I do a word count dash l Gad's B manuscript in 1914 lines right now because there's no letter E in Gadsby.
There should be 1914 lines without the letter H.
Right now we can check that using the V option.
Now the v option basically does the opposite or invert the search.
OK so if we do grep with egrep with the v option for.
E A K in Gadsby manuscript Dotti x t.
What we're doing is we are trying.
This is going to find all the lines that don't have the letter E in them.
Like I said without the V you will find all the lines that do have e in them and with the v option you'll
find all the lines that don't have the letter V in them so let's do that.
So we saw a whole bunch of stuff has come out.
But how many of them how many of them have actually come out.
Well we can count them using the C option and I'm going to court I'm going to cut it right now.
Will it be 1914 lines will Gadsby actually contain no letter.
Oh what a save on time.
Come back in the next video to find out.