Welcome back ladies and gents I'm sure the anticipation has been killing you.
So here we are we're trying to find out whether Gadsby does in fact use the letter e.
Now Gatsby is 1914 lines long.
So if by using this command here we get the answer 1914.
Then we know that every line doesn't contain the letter.
OK so let's go ahead and press enter.
Let's see if we get 1914 lines just like we expected.
And the crowd goes wild.
So there we are.
Yep.
The the group commanders manage to work that way as well.
We got the same answer both ways.
Now you can use the grep command to search inside multiple files at once.
By the way.
OK.
So I have I have a file on the desktop don't I called haloed RTX States if I just head back to the estop
a little bit and Katta out it says hello.
There you see it for people and surprisingly.
Now if we wanted to compare the literary genius of my haloed optics the fall and the Gadsby manuscript
then we could use GRABBE dash.
I would search for the letter E inside the Gatsby manuscript so that's going to be in the Gadsby folder.
Gatsby manuscript on my Hello textfile we can see that it's shown us that my haloed out here has a result
here.
And as a result here as a result here it has a result that you don't see anything for God's Bedacht
text and you can count as well so if I just do that you can see that the Gatsby manuscript returns zero
results for the latter a and my Hello 0.60 file returns for.
So even though I had five lines of text and the Gadsby one had 1914 guess four out of my five lines.
80 percent of my text had a letter in it and theirs had none.
So that's just what I just think Gadsby was was showing off.
So now that you know how to use the grep command to analyze literary masterpiece is the most common
way to actually use it is to search within data that you pipe to it.
OK so if I just if I just clean this this command line here we're going to show you how actually the
screen will show you how you can do something a bit more heavy duty with the find with the grep command.
So let's say that you wanted to look inside a big folder to see whether a file is inside.
OK.
Yes we could use the find command but perhaps we decided that the find command is a bit heavy duty for
such a quick check.
OK so let's make let's make a folder on the desktop called Hello in there and let's move the hello 0.60
into that hello folder.
OK when we look we should see that that is indeed the case.
Yep there we go.
Hello RTX t inside.
OK let's create some more files inside let's touch inside the hello folder.
I dunno I guess like files say 100 or the files Kosa in there.
Now we can see that there's 100 of the files somewhere in there is haloed text.
OK.
So let's say that we wanted to use the ls command to list what's in Hello.
Can you see you get quite a bit of information coming out of the ls command especially if we have the
option.
Definitely a lot of information coming out there.
But you can do is you can just use the last option and pipe it to the grep command and say hey we're
looking for Hello Dotti XTi and you'll see that it is highlighted.
Hello Dottie XTi as as something thats being present.
OK so that can help you search things in there.
Another example that I use often is what I'm looking for details about a particular file or folders
permissions using the ls command.
So for example if I want to see the permissions for The Root home directory I could do ls with the L
and capital f option.
But with the fourth slashes see everything all the permissions for everything in the base directory.
OK but let's say I wanted to look specifically at the folder called Root.
Well then I could just pipe it into grep and say root and it will tell us that you'll be able to see
hear the root folder coming out like that.
Or we could have a look at the OPT or the optional folder if you want to look at that.
We just look at it and it will just cut out that line for you and you can just see that so you can see
how you're filtering out just what you're looking for.
OK so this is a very very useful option.
Let's say we were looking in.
So you know I wanted all of the files not the folders in the ETSI directory.
Let's say then what I could do is I could say ls with the f option for the ETSI folder and you can see
that it showed us everything in here.
All the folders have a slash after them and all the files don't.
OK so if I want to find all the files I just have to find everything that doesn't have a slash right.
So if I take all that data into grep give it the v option and a slash.
This is saying OK take all that data and give me every line that doesn't have a slash and that we are
we've got all of the the game that I could maybe redirect that into a list of files.
Dr. XTi And now here I've got a list of files that are in the N.Z. folder.
OK.
And of course we could sort all of those and whatever else if you wanted so you know we could take it
from there and then sort it reverse let's say we wanted them backwards and then put that into the files.
Team and we'll see that everything is now backwards with Zed at the top and the letter A at the bottom.
So you can see how we're using all this stuff really links together very well and if you're understanding
this you're a pro OK because like you know if you're you know it wasn't that long ago that all of this
would have been complete and utter jibberish to you but now you understand that hey we're just using
the ls command.
We're classifying what's coming out with the f option.
So it gives us a slash around around directories and nothing around files.
I'm looking in the ETSI folder we're searching inside they're using the inside all that data using the
grep command for everything that doesn't have a slash.
That gives us all the files.
And then let's say we're sorting them reverse reverse wise and then save it not in a file called file
start XTi.
OK so you can see how we're using multiple different commands to build up these pipelines easier and
easier as we go through the course.
Now another really common uses of this is when you're using the man dash K command.
So you know when when you wanted to search for things in the manual pages so I wanted to search for
print.
OK we can see that we get loads of different options to print.
Now you could read all of these out yourself but it's kind of a bit of a pain when you want to search
for something a bit more specific.
Well you know you could grap and say OK well I'm looking for files specifically.
OK so and then it will tell me you know to find all the ones that mentioned files which you know makes
it a lot easier for us to see and we might then notice the LPL command which prints files.
OK.
There's also the camp command up here which can concat which can concatenate files try saying that three
times fast can concatenate files to standard output.
OK so this is another common usage of the of the grep command and we have less results to page through
than we would have otherwise had because we filtered out what we were looking for.
So they have a beautiful people.
That's how you can use the grep command to search within files and filter the output from other commands.
Now the grep command has to be one of the most commonly used commands of all time and you'll probably
use a whole lot in your work with the Linux terminal as well.
So to make sure that we've got the important points down let's have a recap.
So first of all you saw how to use the grep command to search for text within files and the group can
search through any kind of data whether it's static within a file or it's piped to it.
And what you found was that the grep command will return lines that match a certain piece of text or
a regular expression made up of wild cards so you could give instead of giving the group command a piece
of text to search for.
You could give it a regular expression using wildcards and it will find all the lines that have something
that matches that wildcards that's a really useful ability as well.
And you can count how many lines that match that text instead of returning the lines themselves just
return the line count by giving the grep command the C option which we used multiple times in the last
few videos.
Now by default because Linux is a case sensitive operating system the you can make the search case insensitive
so that uppercase and lowercase don't matter.
By giving the grep command the option which is really useful and if you don't know whether it's an uppercase
or a lower case letter that you're searching for but you know it's that thing that you're searching
for Arka you don't know whether it's up against other guys but you know it's at least that word or at
least that that letter or something like that.
OK.
Then we also use the grep command to analyze the validity of the 1939 literary masterpiece of Gadsby
which is the 50000 word book that never used the letter.
And we have now confirmed that using using our lyrics or grep command.
And you can find a copy of that manuscript in a link to where I got it from in the resources section
of this video and the last one if you if you want to take a look and play with it yourself.
OK.
We also saw the v option which will invert the search so that means it'll do the opposite.
So instead of searching for lines that match a certain piece of text or match a certain regular expression
it'll will find all the lines that don't.
And finally one thing that we saw was how a group works so well when you piped data to it and you saw
how you can use it to filter out a lot of data to give you the lines that you're looking for from a
big bunch of data that comes out.
So it's useful with the ls command the man command so many other things as well just any time that you
are looking for a specific piece of text or a specific word or something that matches a certain format.
Use the grep command and you'll save yourself a bit Juliann hours of time.
OK.
So there we go.
The next great thing about the grep command is its flexibility and its versatility you know can be used
pretty much anywhere and it will be a tool that you'll likely use time and time again.
So now you know how to do many many things with files and directories you can create them copy them
delete them move them rename them edit them search for them search within them sort them and so much
more.
OK you've come a very very very long way in this section and I applaud you for your progress.
OK but we have one last thing that I want to cover.
File compression and archiving.
Now the last thing that you want to do is lose data on your system and know how to compress an uncompressed
files to create backups will allow you to insure yourself against loss of data.
And it's one of those things that's so important that you just kind of got to know how to do it.
OK.
So in the next video we're going to be discussing how you can compress an uncompressed files to create
and restore backups.
So for that good stuff.
I'll see you in the next video.