Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome to this field where you're going to start learning all about file archiving and compression.
Now I'm sure you've heard millions of times about the benefits of keeping backups of your data and that's
exactly what we're going to be covering in the next few videos in the next few videos you're going to
learn how to archive and compress your files in the next to create backups.
Now just creating the backups isn't good enough you're also going to learn how you can restore data
from those backups in the future.
So when you need to uncompress it you day it will come back out perfectly by the end you basically going
to be able to create and restore your own backups to make sure you don't lose any important data.
You're also going to learn about various compression algorithms so you can save the maximum amount of
space on your file system as possible.
So let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So when you're compressing and archiving files in Linux the first thing you need to know about is something
called a tall ball.
Now I want you to imagine that you're a shopping center or to your local store and you're buying some
apples.
OK.
Now let me ask you a question.
How would you make those apples after picking them up.
Easier to carry Well you put them in a bag right.
And that's what creating a table is basically doing OK so creating a table is basically a way of putting
your files in a bag to make them easier to compress and make them easier to store.
OK and when you add files to a table you make it possible to store all of your files in one place.
The table itself doesn't do any compression but tarballs can be compressed using compression algorithms.
OK so archiving files is basically a two step process.
First you make a table and you make a table.
And then secondly you compress the tarball using some kind of compression algorithm.
OK.
So let's go ahead and create their first Tabo.
And so we're on our desktop now we can see that we've got file 1.60 Faltu that takes the 3.6.
I'm going to put those inside a table.
Now if I do an ls on on these files and just have a look at them you can see that they're all about
10 kilobytes in size.
OK nine point eight kilobytes are about 10 kilobytes in size and we're going to put all of these into
a table.
OK.
So to do so we're going to use the tar command the TJR command.
Now the command takes quite a few different options.
In order for this to work.
So first we type TA.
Then we need to give it three options.
Says Type A dash and the first option is the C option.
Now the C option lets the common know that we want to create a new archive.
OK.
The next is vi which lets the to talk him I know that we want to do we wanted to speak to us.
We wanted to give us some feedback so we know how it's doing.
Nivea stands for Beauce and it basically says hey talk him and don't do this silently.
Talk to me and let me know what's up.
Like I said the v option is entirely optional.
You don't need it to make an archive.
But you know it's good practice to keep it there.
OK.
And the final option is the f option.
Now the f option is so that it lets the talk about accept files.
OK.
So no we need to tell the talkathon what we want to call our Tabo.
Now by convention we enter all files with the TA file extension.
This is just a convention.
So we know what they are called later.
So let's call it archive dot tar.
Okay.
And finally what we need to do now is we need to tell the tar command what's going to go inside our
tarball.
OK.
So we want to a 1.60 Faltu not THC and fall 3 that takes t.
So she use a wild card to save some typing and put file 1 to 3 to 60.
OK.
And with that we're ready to go.
So what we're saying is hey Torkham and we wanted to create a new archive.
So we give it the C option.
We're saying Speak to us we know what's going on.
It's just the v option.
And we're going to give it the f option so that it can accept new files and create a new archive.
So let's just go ahead and press enter.
And we see that it told us what's going on and now we've got this new tar file that's actually being
created and you can see that it looks like a little box like a like you know a moving box.
So you know that it's that it's an archive.
And if we do analysis we can actually see that the tar ball file has actually been highlighted in red.
Just to make it stand a bit more which is quite nice.
So hooray we've actually managed to create our first tabel now that command this talk and I've had quite
a few different options in it.
So what I've done is for all the commands dealing with archiving.
So in this video on the next video I've made a cheat sheet for you to download that details how to do
different archiving tasks.
Don't worry about memorizing.
You can find not in the resources section for the next video.
When we finished dealing with archiving.
OK.
So let's take a look at how large the file is by using ls with the l option and actually what we're
going to do is we look for the ones that have dot tar in them using using Gramp.
So we just see what has doctorand to focus our results a little bit and we see the actually it's about
40000 960 bytes.
Well that's strange because we had three about 10000 byte files and then we've got 40000 960 bytes for
the table.
Shouldn't it be 30000 bytes or somewhere near there.
Well not exactly.
OK.
But think of the apple's example.
If each apple weighed 100 grams and you have three apples and then you put them in a bag with a whole
bag weigh 300 grams.
No because the bag has some weight as well right.
So what we're seeing here is just that in order to create a table we need to add some data.
So just think of the exercise being like the extra weight from a bag when you put apples in it.
It's just part of the convenience of building a tabo But don't worry when we compress the tar ball it
will be much much smaller than the falls would have been on their own.
OK.
Now we can tell that this is a tab all by looking the doc tor file extension.
Right.
But remember that in Linux file extensions don't really mean anything.
They're usually just a convenience so that we can see as humans but they don't mean anything necessary
to the system.
So to double check that it is a tab all we can use the file commands that you learned about earlier
in the course.
If we do file I can click the screen file archive doc.
You'll see that it tells us that it is indeed up ta archive.
OK.
Now if we rename this table so we renamed it to be our archive.
Gosh BLAM.
Let's say now if we do.
If we do the file command on that.
So file of our archived Autoblog.
You see that the system wasn't tricked and it still knows that it's a tar archive even though it didn't
have the tar file extension so let's change that back because we don't need any more confusion than
is necessary.
Best just to let you know that the top the doc file extension isn't particularly anything special to
the system.
But again it might be to other programs you have installed upon it but you can always check what the
true nature of something is using the file command.
OK but the doc file extension is just something that allows you and potentially other users to know
what type of file is at a glance.
Now you can actually take a look at what is in a tarball without having to extract it.
So let's say you downloaded this.
This archive.
From.
From the interweb.
And do you want to take a look at what's inside.
OK.
You can do that using the tar command and what you do is you give it to options like how you do the
t option and the f option and then you tell it aracari doctor.
OK so the T option means test label and it basically lets you check what's inside the file and the f
option it's just necessary in order to pass a file to the TOC command.
OK so when we do that it tells us that file 1 and 4 2 and 4 3 are inside the table.
That's pretty cool right now we're going to come into compression in a little bit.
But first take a look at how we can get these files outside of our tarball.
Again the cable is actually very simple.
First let's delete the file whatever Dotti XTi because they've all disappeared.
We've got just tabel here and we're going to extract the files out of that.
OK.
So let's try and do this now.
The way we'll do it is just it's actually very simple.
Right so you'll have to talk them and remember to create an archive.
You had CVF and then you read we wrote our archive doc Taung then we gave it some files OK now to extract.
It's very simple.
OK instead of C for create you use x for extract and everything else is the same but you don't even
have to give any files because you're not putting any files into the archive you should stop tar X-Fi
extract VIF of for verbose so it tells us what it's actually doing and APH is necessary so you can pass
a file to the talk and when we press Enter we'll see that it has indeed extracted out for us.
For one Faltu and fall three from the archive and we have those back in that in the directory that we
that we were in when we ran the command.
So there we go pretty easy right.
And again all of this is in the cheat sheet for us.
So now you might be thinking OK we've just extracted these files from the top from the table is the
table now empty.
Well actually it's not.
You can just.
You can actually check that the files are still in there by telling it just like you saw before checking
inside with the TANF options.
You can check the file one file to unfold three are still inside the table so no matter how many times
you extract from a table the table still contains what's inside of it.
So it's like an A it's a reusable bag that maybe you get from shops.
OK that's pretty awesome right now.
I'm going to break the video here.
In interest of time and in the next video we're going to be talking about how we can compress our tar
balls to make them smaller.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.