Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back.
Now in the last video we put our files into a tarball and now we want to learn about how to compress
that tabel to save space on our hard drive.
Compression happens using compression algorithms.
And there are two main compression algorithms in use in the Linux world.
And the first is the JE's it algorithm and the second is B zip zip to OK and the main difference between
them is usually is faster but has less compression power.
And because it too on the other hand can generally compress files to a smaller size than Jesus but does
require more computational time.
So both these compression algorithms are really easy to use Let's just start by talking about Giza.
OK.
So to compress a table using Jees up all you need to do is type G.
And then the archive names are archived on TA and press enter and we'll see that that file has been
compressed ins in place using the Jesus algorithm and we can see that it has if we use the ls command
here we can see that the DOT G Zed file extension has automatically been added and we can use the file
command to confirm that yep this is indeed Zipp compressed data.
And it was archived.
Ta ok and it tells you when it was last modified as well.
OK.
So that's really cool.
We can see quite a lot of information about that.
Now let's take a look at the file size.
So if I do the ls command with the l h option like actionless just the option will see the fall one
for two and four three or ten thousand bytes in size.
But I archive the compressed archive is only 23000 bytes so it's about 7000 bytes or seven kilobytes
less than what the files would have been originally.
So we actually have managed to do a compression of about 23 percent.
So that's not bad.
This will vary from file type to file type and what you're actually compressing.
But in this case we've got a compression of 23 percent with Jesus.
So not just how compression is a two stage thing.
First we make a tarball and then we compress that tarball with a compression algorithm OK which in this
case was it.
Ok cause How about reversing the GS.
How can we get the Tabo back.
Well this is very easy.
All we need to do is just click the screen G and zip archive dot dot dot.
OK so you just use g unzip on whatever it was and when you do that you see it's now back to a tar file.
And if we look we can see that it's a top file using the file commands are archived on TAR.
And it tells you it's a puzzle to our archive.
Hooray.
OK so we've managed to undo the GS app operation.
OK so what about being zipped too.
Well because it too is a more heavy duty compression algorithm and it takes more computational time
than JE's up but usually not always but usually returns more compressed files than you get with it.
Because it's a bit of a tradeoff.
Now let's compress at Tabo with BS too and see what we get like.
So it's very easy.
All we have to do is BS it to archive.
DR.
And when we say that we now see that it's gone and got the BS had to file extension and if we use the
file command on it we can see that it says it because it to compress data.
It doesn't tell you what it was before it was compressed so we lose a bit of that information but it
has indeed been compressed and the file command knows that it has.
So how big is it.
Well if we take a look with the l option we can just have a look right there and we can see that this
is 23000 137 bytes.
So it's slightly larger than the GS version of 23000 and 23 bytes Nabby's it to is usually best saved
until you have really large files.
Now for these relatively small text files it didn't do as much good to use it to but rather large file
such as a video.
You'll definitely see a large difference between the compression results achieved by b.s up to and GZA.
Let's undo a BS app to compression.
It's actually very easy.
All we've got to do is be unzip to and then whatever the bees have to archive it.
So in our case this archived UNCTAD are easy to we press enter.
We see that we've come back to the tar file and again we can use the file command to check and we've
got our tar archive back.
Now there are other compression algorithms that Messers the ex-head compression algorithm.
And if you want to see a more in-depth comparison between the performance of Gs of bees it to and the
exit algorithm I put a link in the resources section for you to find out.
Now there is something that you should bear in mind however which is how do you create zip files.
Now zip files are files that you know are commonly used on Windows or Mac.
And do you know as compressed archives.
Now they're not.
I don't think they are as compressed as what you'll get with be too but they are commonly used on other
on other operating systems.
So if you want to create a zip file it's actually a one step process.
You'll just type zip.
OK then you put the files let's kill let's call it thing.
Dot zip.
And then we'll put file 1.60 for 2.6 for 3.6.
I want to be president.
We'll see that we now have a zip file in there so if I press files file are things sorry zip it does
that it's a zip archive data and this is what you can use on other operating systems such as Windows
and you usually can with zipped files or zip to compressed files because they don't tend to work too
well on other operating systems by default you don't have to install other software like 7 zip or when
raw or whatever it might be to extract them.
And of course you can just unzip that zip file and it'll ask you do you want to extract them all and
then you can extract them all.
This is just asking us because it was like oh I have to overwrite some stuff.
That's no problem we just said yes and that worked.
So if you want to make zip files zip and unzip is the way to go.
So if we clear the screen no so far we've been looking at compression as a two step process.
OK first we've been creating a tarball using the command and then compressing that tabbouleh using either
zip or it to or you know any other compression algorithm.
OK.
But is there any way to do it in one step.
Well because creating backups is such a common thing to do.
The answer is yes you can actually create a table and compress it using a compression algorithm straight
from within the Tor command.
So let's just delete our top or phenomenas it followed us or tar archive dot tar we're going to remove
that thing dot zip.
So we're going to get rid of all every archive that we've got and then we're going to take it right
from just the raw data here these raw files straight to a compressed archive in one go.
OK.
So to create the tab to create the tar ball itself how would we do that.
Well what we do is we'd create what we do TAR CVF so create verbose and allow it to accept files.
We're going to create our archive dot.
There we go and file one to three.
So this is the way that we normally do it.
OK.
But now to compress the files we just need to give it one more option.
So to do it with GZA you just give it the Zed option.
OK.
And if if we do that that will compress using geezer.
And we should remember that instead of naming it as archived on TAR because this is going to be a zip
file we should add dot G Zed at the end as well just for convention because it won't be added automatically
when using this method.
OK.
When you run Jees upon it before it was added automatically the doc desired file extension.
But now because we're doing it all in one step we have to provide the file name.
So we need to add on that just so you know it's a bit easier to see what's going on.
And when we have when we press Enter we'll see the archived Algy's that has been has been created and
we can check that it is in fact GS It file using the file command.
And it says that it is just a compressed data so it's super cool.
OK.
Now how would you do it using it too.
Well if we clear the screen BS It too is exactly the same except instead of zed.
You just have J.
OK so if you press if you have J.
And now remember we're going to change our extension to be 0 2 percent or we'll see that archive Dombey's
2 has been created and we can check that that is indeed valid by using the file command telling it to
look at the bes to archive and it tells us that it's BS to compressed data.
So that's how you can compress in one go.
How would we go about extracting from those compressed archives in one go.
Well it's really easy as well Caylus delete them again.
Actually I was not doing them because we'll need them right.
So how would we normally extract from a file.
Well I would normally do it.
If you remember is TA then X V.F..
So X-Fi extract VIF of Abodh and I have to accept a file and you'd give it the file.
OK but let's try and extract the Jesus option versus delete these original files and then trying to
extract the the GS option first.
So to extract the Jesus option we will do is that again because that is Fuji's.
OK.
So you had the Zed when compressing you have the Zed when extracting all you've got to do is change
the C to an X and you get to go.
So when we press that we'll see that now we've extracted them all out again and we've got the data back.
So if we delete these files here if we just delete them there.
Now how about extracting using it.
Well you remember that J is for.
So instead of having XEDIT let's just put the J.
And then we just need to tell it what the archive is and remember that it's a BS app to archives which
actually change the name.
So we are Taar extracting verbose through Baeza up to and then giving it the file and that we are we've
extracted it too so it's very very easy as long as you can remember.
Is Fuji's EP J is for it too.
You saw it and you can extract and compress all in one go Hooray.
So we've seen so much in the last two videos it's quite hilarious that a section on compression would
take so long right.
Anyway let's have a quick recap so you first learned about the concept of a tarball now tar files or
tar balls or just containers for you to store the files that you want to compress.
OK.
They can create tarballs using the tar command and tables do not really do any compression on their
own.
That's the job of a compression algorithm the tarball just contains the files and you saw how to add
files into tarballs and how to extract files from tarballs using the command.
And remember that there's a cheat sheet in the resources section for this video that will list out the
different options different ways of using the talk command.
Now once you have the table in order to compress it you need to use a compression algorithm.
OK.
So tarballs can be compressed using a variety of different compression algorithms.
And we took a look at GS.
And these two which are common options on Linux.
But the exect option is another option we didn't discuss it here but if you want to read more about
the comparison between the different algorithms I've also put a link to a intrusting blog post in the
resources section for this videotape for you to have a look at as well.
OK.
But with regards to JE's up NBC to GS It tends to be faster but give less compression Busby's it tends
to give more compression.
But take a bit more computation time.
OK so that's just something to bear in mind but by all means check out the link in the resources section
for a more in-depth discussion.
You saw also how you can create zip files for compatibility with things like Windows or Mac using the
zip and unzip commands so that's something as well that you've got on record as well.
OK.
And you saw as well how to not just do making the tarball and then compressing into steps.
So I had to do archiving and compression in just one step using variety of shortcuts and all that stuff
is in the cheat sheet.
You can find in the resources section for this video if you ever need a refresher.
OK it's all very simple and once you look at the cheat sheet probably you'll be able to see the pattern
but it's really quite simple stuff.
Once you've done it once or twice.
OK.
So all in all you can now create your own archives and backups using Linux using the Linux command line
which is super awesome because on this section all about learning how to use files.
Now when you've created Defarge you've edited them they've copy paste them you've moved them you've
done whatever you want with them.
You can also create your own backups and save for later in a say in a space efficient way.
So Welden you now in the next video what we're going to be doing is we're going to be closing our discussion
for the section on files and the file system and I want to say that you've really come so very far in
this section and the next video I want to take the time to have a recap of what we've learned in this
section and also to celebrate your progress.
So Welden you now for a summary of the section of the Course as well as some a deserved set of praises.
I'll see you in the next video.