So congratulations you've made it to the end of this section of the Course all about the Linux file
system not being able to effectively navigate the Linux file system and work with files is likely going
to be skills that you will use over and over and over again.
So congratulations for making it this far.
So.
So to celebrate your success so far in the course in this video have a quick review of what we have
covered in this section so you can see just how far that you have come.
OK.
So we first started off with a discussion of the structure of the file structure of the US system sorry.
And you saw that the whole file system has a tree like structure starting with a root directory and
branching out from there.
And once you understood that the structure of the file system and had a map to work with you learned
how to tell where your shell is currently operating from using the P WD command that PWT sounds will
print working directory and it basically prints out on your screen the location that your shell is currently
operating in.
And you also learn that you can do the same thing by glancing at your shell prompt which the bit of
text in your terminal on the left where you enter your commands.
OK.
Now once you saw how to find out where you while you saw had to move around the file system and change
directories using the cd command I had to look around by listing the contents of directories using the
L s command.
Now after learning these critical navigation commands you had a discussion about the meaning of file
extensions in Linux and you saw that file extensions don't matter much in X but might matter to the
programs running on it.
This means that you have the flexibility to give files whatever names that you want but remember that
you might want to stick to standard file conventions.
If you're expecting those files to be used by other programs then you learned about a feature of the
shell that I'm sure you fell in love with by now which is wildcards.
Now wildcards allow you to operate on many different files at once and just operate on specifically
what you are looking for which is which saves you lots of time and typing and it basically makes your
commands a whole lot more powerful.
Now once you had got those very important basics down you learned a whole bunch of commands.
I had to create files and directories copy them paste them delete them rename them move them around.
And also I had to edit them with a command line based text file editor called Nano.
But with all of this creation moving and editing of files it's quite likely that at some point you won't
know exactly where a file is created or located and you might need to find it.
So you use the locate command to find files on your system and you'll have the locate command uses a
database to find files and you saw how to use the update DBI command to update its database for security
reasons updating the database requies elevated privileges that normal users don't have.
So how do you use the sudo command to temporarily become the root user and do what you need to do.
And you can use that for any command not just the locate command.
Now although the locate command is awesome you can get the job done quickly.
Sometimes you need something a bit more customizable and heavy duty.
So after learning about the locate command you learn how to find files using the find command that find
command is a super powerful command that has loads of options to make sure that you can find what ever
you want on your system.
There it also has the added bonus that once you have found a bunch of files of directors with the find
command you can actually tell the find command to run under the command or series of commands for each
result that it finds.
And this allows you to create incredibly powerful functionality with very little effort.
And then you moved on to learn about how to look inside files using the cat command so that you can
also stick files together or concatenate different files using the cat command and sometimes you need
to reverse data.
So you saw that you can reverse files vertically using the attack command or horizontally using the
command.
Now sometimes when you open files or run commands you get a whole lot of output on the screen and having
all on the screen at once is not very helpful.
So you learnt about the last page a program that allows you to page through large amounts of text to
make it more manageable and you also learned a whole host of useful tactics for getting just what you
want from a file.
So is the head command the tail command and grep command then you saw how you can sort of files content
in a variety of different ways.
And finally we topped off the discussion with a look at file archiving and compression.
So you've really learned a lot of stuff in this section and you should be incredibly proud of yourself
so well.
Well done.
Now you will use the skills that you've learned here all the time.
We all work with that and it's come on line.
So it's a really amazing moment right now in your Linux skills development.
So in the next section you're going to learn about how you can schedule and automate tasks on your system
using bash scripts and a super useful utility called Krumm.
But before we get to that I have a project for you to complete.
Now the project will challenge you to do various things with the Linux file system and use a whole bunch
of the commands and build a really advanced pipeline.
OK now it's going to be awesome and it will serve as a badge of honor that you have learned everything
that we've covered in this section of the course so you can feel confident moving on.
So in the next video I'm going to be giving you a project brief.
So congratulations once again for what you've done in the section you're doing amazingly.
I'm super proud of you and I'll see you in the next video.