Lovin you beautiful people are welcome to part two.
Navigating the Linux file system.
So in this video we're going to build upon what we learned in the last video about using the PWT and
the LS commands.
But in this video you're going to learn how to use the cd command to actually move around the file system.
You're going to learn the difference between absolute and relative paths.
You can learn some awesome keyboard shortcuts that will make navigating the file system so quick and
so easy and you basically going to see how you can put together the PWT the Ls and the CD commands to
elegantly navigate the file system.
By the end of this video you're going to know everything you need to know about navigating the Linux
file system using the command line and you watch with a bit of practice you'll soon agree with me that
doing it this way is a lot faster and a lot more effective than using your pointy clicky graphical methods
that you've been using.
Probably all of your life so far.
So let's go ahead and jump right into this next part of your superhero training.
OK.
So in the last video we saw that we could use the P W D command to see where we were on the file system
and we saw that we could use the ls command with a variety of different options to basically look around
and list what was in the directory the way in.
But using just these two commands we're kind of stuck in the one place right how can we actually move
from our home directory.
Well the missing piece is the C D command and the cd command stands for change directory.
So let's say that we used our last kind and we saw that the downloads folder by noting that it's in
blue and it's a folder and we wanted to go into the downloads folder.
How would we do that.
What we could do it in a few ways.
Firstly we can give the cd command the absolute path for where we want to go with a go starting at the
base directory we'd go slash then home then Ziyad then downloads OK and we could type that in like that
and that would totally work or if we didn't want to have to write the entire path to our home directory
we could just replace all that with the Tilda.
We say OK go change to our home directory and then download that's where you'd use the tilde at a shortcut
or what we could use is something known as a relative path number relative path is a path relative to
where you currently are.
OK so because we're currently in the home folder how do we get to the downloads folder.
Well let's think about it if we open up the graphical graphical menu.
Here we are we're in the home folder from here.
What do we do to get to the downloads folder.
We literally all we have to do is just click downloads right so that you can say that that's a relative
path which is going from here to the download that's all we've got to do.
So to change to the downloads folder all we've got to do is type downloads.
So if we do that if we just type CD and then downloads just like that and press ENTER you can see that
we have changed directory and a shell prompt has changed as well before it was just the tilda telling
us that we were in our home directory.
Now it's saying we're in our home directory and the downloads folder inside.
OK.
So this is this text in blue here shows us the path to where we currently on if we use the PWT command
now we can see that we get slash home slashy or slash downloads and we can also look around by pressing
the ls command and we can see that there's actually nothing inside that folder.
OK so neither We're not Downloads folder.
Here's a challenge for you.
Go ahead and post the video and see if you can use the CD command to change back to our home directory.
So go ahead and pause the video and give it a shot and then come back to see how you did.
Did you manage it.
If so really really well done.
You learn super quickly now you could have done it using an absolute path like this you could type CD
then slash home slash your username or whatever would be in my case it Ziyad slash.
And that's it.
OK that would work.
Or you could have used a Tilda to make it nice and easy just use CD and then Attilla.
Now I kind of cheated a little bit because there's another way that you could have done it.
And this is the way you probably do it from now on.
But I haven't shown you this before.
Now by default if you don't give me any input the CD command will take you to your home folder.
So if we just type CD like from scratch type CD and press ENTER you can see by just looking at the shell
prompt that we've ended up back in our home directory we can use Peter Beattie to confirm that.
I mean it tells us that we are back in our home directory and that will work no matter where I was previously
on the file system I could have been anywhere on the file system all of the do is type CD or press Enter
then I will end up back in the home directory.
Pretty cool right.
Okay great.
So now we're back in the home folder I want to show you a very useful option for the ls command.
It's kind of like wearing X-ray glasses.
And it's the A option that the option is short for all.
And it allows you to see all of the files in a directory even the hidden files.
So if I type ls and give it the option OK.
If I press Enter you'll notice that we see a whole lot of stuff in here.
Print it out.
OK if I clear the screen on top you just the last option and then show you the ls with the A option
you'll see we get a lot more stuff with the A option.
Now a lot of these files you'll notice have fall names beginning with dots and that means that there
hidden files or even hidden directories.
OK.
Now if we look in the graphical editor we may not be able to actually see them by default but if we
click up here like we do in the last few videos and show hidden files we can now see them as well so
you look you can see that we're getting exactly the same output so that's how you show hidden files
using the using the the the ls command.
OK.
And you may also notice in here that we've got our bash alias's file that we made a few videos ago.
Now the reason I mention this is because these two very important hidden folders inside each folder.
They are the dot and the double dot folders.
OK.
Now these are shortcuts to allow you to move around easier or refer to stuff on your file system a whole
lot easier.
The doc folder simply refers to the current directory.
OK.
So for example if I go to the Desktop folder OK then we can print.
My apologies if I can do print working directory and we can see that we have that we are in the desktop
and if our list its contents this shouldn't really be anything on my desktop.
But there always is this data and double dot folders which are only visible using the ls with the option
of just the normal address.
It doesn't show up for duellists dash 8.
They show up.
OK.
Now in here we've got the dot and the double dot folders.
If I try to do cd to the doc folder Bash is basically going to stay where is the shell is going to stay
exactly where is if I do that.
You can see that we're still in the desktop looking at the shell prompt because the DOT folder refers
to the current folder that we're in.
OK.
It's just a way of saying this folder.
Now what if I went to the doubleback.
What if I do cd doubled up OK.
You noticed that we did actually change and were in fact back in our home folder the doubled up folder
means the parent folder or the folder above where we currently are.
OK.
So if I go back to the desktop you can see that we've got the doubled up for if I press CD double that
we've gone back up a folder.
Which brings us into the home directory in case we're back in a home directory let's clear the screen.
What if I kept going.
OK if I go see the dot dot I'm now in the actual home folder which is not my home folder but it's the
folder above my home folder.
OK let's keep going.
See the dot dot.
And now we're actually just in the slash for the we're in the base directory for the whole system.
OK.
See if we can go any higher we go C.D dot dot.
You can see that we can't go any higher because the dust the slush folder is the highest point on the
file system.
OK.
And we can actually have a look around if I do an ls what's in the base directory.
See there's quite a lot of files here that you saw when we had a little bit of next mation of the file
system you've got the bin folder the boot folder the folder the ETSI folder which is full of your configuration
files.
The home folder which is where we just were to get our home stuff.
The library's media which is where you have your room remove wardrobe's your optional stuff.
The route users home folder and so on.
So on the variable files temp files user stuff and so on and so on I guess these are the folders and
the most important of these anyway are the ones that I gave you a cheat sheet where we talked about
the file system.
OK.
And see what happens.
This is the root user's home folder right.
This is the home folder for the administrator.
Let's try and see what happens if we try to enter it.
If we do see the route OK and press enter you can see that we get permission denied.
OK so there's some folders that you were allowed into and some folders that you're not allowed into.
So we don't have enough privileges to be able to access the root user's home directory.
Well what about the ETSI folder OK along with the configuration files as try that.
If we try CD and see how we can get into that one let's see what's in there for us.
Ls us who you can see the whole bunch of stuff in there right.
And you get some folders in here.
The blue ones or folders and the white ones files and some of them have different types as well.
But you don't have to worry about that.
Mostly what you'll see are blue and white blue ones folders white one files and you can enter anything
that you want in there.
For example there's one here where are we looking.
There's one here called DHC pay we could go into that folder.
We could try CD DHC page.
OK.
Now what's in there.
We could do ls and we can have a look around we can see this other stuff in there.
There's another one there.
De D.H. climbed and to hook day.
Let's try to get the D.H. client dash and dash hooks.
You can see that we're in there what's in there two Ls we see this other stuff in there.
The green ones here are programs but you can see here right the way that we are moving around the file
system using either CD to move LS to see what's around us or Peter Beattie to confirm exactly where
we are.
And it's this way that you will actually move around the entire system and it doesn't change no matter
where you are as long as you've got the permissions to enter those folders you can get there using just
the cd command and you can look around using the ls command and you can confirm where you are using
the Pido EDI command.
Now how do we get all the way back to our home folder.
Very easy just press CD press enter and we are back in our home folder.
So you can see the pretty much anything that you need to do in the Linux file system anywhere in the
expansion that you want to move to as long as you have the required permissions on the CD.
LS And Peter really commands and you can get wherever you want and if you get lost or shoes the Pido
E-D command to check where you are pretty epic right.
So now that we're back in our home folder there's one final thing that I want to teach you.
And that's called tab completion.
But for goodness as well as a summary of everything we've learned in the past few videos I'll see you
in the next video.