Hello you beautiful people.
And in this video we're going to be wrapping up our discussion of how to navigate the Linux file system
using the command line.
And in this video you're going to learn how to use tab auto completion to speed up your navigation of
the file system.
And we're also going to have a recap of what everything that we've learned about navigating falses and
in the past few videos.
And by the end of this video you can have all the knowledge that you need to navigate the false system
like a pro.
Just add practice and you're going to get plenty of that as we go through the course.
So to get the final few pieces of information about tab auto completion.
Let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So let's go ahead and learn about a really awesome feature known as tab completion.
Now at the minute we're currently in our home directory as you can see by looking at the shell prompt
and also by using the P.W. DICOM and we see that we're in our home directory.
Now we could actually jump all the way to the base directory of the system by just typing CD and then
a slash.
And if I do that you'll see that if we use the print working directory command we can see that we are
in the base direct of our system.
I don't want to do this just to highlight that you don't have to go folder by folder when you using
the Siddiq and you can actually just jump all the way around your system.
So for example if I wanted to jump all the way to my desktop I don't have to go CD then slash.
You know I don't have to go step by step all the way through.
I can just say CD give it the tilda and then say because that's my home folder and then say desktop.
OK.
Now we are we end up in the desktop so you can you see come into jump around.
You don't have to go step by step.
OK.
So clearly the scream Let's go ahead and now learn about tab completion.
So let's say that we wanted to get all the way to my home directory using an absolute path.
OK.
We can do that simply by just typing it all right we can type CDs slash home slash Zyad And you know
if we're to go to documents we can type slash documents.
You know we would be there.
OK we would get all the way to the documents folder.
But typing it takes a bit of time.
It's error prone and you know we're kind of lazy as programmers.
OK so we want speed and we want things to be without errors and we want things to work right the first
time.
So that's where tab completion comes in.
Let's head back to our home or back to the very base directory and clear the screen.
Peter Beattie we're in the base directory.
This is how you can use tab completion to get that room.
We want to get to the documents folder.
OK.
So that's going to be like this.
OK that's where we're trying to get to.
So let's see how we would get there which I've CD can slash now is that it's happening at home.
We could just type that page and press the tab and you'll see that the shell automatically completed
that piece of text for us.
Now that's pretty cool.
They're trying to type out Ziyad So we just type Zed and then we press tab and it's filled out my name.
Awesome right.
Now let's say we want to go into documents.
OK let's let's try it.
Capital D and press tab.
Now why is it not working.
Let's try again.
Cable is not working.
Well the reason is this capital D could refer to lots of things in our home folder.
So let's take a look at it.
If we go to our home folder here.
Click the screen and take a look you can see that the capital D could refer to the desktop it could
refer to the downloads or it could refer to the documents and the documents that we want.
OK.
So if a file if you.
Now if I say OK I want to go to the capital D here and press tap twice with each passing ones it won't
work.
Suppress it twice really quickly.
Just like that.
It will actually.
It's a lot.
It will actually clear the screen.
It will press it twice it will actually tell us which ones it matches.
OK.
So we want to go into documents if I type doc.
Because what audio and double tap that's still no good because it could go for documents or downloads
of a type doc and then press tab.
Now it's going to go to documents.
OK.
And there we all were in the Documents folder.
So that's awesome.
And it cut down our level of typing and error proneness massively So if we go all the way back to the
root directory.
Now we can just type CD slash page tab Zad tab DOHC tab.
There we are in the documents folder.
It's really really cool.
This will work for filenames just like it will for folders and it's amazing and I use it all the time.
OK.
Nas one final awesome trick.
Let's not forget to the desktop the graphical way.
OK.
So we're going to open.
We're going to go into the gooey.
We're going to get to the desk top and it's actually open a terminal.
So the shell is operating from in this directory.
You can right click and you'll notice that you'll see an option here that says Open in terminal.
OK.
So if we click that you can see that we've got a terminal that's automatically opened in the desktop.
So say for example you're doing stuff in your navigating files in your data in your or your documents
folder.
OK we've got some files in here let's say.
Then you could actually just right click and click Open in terminal and you directly now operating in
your terminal.
From within that documents folder.
So you know if you're doing stuff graphically and then you want to switch the terminal and then switch
back and this is a nice shortcut to be able to use OK so you've learned a whole bunch of stuff in the
last three videos or so about navigating the Linux file system so I just wanted to take a bit of time
to have a quick recap of what we have learned to make sure that it's all sunk in.
So you know that you use the PWT command to print the current working directory that the shell is operating
in and it will print an absolute path to where on the file system your shell is currently operating.
You can use the ls command to see what's around you when you are in that directory it is a list so the
contents of the directory folders are in blue and files are in white but you can make that easier to
see using the the capital f option.
And we went through several other options that the ls command can have to make you know viewing things
and viewing files in the in the command line.
A lot easier.
You saw that the cd command can be used to change directory or move to a new location on the file system.
And you saw the absolute paths are paths that start at the very base directory of the file system so
the slash and relative paths are the paths that start from the directory that your shell is currently
in.
So relative paths are usually easier to type but absolute paths are very clear as to where they end
up.
OK.
Now every directory has the dot and dot dot.
Hidden folders that you can see using the ls command with the option and the dot the one dot is four
means the current folder and the two dots Riffe refer to the parent folder of where you currently are.
So if you did CD and then did dot dot that would move you up a folder OK because it's saying Go up go
to the parent folder where I currently am and if you did see the data then that would just basically
keep you where you wouldn't make any difference.
OK.
Now tab auto completion we saw in this video and we saw that tabbouleh commission is a really useful
technique to speed up typing and avoiding errors.
And if you press tab and nothing happens just hit tab twice really quickly and it will show you several
options that are conflicting and you can just then type out a bit more to make sure that it selects
the one you want.
So like we saw when we print when we type the capital D it wasn't working but if it's press tab twice
we could see that it was clashing with documents downloads and desktop.
And then we could modify their own to make sure tabel to completion worked.
But you use tab order completion all the time it saves you so much time and so much hassle.
It's a great great feature that the show has and it can also be used anywhere not just when navigating.
So if you're if you are you know trying to enter an argument to a command and it's a file path you can
use tab auto completion.
There is why it's not just when using CD or ls or whatever it might be you can use it for pretty much
any command.
And if you want to open up a terminal where you currently are when you're navigating graphically using
the graphical user interface just right click and click Open in terminal and a terminal will open up
with the current directory being exactly where you were when you opened that terminal.
So that's a really useful features why if you just need to make some quick edits on the terminal and
then shut it again and get back to doing what you are graphically.
It's a great great feature.
So make sure you keep hold of that.
So we've got a whole bunch of stuff in the last few videos and now you should start feeling comfortable
with how to navigate you just use Peter Beattie to see where you are.
LS to look around and see to move and in the next video we're going to start discussing file extensions
in Linux because they don't work like they might do on other operating systems and there's quite a few
core freedoms that fall extensions that you have when working in Linux.
So for that goodness I'll see you in the next video.