Hello these beautiful people and walk into this video all about file extensions in Linux now an operating
system such as Windows file extensions allow you to tell what type of file that you're dealing with
at a glance.
For example we know that files with names ending in Dr XTi are text files and files with names ending
in Dot J-P or PNB are likely to be images in Linux font extensions usually don't matter and the system
tends to look at the contents of the file rather than just its name but sometimes file extensions really
do matter.
So in this video we're going to take a bit of a deep dive into understanding file extensions in Linux
and shine some light onto their strange behavior.
And by the end of the video you'll know what freedoms the Linux operating system gives you when naming
your files.
What interesting things can happen and what you need to be aware of.
And you'll also have a new command in your tool kit that will help you when dealing with files on your
file system.
So this is all very useful stuff very exciting stuff.
Let's go ahead and jump right into it.
All right so I've gone ahead and put some files on my desktop.
First of all I've got an image of tuks the traditional penguin logo for Linux here in P and G format.
Now talks in case you're interested is short for the word tuxedo which is a fancy type of black and
white suit usually worn by waiters and possibly just people at high class parties.
The penguins are said to look like they're wearing little tuxedos because of their black and white coloring.
And that's where tuks gets his name from a tuxedo.
In case you were interested but besides a picture of the lovely talks here on random trivia I've also
got a text file here with some Shakespeare in it called Shakespeare doc text and I also have a spreadsheet
file with some random numbers in it.
OK so let's go ahead and take a look at the file command to see how Linux handles file types.
So if I go ahead and open a terminal using the control alt anti keyboard shortcut and just drag it out
the way so we can still see the files.
I'm going to introduce you to a new command called the file command.
Now the file command will tell us basically what type of file we are dealing with.
So for example if we tried to have a look at tuks here.
If we do file took it stop here and we actually took it to our desktop first shift over to a desktop.
Clear the screen and do file tuks.
Actually just just so you see I can actually just with you.
Go ahead and press tab and it will auto filled as well just showing you the table to completion works
perfectly fine for filenames just like it does for folders so it's a great great thing that we learnt
in the last video.
OK so let's have a look file of talks stop DNJ and it will tell us that this is P N.G. image data.
It will tell us the size of the file and loads of other stuff as well.
OK but it tells us the file type.
OK now if I rename tok stop DNJ.
OK if I rename this to took start JP G.
OK which is another type of image file.
You can see there's been renamed there but I to do that again.
OK try file of took stock JP and let's see what happens.
Now you can see here that it still says that it is a P and g file.
Now this is important.
Point number 1 in linux file extensions don't matter.
Ok unlike Windows Linux doesn't determine file type.
Using the file extension.
But instead it reads a piece of code inserted at the top of every file and that piece of code is known
as a header and it serves as a kind of label for Linux to read and when Linux reads that label it knows
the file type.
So changing just the name of the file won't make a difference because that file header won't have changed.
OK so here we have some Shakespeare script in text format.
If I open the up you can see that there is plenty of text in there which I just copied and pasted from
Romeo and Juliet.
OK so this kind of stuff that I do so when we check the file type we have here if we do file Shakespeare
to text it will tell us that it is an ASCII text file.
Ok but now if I try to turn this into a PTF So if I rename it and try to say OK this is now Shakespear.
Doc PTF OK and rename it.
Now the system appears to have changed the icon right.
It looks like that's a PDA file.
But if I try to run the file from command again for Shakespeare or PTF it still tells us that it's ASCII
text so Linux read the Linux read the header of the file and saw that it was still a text file.
But what happens when we try to open it because it looks like the system thinks it's a PTF because you
can see the logos changed but it's still telling us it is a text file.
What's going on there.
Why is it think it's different if we try to open it what happens.
Well now we get an.
OK which is the default program to open files with names ending in Dot PTF is a PDA reader.
When we try to open this file in the PDA reader we get an error from the program as it's trying to open
our file is a PDA file and what the system basically did is say ah that's a file that ends in Dot PTF.
It's probably a PDA file.
So let me be helpful and allow the user to open it in a PDA viewer.
Now obviously a PDA reading program isn't designed to read text files is designed to read PTF.
And that's what's causing the issue here.
Now this is import this is an important distinction to make.
Important point number two although the operating system will know what file format the actual file
is by reading the header.
The extra programs that are installed on top of the operating system such as this PDA viewer are trying
to open the files that might require a certain formats or the file extensions in order to work.
So what's happening is it all this to make this automatic you want to open as a PDA it just saw the
file name it just looked at the file name but the content is still text.
And it says here are a file type plain text is not supported but it got the program got tricked it saw
the file name and that's why it wanted to open it as a PDA.
If I rename it back to text just change the text change back.
You'll see now that it will open fine as a text file.
OK so that's the important distinction to make there the programs that are installed on top of the operating
system such as PDA views and the fact that they might need the file to have a specific file extension
in order to open them.
But the operating system itself does not care.
So this is a bit more detail if I take a look at the spreadsheet here.
It's called data O.D. as if I do file of data that odious.
OK.
It says that it's an odious forward transfer open document spreadsheet.
Now this means we can open it up in Libris office calc which is basically the Linux version of Microsoft
Excel.
OK all the Apple equivalent is like the spreadsheet program.
OK.
And it's got it's got a few numbers in there.
But if I close the spreadsheet and rename that for example to adopt Ex-Sea file.
OK.
So if I rename it to data RTX to rename that.
OK you can see that now it wants to be opened up in adult text format.
OK.
And now I tried to open that up in Libris office calc so if I click here I type calc and it comes up
Libra is calc.
Wait for that to boot up.
File Open go to my desktop so home and then desktop and then try to open up data RTX day and you can
see now that we've got all kinds of problems happening here.
OK so if I try to just open it like that a strong click OK.
We're going to get an error.
OK.
And this is because the DOT TXI file extension is fooling Libris office calque libral office calque
made the mistake of reading the file extension and trying to open the file as a dot.
T x t file.
OK.
Where is the actual content as we can see here is a spreadsheet file it's not a text file.
Ok but if we rename that back and we rename it so that it's dated.
Yes.
Now it will open fine.
So this is the important distinction that we need to make and to hammer this home the file extension
isn't important to the Linux operating system but it might be important to the software packages that
we install on top of Linux.
So do bear in mind that don't basically don't give your file names really weird file extensions that
don't match their content because it might confuse third party software that is installed OK even though
you don't necessarily have to.
OK so let's give the spreadsheet a completely unknown try something else.
This is something quite interesting.
Let's give the spreadsheet a completely made up file extensions.
If I call it spreadsheet dot Shambhala OK I'll call it spreadsheet datcha blah.
That was interesting.
Notice how it automatically still wants to open it up in the spreadsheet software.
Now we notice here that we didn't fool the the the software and it still knows it's an odious file and
we can actually open it up if I just go ahead and double click the it's going to open up perfectly fine.
You see we've got our data in here.
No funny business this time.
So why can this system why can it open up a weird file name but not a simple one like Dotti XTi.
Well the reason is the software just simply didn't recognize the Dutch pablum file extension so it might
have looked to the operating system to help determine the file type instead.
But when we called it a Datti XTi file huh.
When we actually named it directly to be Datti XTi the software thought it would be a bit clever and
it thought aha I know how to deal with this and it made a little bit of a shortcut to itself and was
like I'm just going to open this automatically as a text file.
But that assumption was wrong in this case because the content is a spreadsheet.
We just named it Dotty XTi and that caused the program to throw an error when it found out it wasn't
a text file after all but actually was a spreadsheet.
The bottom line is have a lot of freedom to name files what ever you want in Linux you can even call
them.
You can even give them file extensions like Dot shoeblack.
Which of course you couldn't do in any other operating system.
This is common for having files.
For example if I just try and copy and paste this if I copy and paste this file you know you might have
a backup.
You might for example call 1 file an original So you'd say OK I'm going to call this one dot a ridge
and then I'd call this one.
Maybe I'll call in the one dot back or you know a copy and call it dot dot dot copy or something like
that.
OK and this is how you might name your files.
I believe this is the original this is the copy I can see just by looking at the file name without actually
affecting the way the system works.
So this is sometimes used to allow people to read file extensions that are a lot more human readable
than you know things like dot odious or dot whatever.
Ok but just make sure that if you name your files in such a way don't give them file names that might
confuse the software that you expect to open them because not all softwares like to play ball with strange
file names.
OK so that will bring a discussion of Linux file extensions to a close.
So it's a summary of what you learn in this video.
You learn that you can use the file command to know for sure what type of file that you're dealing with.
Or you know that file extensions aren't important to the Linux operating system which means you can
name files whatever you want.
Yes even DOT shoeblack.
But while you're doing that make sure you try not to confuse third party software that might need to
open the file because it might be expecting specific file extensions.
And if you try to confuse it then you know you'll just get errors in a very very bad time.
So coming up next in the next video we're going to take your command line skills to a whole new level
by looking at the concept of wild cards.
So let's say you had a really messy desktop and you wanted to move all of your images to one folder
and all of your PDA to one or the folder and all of your spreadsheets and office falls under the folder
using the command line.
How can you use a command that's actually so specific.
Well you can do that using wildcards.
Wildcards allow you to make your commands really really specific and also really general thereby allowing
you to level up your control over what commands actually operate on.
Now this is an incredibly useful ability when dealing with files so for another dose of epic superpower's
I'll see you in the next video.