Hello you beautiful people are welcome to this video.
Well you're going to be learning about wildcards now other than having an awesome name.
Wild cards are very useful tools that will make your commands a lot more precise a lot more expressive
and a lot more powerful.
Now in this lecture you're going to learn about the most common types of wildcards and you'll see how
they can be very useful for manipulating files in Linux.
By the end of the video you'll know how to use some of the most common types of wall cards and you also
have the ability to create more powerful commands.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
OK.
So first let's take a look again at the L s command now the ls command will list the contents of every
directory that we give it a valid path to.
So for example let's say we wanted to list the contents of our documents directory.
We could do ls and then give it a path to our documents directory.
OK so when you slash that maybe we'd throw in a bit of tab completion and get it to list our documents
or if we're already in our home folder like we are now as you can see we could just say list list out
documents and that will do fine.
But what if we wanted to have a look at what's inside our documents folder our downloads folder and
our Pictures folder at the same time.
Well it's clear the screen the way we do that is we just say less than documents bit of cheeky tab order
completion downloads bit of cheeky Tabata completion and some pictures with a bit of cheeky tabel to
completion and then if we go ahead right now you'll see that we can actually see the contents of each
directory listed.
So far so good.
But you can see how manual of a process this was right where to type out documents then type out downloads
and then type at pictures even with even with tabel to completion in order to pass them as common arguments
to the ls command.
Now wildcards are basically special symbols that the shell interprets to have a special meaning.
The idea behind wildcards is to build up powerful patterns known as regular expressions so that instead
of typing out every command line argument manually you can instead say something like hey linux make
this command act on anything that matches this pattern.
The patterns are known as regular expressions and you can think of wildcards as being some of the useful
building blocks for creating regular expressions and using wildcards to build regular expressions gives
you lots of flexibility and control of how your commands work and can save you a whole bunch of typing
and using regular expressions make sure commands a lot more expressive.
So for example instead of expressing the ls command like list out the contents of this folder and this
folder and this folder which is the way that we would usually be using it with comma non-arguments right
we'd be saying LS Do documents and downloads and pictures downloaders down downloads and pictures.
OK.
That's how it works.
You've got to list them manually.
Instead you could just do something like hey wouldn't use list out the contents of every file starts
with the letter D.
For example if you're removing files instead of saying remove this file and this fall and this fall
you can say remove every file in this folder as long as its name ends in Datti XTi for example.
Or if you're copying files instead of saying copy this file this far in this file you can say copy every
file from this folder and to this other folder as long as its name ends with Dot PTF case.
So now that we understand that we're using wild cards to build these patterns these regular expressions.
Let's start building some regular expressions using wildcards.
And then one of the most used wildcards is the asterisk or the star wildcard.
Now I find the star by pressing shift and eight on my keyboard the first shift in eight.
I get the star come up if you ever use Microsoft accelerate you know a software spreadsheet package.
It's the symbol you use to do multiplication.
But I find that using shift and 8 on my keyboard it might be different on yours but it's that simple
we're looking for now wildcards.
Each match a specific pattern and the asterisk or the star wildcard matches any piece of text regardless
of the length of that text and it also matches numbers.
So let's say that we wanted to check the contents of every directory in the home folder.
Let me clear the screen.
If I play the screen instead of listing them all out OK because it's quite a few folds in here right
instead of saying OK LS desktop and documents and downloads and so on and so on.
All we have to do is just do ls star.
OK so if I press it if I do that you can see that it is just listed out all of the contents of the home
folder the desktop documents downloads music pictures public templates and videos all in one go.
So we clear the screen.
OK.
So how did that happen.
The reason that happened is because the store matches anything.
OK so you will you need to think of is when you give a command a regular expression to work with.
Imagine it putting as command line arguments.
Anything that matches that pattern.
OK.
So because the star wildcard matches anything it puts everything as command line arguments to the LS
command.
That makes sense.
Let's take another example.
OK so let's say I just wanted to list the contents of the folders starting with D.
So the desktop downloads and documents folders.
OK.
What I can do is I could say OK let's do less than a capital D and then a star.
Now the pattern is this bit.
OK the pattern is the D them the star.
OK.
And the star is one of the building blocks with the letter D.
So what we're saying here is listo then giving it as a command argument anything that has a D a capital
D and then followed by anything.
So basically anything that starts with a capital D.
So if I do the you can see that we just see the desktop documents and downloads and you can see that
they all match this pattern this D-Star they start with a capital D and then if followed by anything
they start with a capital D and then are followed by anything.
What if we just want documents and downloads.
Well they start with d'eau and then followed by anything right.
So if I do ls D O then anything you can see we just get documents and downloads.
But desktop is ignored.
Now something that is important to remember here is that these wild cards and these regular expressions
are case sensitive.
So if we did LS D and then astonied does have the DS lowercase you can see that we get nothing nothing
comes back because nothing starts with the lowercase D.
But if we do capital B.
Now that will work OK.
So that's really awesome.
Let me just clear the screen you've seen a few ways that the star wild card can be used to match any
text and you've seen some ways that it can be used to build regular expressions.
Now there are a few other common wild cards that you'll likely use when working with regular expressions
and wild cards.
And the first is the question mark wildcard.
Now the star wildcard will match anything regardless of length.
So for example if I do something like Stardock T-Rex t that could match anything as long as it ends
in Dot XTi t because if I do ls start up to 60 you'll see that we only see things that end in dot T.
X take.
Now it doesn't matter if what at the beginning of the of the comes before that takes t is 1 let alone
1 number long or you know a hundred letters long always full of numbers or whatever it doesn't matter
if it's a thousand characters long and it'll still match because the star matches anything.
But the question mark wildcard will only match one place.
So if I do.
Question mark.
Dr. XTi.
OK if I do ls now nothing will actually show up.
OK.
Because the question is this.
This says basically what this says is.
So anything that ends in Dot takes t but only has one thing before it.
OK.
So this would match things like a dot t XTi or cued up to 60 or Elda T-Rex T or 1.60.
OK you notice how they've all just got one place just before the Datti XTi.
OK.
The question mark is a way of saying it's like a placeholder for just that place where's the star.
It doesn't matter how long it is.
So the question mark wild card allows you to maintain the generality of the star wildcard because it
doesn't matter what it matches it can match a number or it can match a letter.
But it allows you to limit the length.
OK the star doesn't put a limit on length.
Where's the question mark.
Does but it doesn't really matter what fills that place.
OK.
Now you usually use the question mark wildcard when you want to build a general pattern but care about
the length of the filename.
OK so if we did something like question mark question mark PTF then that would match things like a 1
dot PDA or B2 or PTF or aid or PTF or you know Zed seven dot PTF or something like 7:7 dot pedia.
You see how we're just taking up two spaces and then not PTF that's what question clock question mark
or PTF would do.
OK we're saying we're going to fill it with two things.
Two spaces we're not sure it's going to go there but there's got to be two spaces two places.
And then PTF.
OK.
So that's how that works.
That's the question mark now.
Another type of wild card is called is the square brackets which are these ones here.
The square brackets here.
OK.
And the square brackets wildcard is similar to the question mark in that it will only match one place.
But instead of matching anything like the question mark will square brackets allow only allow the pattern
to be there to be more specific and only match the letters or numbers if they belong to a given set
of options.
Probably easier for me to show than to explain.
OK.
So say we had six files we had for a text we had file B directx t we had falce Dotty x t and we are
followed 1.60 for 2.6 T and for 3.6 D.
OK which intent.
If I do unless we actually already have those in a in our home directory.
OK.
So let's say we wanted to match the files that just had numbers in the filename.
So for 1.60 for 2.2 XTi and for 3.6.
But we don't want the ones that have Abian say OK to do this we could do less than file because the
name's got to start with file then open the square brackets and give it a bunch of options.
We could say 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 dot text.
Ok so what's this.
Basically everything in these square brackets is an option that could fill that one place.
So anything goes file and then either 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 0 any one of those then Dotti XTi case if
we do that you see that we get 4 1 4 2 and 4 3 but we don't get the A B and C because they're not part
of the options.
Right.
From a given set of files that just matches for one Faltu and for all three.
But I don't want you to know is how this wouldn't be possible using either the star wildcard or the
question mark wildcard if we do.
LS final question mark t the question mark will match anything.
AK but only one place.
If we do the star you're going to get though.
I need to LSN you're going to get basically the same thing as well because these don't restrict what
goes in that place.
The stock will have anything regardless of length.
The question mark will need just one place but it doesn't care what fills it.
The square brackets also only have one place but they allow you to restrict what goes there.
So they're like the most restrictive it's like a very restrictive kind of kind of Wockhardt.
Now you may have noticed that typing out all these numbers 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 is a bit of a hassle
right.
So the Schum makes it a bit easier for us.
We've got a shortcut we can do for 0 to 9 and that gives us exactly the same thing.
So instead of having to type out all the numbers it's it's much easier.
Which is really useful for when you want to work with the alphabet and you can go ahead and that will
work perfectly OK.
What if you want to notched two digits.
OK so what if you wanted something like file 11.
OK.
How would I do that.
Well the way you do that is you'd say LS file then for the first digit 0 tonight then just give it another
one zero to nine then Datti XTi.
OK.
So this one becomes the first digit.
This one becomes the second digit.
What if I wanted to have a number and then a letter.
Well that's easy.
Just change that to letters.
What if I wanted to have a number then a letter then a lowercase letter.
Well that simple change that like that.
And you can see the in file.
Then one space which can have the number zero to nine then another space which can have the number of
the letters 8 is adding uppercase then another space which can have the letters eight As'ad in lowercase
and then ends in Dotti X take.
So you can see just how powerful these regular expressions can become just by adding a few simple wildcards.
We could also what if we wanted to have the numbers 0 to 9 but also the letters A B and C you can do
that as well.
Just like that.
And that's going to show up in Shope exactly what you'd expect.
Anything that has the word file.
Then one of the numbers from 0 to 9 or the letters A B and C and uppercase then not text me.
If I reduce that to lowercase ABC they will just get 4 one two and three because these wildcards and
these organizations are case sensitive.
So you can see wild cause of really really powerful stuff guys.
And the the only three that you really need to know are the star which matches anything.
The question mark which matches anything but only from one place and the square brackets which allow
you to match just one place.
But they also like to define what matches.
OK so that's enough wild card goodness for now.
Wild Cards can make your commands a lot more expressive and give you much greater control over how the
commands work and using wildcards in this way to search for filenames actually has a fucking funny name.
And it's called globbing.
So if you ever hear the word globbing floating around it just means using wildcards to look for file
names just like we've done in this video so before closing out just take a quick recap of what we've
learned.
First you learn about the concept of regular expressions and regular expressions are basically patterns
that a piece of text needs to match.
OK.
And anything that matches that pattern will be passed as a command line argument to the command.
Now the star wildcard matches anything regardless of length.
The question mark matches anything but just for one place and the square brackets match just one place
but allow you to specify options that you know will actually be matched.
So unlike the start in the questionmark which will match anything the square brackets alays you choose
what will be match.
And of course you can just type letters and numbers in that you want specifically to appear as well.
So if I did capital D then start that means anything that starts with a D and then has anything afterwards.
You can type letters and numbers in there as well.
You don't just have to only use the star questionmark and square brackets.
OK so with wildcards understood you have a very solid foundation for learning about the different ways
to manipulate files in the file system.
Major the commands to create delete move copy and paste files and so on.
It's actually rather simple and when you learn them you might wonder what's the point of actually learning
how to use them instead of just pointing and clicking.
But by knowing how to use these commands along with wildcards you'll be able to manipulate hundreds
of files at once and with complete control to the point the pointing and clicking will soon seem like
a very slow and sluggish way of doing things.
Believe me.
So up next you can have a quick quiz to help you cement your understanding of wildcards because you
know practice makes perfect.
And then the next video you're going to lead had to create files and directories using some new commands
and you're also going to combine those commands with wildcards to make them even more powerful.
You'll even learn about something called brace expansion which will see which will show you how you
can create 3 folders with 100 files in each of them using just one or two commands.
Don't believe me.
Well I guess I'll see you in the next video.