Hello you beautiful people know one of the biggest reasons for someone to switch to Linux is to use
what is arguably the most powerful feature of the Linux operating system and that is the terminal.
Now if you've ever seen a film where a hacker or a computer genius has sat behind their computer typing
commands into what looks like a big black box on their computer screen that black box is called the
terminal.
Now at one time the entire Linux operating system was purely terminal based.
But as time has gone on more graphical tools have been developed up until now where we have these beautiful
desktop environments like what we see on a buntu.
Now fundamentally the main difference between using the terminal and using normal graphical methods
that you're probably already familiar with from even using a Windows or a Mac is that instead of pointing
and clicking with the mouse to control your computer you'll be typing with the keyboard instead.
Now Linux is unique in that the development of Linux is inseparable from the terminal.
And this means that knowing how to use the terminal gives you pretty much absolute control over how
your computer works by using the terminal.
You can do pretty much anything that you want with your Linux computer.
Now you can't get this level of control over your computer in any other operating system.
And this makes the terminal an incredible skill to learn.
Now although it's absolutely awesome I understand that the terminal can be a bit intimidating at first
so in this video we're going to start off nice and easy and I'm going to show you how you can actually
open and close the terminal in a buntu.
And by the end of this video you'll have taken a very important first step in your mastery of the Linux
operating system and you'll also be able to open and close at will.
The most powerful tool that Linux has to offer.
So let's go ahead and get started.
All right.
So here we are in a beautiful buntu desktop.
Now I'm going to show you how you can go ahead and open the terminal using graphical methods.
Now down the bottom left here you'll notice a a set of nine dots.
And if you hover over it says show applications.
If you click on that it will open up in a rather awesome way.
A whole list of different programs that are installed in your computer and you can just look around
here you can see like you know there's a calendar a calculator some office software.
You can keep scrolling down and there's loads of things.
For example the Firefox web browser a music player and so on and so on.
And like you know I encourage you to have a look at these and see what they do.
And this is how you can explore the files that are on your computer and things like that.
But if you scroll down or you click this the second button over here you'll see a program here called
terminal.
Another way to do it is you could just go at the top here in search and just type terminal and it will
come straight up.
Now if you just go ahead and click on that.
Here we are.
Your terminal window has opened up.
So in here is where we're going to be typing the commands for the course we might maximize the terminal.
We might make it a bit smaller.
You can move it around the screen and so on and so on there's loads of different options at the top.
For example you can open terminals and things you can edit copy and paste.
Change the zoom and so many other things play around with it as you wish but it's rather easy to open
if you want to close it just like you would on any other graphical system.
You just click the X at the top there.
OK.
So that's how you go ahead and open and close the terminal which is rather easy to do and it's Once
you've done it once or twice you probably won't forget it.
But there's also some keyboard shortcuts that will make this process a whole lot faster.
For example if you want to open the terminal using just your keyboard you can press control alt and
the letter T and you will find that there were all the terminal pops up and if you want to close it
you just press control and D.
And it goes away.
So you can see how quickly this how quick this might happen you don't control T and Open's control D
and it shuts.
OK.
So there you are.
That's how you can open and close the terminal using both graphical methods and keyboard shortcuts.
You've an excellent first step already and should start feeling a bit more like a Linux pro because
now you know how to actually open and close the terminal.
It's just like any other program on your computer.
It's not scary and it's actually rather easy to use as we'll show you in the next few videos.
But here's where your training really begins in the next video you're going to be running your first
commands in the terminal.
And trust me they're pretty awesome.
So for not goodness I'll see you in the next video.