Hello you beautiful people.
Now although each of the Linux commands are very powerful on their own the true power of the Linux command
line comes from our ability to change these commands together to build what are known as command pipelines.
Now each Linux command is designed to do one thing and do it incredibly well.
So by being able to combine together loads of powerful and feature rich building blocks you can create
very powerful workflows and pipelines without much work at all.
But in order to change the commands together and create these powerful workflows these pipelines we
need to understand a bit better how Linux commands actually take input and give output so that we can
link the outputs and inputs together.
So in this video you're going to learn about the different ways that a command can take input and give
output.
And by the end you'll be able to understand the different ways that data can flow into and out of a
command and you'll be ready to connect.
These commands these data flows together to build powerful Linux pipelines.
This is going to be an absolutely revolutionary time for your Linux abilities.
Because we're going to step up from taking just one command and learning about it to actually learn
how to change multiple commands together.
So I hope you're very very excited.
Let's go ahead and jump right into it.
So as you learned earlier each command is basically its own computer program.
Now a computer program is simply an automated way to take inputs process them and give outputs.
So here's a diagram that shows you the different ways that a command can take inputs and give outputs.
Now you can see that a Gen X command can take input from two places and will output to two other places
making a total of four possible ways to get data into and out of a conventional Linux command.
So the inputs are command arguments and standard inputs and outputs are standard output and standard
error.
You can see that three of these are indicated by the yellow dashed arrows and are examples of something
called a standard data stream.
You can tell this from their names because they all start with the word standard.
So you've got standard input.
Standard output and standard error and they're all standard data streams whereas the command line arguments
have a solid blue arrow and aren't a standard data stream.
So in this video I'm going to explain to you what the different input or output options are and you'll
also learn what is special about a standard data stream and how these data streams can be used to connect
commands together.
So let's Lester over to a buntu and see all this stuff in real time OK so for this discussion it makes
more sense to start with the outputs.
So let's start there.
Now when a command has run successfully the primary way that the data is output from the command is
on the channel called standard output.
Now standard output is something called a standard data stream just like a stream of water data stream
start somewhere and they end somewhere.
So where does standard output lead.
Well by default standard output will lead to your terminal.
So that's why when we type commands the output of the command appears on the screen.
So for example let's take the DATA command if we type date and press ENTER when we tell the date command
to run the output will be sent from the date command and flow down the standard output stream which
by default is connected to our terminal screen.
Therefore we see the data appear below our command.
OK.
So that's pretty cool.
But I want to plant a little seed in your mind first to come back to later and remember how I said that
by default the standard output of a command comes to the terminal.
Well the amazing thing about output data streams is that you can redirect where they go using a process
imaginative imaginatively called redirection.
So just like redirecting a pipe or change where water flows redirecting a data stream will change where
the data goes.
OK so of that seed has been planted and will come back to it in a moment.
Now the second type of output is something called Standard era.
So when a command gives an error message or a log message or something like that anything that isn't
the primary output of the command that is outputted into the stream known as standard error.
This helps keep useful output and log information separate.
So for example let's take the data command again.
If we make the date come on fail by giving it some invalid command arguments like this.
OK.
And then I press enter.
You'll see that we get an error message and it says invalidate blah blah blah blah blah.
OK.
Now because it's an error message it was sent down the standard error stream and because the error message
arrived at that terminal screen we can see that the standard error is also automatically connected to
a terminal just like standard output is.
But again because standard error is a data stream it can be redirected wherever we wish.
So now that we understand that standard output is where the main output for the commands go.
And that standard error is where the error and log messages for the command go and the both of those
are by default connected to the terminal.
Let's now turn our attention to inputs as mentioned there are also two ways for a command to get input.
The first we would discuss is another type of standard data stream which as you can guess is called
standard input.
Now standard input is by default connected to the keyboard.
So to demonstrate this I will introduce a new command called Cat.
Now we're going to discuss cat in a later section but I'll just use it now to explain the concept of
standard input.
If we take a look at the man page for cat so we type man cat.
OK.
We see in its description section the cat is not given any.
If it's not given any how can I say so given any command line arguments that that cat will read from
standard input.
So if no file is given then read it or it'll read from standard input.
OK.
So let's do that.
If I just type cat and don't give it any other form of input we can see the terminal kind of just hangs
there.
But if I start typing and I type hello and press ENTER we see that the text is read from our keyboard.
Are you from standard input and then cap processes and outputs the results to standard output.
Now because standard output is by default attached to our terminal we see the output appear right in
our terminal.
OK.
It's pretty awesome now because standard input is a data stream.
It can be redirected as well.
That means we can tell a command where it should read data from.
And this could be a file where we already have some pre-configured input or more powerfully.
It could be another data stream.
And it's this ability for data streams to connect together.
That makes them so powerful you can simply pass the standard output stream from one command to the standard
input stream of another then pass the standard output stream of that second command to the standard
input stream of the third command and so on and so on until you build up a very powerful pipeline connecting
outputs to inputs in this way is known as piping together commands and it's an incredibly important
concept in Linux as it's what makes working with the command line so powerful and effective as you you'll
see in coming videos.
Now the final type of import is command line arguments and we've already actually seen command line
arguments in action already.
For example when studying the command structure previously we took a look at the Cal command and we
saw by the way I'm going to press control and see to cancel this control and see my counsels and press
control not clear the screen.
So we we're using the cow command we saw something like cowe 12 20:17 which allows us to see the calendar
for December 2017 and the numbers 12 and 2017 were command line arguments.
And you can tell that because they were added on the command line as an input to the command.
We also made the command more advanced like this if you remember we had cow gave at the capital a option
gave that option an input gave the capital B option gave the option it's own input and then gave the
command to other inputs.
OK so it was quite complicated and it showed us the calendar for December 2017 with one month after
one month before.
Now the A and B options have their own command line arguments here the option has the command line argument
which is number one.
And B also has a command line argument of the number one.
And on top of those the overall cau command has 12 and 20:17 as its own command line arguments.
In case of this one argument for the option one I'll give it for the B option and two arguments for
the overall count command and the difference between command line arguments and data streams is that
data streams can flow.
They can be redirected and piped together command line arguments only associate with the command or
option that they're dealing with at the moment.
Now there are a command such as the X OGs command that allows you to blur the lines a little bit between
data streams a command line arguments.
But in general the difference is that data streams can flow and be patched together but command line
arguments are more static and still there is one other key difference to keep in mind though in the
not all commands accept standard input.
For example the echo command doesn't accept standard input but pretty much every command can except
command line arguments.
And if you want to know whether a command can actually accept standard input just check its man page
and if it's not there just to show you that it can awesome.
So in this video you've learned some incredibly important concepts as a quick recap we learned that
there are two ways to get data into commands and two ways to get data out.
The ways in our standard input and command line arguments and the ways out our standard output and standard
error there are three ways that start with the word standard are examples of standard data streams.
We mentioned that standard output is where the output data for a commando's and that standard error
is where the error and log messages for a command goes.
And by default standard output and standard error are attached to your terminal.
But this can be changed.
You also learned about standard input now standard input by default is attached to your keyboard and
is also a data stream which means it can take data from other places to using something called redirection.
That's right data streams can be redirected from their default locations to where ever you wish using
a process called redirection.
We also mentioned that you can actually connect the output streams of one command to the standard input
of another using a method called piping piping and redirection are incredibly powerful abilities that
Linux gives us.
And being able to use them effectively will basically give you super powers for interacting with your
computer in ways that you never thought possible.
And I hope that you're super excited because piping and redirection are going to be the topic of the
next few lectures.
So if you want to gain superpowers I'll see you in the next video.