Hellova you beautiful people know the last video you learned about the different ways that commands
can handle input and output.
And I see that in your mind the concepts behind the most powerful abilities that the Linux operating
system can give us piping and redirection.
Now piping and redirection allow us to create sophisticated command pipelines and move data around our
computer system with such unbelievable ease and flexibility that it's basically a super power.
So in this video you're going to begin gaming superpowers by learning how to perform redirection in
Linux and later on in the next few videos we'll be covering piping.
But by the end of this video you'll be able to redirect standard input standard output and standard
error to your heart's content and you'll feel much more like a computer genius already.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
OK so our main friend for this video is going to be the cat command that we saw a bit earlier.
Now the cat command is used to concatenate all stick together multiple different files.
You'll see how it works in more detail in a later video in the course.
But the reason I'm using the cat command in this video is because it's a simple command that reads from
standard input and writes to standard output so it fits our purposes of learning redirection perfectly.
So let's watch cat received data from standard input.
So if I just type cat here the cat command waits to receive some data on standard input.
Now cat needs standard input in order to run but because standard input is by default connected to the
keyboard cat just sits there and waits for us to enter something on the keyboard.
So if I type meow like that once we do it will output the same input into standard output.
And because standard output is by default connected to our terminal it it outputs that the same word
that we are under which was meow which is appropriate for the cat command of course and it outputs that
to the terminal.
Now in order to tell the cat command that standard input has finished we need to press control and see
and cap will stop listening and we will have back control of our terminal of our show.
OK.
So that's awesome.
So what if I wanted to change where the standard output goes instead of having it come to the terminal.
In other words how can I redirect standard output.
Well let's say that I wanted to redirect standard output to a file called output t x t to do that.
I would use a special symbol I would write cat just like normal.
Then I would type the number one and the greater than sign and then or type output.
Dr. XTi.
OK so let me explain to you what this means.
I want to remember that standard output is the name of the stream the output goes down like a standard
output isn't the destination but it's the name of the stream or the pipe or the yes or the stream that
the data goes down.
Now every data stream not only has a name like standard outputs and imports on that era but it also
has a number associated with it.
Standard Input is number zero.
Standard output is number one and standard error is number two.
OK.
So what we're doing here is we're changing the destination of where stream number one points.
In other words we are redirecting or changing the destination of standard output because standard output
is number one.
So that's why we talk the number one.
And we said put the number one put data stream number one in output.
XTi.
OK.
So instead of pointing the standard output stream at the terminal which is where points by default we're
pointing it towards a file called output directx t in our home folder.
And when I run that cat is still waiting for some input to run.
So if I type Linux is amazing.
OK.
And press ENTER we notice now that actually it didn't come back out to the terminal.
And when I tell that some of the input is finished again by pressing control and see first thing we
notice is the command is no longer running.
And as well we also don't see any output.
But if I click here to navigate to our home photos I click files and I when that window opens up if
I navigate to a home for a window see a folder or a file called output directx take an inside out put
duct tape XTi.
If I open it we see the text.
Linux is amazing.
How cool is that.
Now because standard output is usually what you want to redirect.
Linux makes it so that you don't actually even need to put the number one.
So if I just get rid of if I just delete productive X-ers press the delete key on my keyboard.
Yeah.
You don't actually even need to put the number one in this symbol here.
So actually if I just do cat then the greater than sign an output not dx t.
OK.
And I enter.
Linux is amazing.
OK.
And outputs it.
And then I press control and see to stop the command.
You can see that we basically get the same result output.
He actually has been created.
And inside there is Linux is amazing.
So that's a nice shortcut.
You don't have to put the number one there but it's useful to understand that for when you actually
come to redirect the other data streams maybe you might be wondering about the spacing.
So let's take the long form again the long form is Cat 1 greater than an output 60.
OK but I couldn't.
And so I could write it like this.
I could get rid of the space there and that would be fine.
But I couldn't add a space between the wan and the greater than like I so I couldn't do that have a
space in between that because this has to be one symbol that wouldn't work.
OK but this would I could have I could close the gap there so this symbol is preserved.
The symbol is preserved but I can have a space after it between that and output that state.
This is fine.
This is not fine.
OK.
Does that make sense.
B I just remember that the shell is interpreting what we write.
The shell is looking for one greater than or just greater than as a symbol and it has to find that symbol
in order to understand what it wants.
To do so if we break up one grid with a space now it no longer works because the shell isn't looking
for that.
OK.
Awesome.
So let's try adding more text to the file.
Let's try and add the text.
Wow.
So it says Linux is amazing.
And then wow.
OK.
So if we do that and we type Wow and then press control-C to stop.
Now when we check the output RTX the file we expect it to say Linux is amazing.
Wow.
Right.
But when we open it it just says the word wow what happened to the text it says Linux is amazing.
Well redirection by default will remove everything in a file before writing to it.
The fancy word for that is called truncation.
But basically what happened is looks emptied our file and then wrote Wow.
It was kind of annoying.
So how can we write to a file again using redirection without truncating it well to do that we would
write the redirection like this.
OK.
So you would write cat 1 greater than greater than 80 X-Tex you can see we've used two arrows there.
So instead of having one Ira we have two right after one another.
Now when I type Linux is amazing.
OK.
And I press control and see this too.
And that now we look inside politics.
We now have Linux is amazing.
After Wow.
OK.
And again the shortcut still applies.
So instead of having cat one gray and angry and by the way if that's shortcut right there I just press
the barricade.
Is it having one great regret that I can just have greater and greater OK when I do that.
And I say Linux is very amazing.
Did that stop then.
When I reload the file we can see the ads.
Linux is very amazing.
OK so this works just as well with just a great great great on and it works just as well as having the
number one because Linux makes it just easier for us because usually you're redirecting standard output
which is data stream number one.
So that's how you redirect standard output.
And this process as I said of using the double Aros is called appending to a file.
So in the interest of time we're going to cut our discussion short in this video and we're going to
pick it up again in the next video.
But in summary what you've seen in this video is first of all that data streams have numbers associated
with the data stream number zero is standard input data stream number one is standard output and data
stream number two is standard error.
And you can use these numbers to actually access the specific data streams that you want for redirection.
Now you've in this video you've seen how to redirect standard output which is data stream number one.
And it's probably the one that you will be using most of the time.
But what you need to make sure of it.
And this works for all data streams is you need to be careful of truncating your files.
You saw that when you use one arrow when you were a reader when you were redirecting some of the output
stage the shell would delete everything that was in the file or in the place that you were redirecting
to before adding the data in.
But if you use two arrows then you can actually append your data to the file you can add your data on
top of what is already there.
So just be aware of that.
So in the next video we're going to take a look now at how you would redirect standard error and standard
input.
So I'll see you in the next video.