Hello you beautiful people so in the last video you saw how to redirect standard output.
And in this video we're going to be picking that up and continuing by learning how to redirect standard
era and standard input.
So let's start with standard error.
How do you go about redirecting that.
Well some of there are works in very much the same way a standard output than the number for the standard
error data stream is the number to sort of redirects standard error.
You would type cat and then instead of one and then agree and unsigned which is what we use for standard
output you just have to because the data stream of a standard error is number two.
And this would redirect the standard error from the cat command to Arundhati ex-state and to append
the standard error to whatever is already in aridity XTi you would do the two arrows.
So remember the difference between the one arrow and the two arrows is the one arrow will delete everything
that's in the file before a pen before writing to it and so it will truncate the file.
And two arrows will append or add to what already there.
OK so let's demonstrate this.
The cat's command doesn't have the k option.
OK so if I do cat give it the k option and just type blah.
Right.
We're going to get an error and it's going to say Invalid option.
K try cat help.
For more information.
So this is an error message.
So therefore it was output on the standard error data stream and the standard data stream is by default
connected to a terminal and therefore we see in our terminal.
But let's redirect it to Arundhati XTi.
So unimpressed the up are ok to save myself some typing and I'm going to type the number two and then
a great unsigned and say redirect that to RTX XTi.
OK so I'm saying Run this and redirect the the Sendero to Arati active.
So when I press Enter we first of all we notice that nothing popped out on our terminal which is a good
sign.
When we open up our files we can see there's a file called aerobatics.
And when I open it we can see that indeed the error message has been sent to that location.
A common use for this kind of for redirecting standard error is to keep track of log messages coming
from web servers and things like that.
But a common mistake is to use just one arrow like we have here.
OK.
Because if I keep doing that what that means is it will delete what's in the file before before it sends.
Standard error against If I keep doing the OK.
Imagine a new era happens every time.
OK.
If I keep doing an open air 0.60 only the most recent error has been saved.
But if my Instead of having one arrow I have two arrows.
Now I'm going to append each area on top of each other.
OK.
Which is exactly what you want with a log file because you want to be able to scroll back and see what's
happened in the past because it's open again.
Now we can see that the errors are being added on top of each other.
So that's the difference between having the one arrow and the two arrows the two arrows pens onto what
was already there.
OK.
And that's really what you need for standard era.
Now you can of course redirect standard error and standard output at the same time.
So for example we could type the cat command and redirect output to output RTX t member that standard
output data stream number one and we could also redirect standard error to another place called error
XTi and we can make sure that we've that we append both of them by making sure the two arrows at both
places.
And then when we start something like Linux is amazing.
And then we cancel when we open up our file browser here.
We will see that we now have two files.
I would like to see an output that takes two output.
DXi contains Linux is amazing and standard error the error that actually doesn't contain thing because
there were actually no errors from this output.
It was a perfectly valid command there were no errors required but that is how you would go about doing
it.
So this is how we would we would be redirecting standard output to output to actually we can tell that
because the number one is here and standard error to a file called aridity XTi.
Now we can see what the number and the error is that standard error would be appended and so would output
ATX T.
Now we actually remember you actually don't need the one output text so you could actually just do that
and do say Linux is very amazing.
And when I look at that we can see output it has had it's text appended.
And again there will still be no errors in aeronautics because there weren't any errors.
But you can see here that without using the number one this will still work.
But you do still need the number two for standard error because that Shawk isn't available.
OK.
So you can only get rid of the number one for the standard output data stream OK.
Brilliant.
So you know I understand how to redirect standard output and standard error.
So how about standard input.
Well actually that's relatively straightforward at the moment the cat command is looking for standard
input from the keyboard.
What if we told it to get standard input from a file instead.
So let's make a file called input RTX T and type in the words hello world.
I so what we're going to do is we're going to use the cat command and we'll get output that now to a
file called input Datti XTi.
OK so we can make a file We're going to put in there.
Hello world.
Now when I cancel the we have now effectively created a file called input ATX D and in there we have.
OK.
So you can see how you can use redirection to create files like this as well.
Now let's use now let's try and read from that file using the cat command again.
OK how can we make the contents of this file this in politics file be read into standard input for the
cat command so that we don't have to type it later on let's say.
Well the standard input stream has the number of zero.
So what we can do is we can type cat the number 0 and instead of the grey of unsigned which is like
an output you actually use the less than sign.
Ok we say then input RTX.
Or as a shortcut.
Because the standard input stream is the only way that you can actually input.
You don't even need the zero.
You just put the less than sign my back.
Now when we do this we see the hello world message pop up on the screen.
Now this is because cat has read the file from standard input and output it to standard output which
is by default connected to our terminal.
Now here's a mini challenge.
OK.
I want you to get cats to read standard input from input ATX T and redirect the output to.
Hello Dr. XTi.
And make it so that that happens.
OK.
So go ahead and give that a go.
Pause the video now and try to get cat to read standard input from input that he XTi and redirect the
output to hello itx he then come back to see how you did
did you manage it was here's how I would go about it.
I would first redirect cat standard input so that it comes from that he XTi.
So we're just going to do by law and then I would put it to a file called Hello Datti XTi.
OK.
Now to make it easier to read I might add the stream numbers so I might say I am going to redirect into
stream 0.
But it takes t and I'm going to redirect from stream 1 which is standard output to hello 0.60.
It's totally up to you which one you use.
This might be a way to do it.
It might not be but just remember that 0 is standard in part one is standard put into standard error.
OK and here we can see that we're reading input ATX t into standard input.
It's quite easy to see that quite quite graphically and we're writing from standard output into Hello
Dr. XTi.
OK.
So if we go ahead and do that now we should be able to see that in fact yes we now have a file called
Hello tactics and when we open it we see Hello world.
Isn't that amazing.
That's how you can redirect data all around your computer.
Now here's one more mindblowing thing.
Everything in Linux is actually treated the same as a file.
Even terminals.
So let me open up another term along and use the shortcut control Altamonte and I get to open them right
next to one of the song and put one over here and I'm going to put one over here.
OK.
Now in the other terminal this one over this new one on the right.
I'm going to run the T.T. y command.
Now the TDY command will actually tell us where this terminal is located where on the file system it
is.
And we see it comes back with Slash dev slash PTSA slash one.
OK.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to redirect the the the content from input ATX tape.
So just like this.
And instead of writing it to a file I'm going to write it to this location slash def slash PTSA slash
one so slash def slash PTSA slash one.
OK.
And when I press Enter Oh my goodness we can see that the data has been passed from one terminal to
another.
It's kind of like a really rubbish instant messaging system right now but this isn't particularly useful
in itself.
It shows how redirection can be used to pass data around your entire computer and even over computer
networks I've heard.
So that's pretty amazing.
So how awesome.
You know know everything you need to know about redirection in Linux and the beauty of the Linux system
should begin to be making itself clear.
Now as a quick recap you learned that standard input standard output and standard error are streams
of data and like normal water streams that flow comes from somewhere and goes to somewhere redirection
is all about controlling that we're using redirection.
You can control where standard output and standard error streams go and you can control where standard
input comes from.
You also learned that these data streams have numbers associated with them.
Standard Input is stream number 0 and standard output stream number one.
And so that error is stream number two.
You then learned about the different symbols that can be used for redirection.
They are basically the greater than and less than signs.
Just remember that if you're redirecting output one gray of unsigned means that the file will be erased
or truncated before you write to it.
So if you don't want to lose the data that's in there.
Make sure to use to greater than signs to append data to the file.
In other words add data to what's already there.
Now there are a few more cool things that you can do with redirection but they're less common than what
you've learned in these last few videos.
So if you're curious I've put a link where you can learn more about redirection in the lecture resources.
But one question that must be burning in your head right now is how can I redirect the output from one
command to the input of another.
Surely there must be a way.
Well that process is known as piping and it is in my opinion that that's the crown jewel of the Linux
command line piping is probably the most important thing that the command line lets you do because it
takes all of the commands that do one thing very very very well and allows you to tie them together
seamlessly to do basically anything that you want.
Mastering piping would definitely give you superpowers so to master the power of piping and gain superpowers.
I'll see you in the next video.