So here we are you beautiful people you're about to learn the crown jewel of the Linux operating system
piping.
So in the last few videos you've learned that you can use redirection to change the location of where
you send command output and where you get command input.
But what if you wanted to connect the standard output of one command so that it flowed into the standard
input of another command.
Well that's where piping comes in and it's ridiculously powerful.
Each Linux command is designed to do one task extremely well.
So if you can continually pipe these highly specialized commands together and pass data between them
you can build advanced pipelines to do pretty much any task that you can think of and once you know
how to do it it will really feel like a super power.
So in this video you're going to learn how to build your very own command pipelines.
And then in the next video in part two you're going to learn how to make your pipelines more flexible
by using the T and the Exarchs commands.
This is going to be a great section of the course and you will not recognize yourself after you learn
what I'm about to teach you.
So I hope you're excited.
Let's go ahead and get into it.
OK.
So piping is all about taking the standard output of one command and connecting it to the standard input
of another command.
So let's take for example the DATA command the date command as we know will show us the date.
Now we can write the standard output of the date command to a text file called Date directx DXi using
redirection.
So it a mini challenge.
See if you can remember how to do that.
How would you take the data command and redirect it into a file called Date.
Dr. XTi give it a go and then come back to see how you did.
Did you manage it.
Well this is one way you could do it you could type the date command and then say I want to redirect
the standard output into data Darty XTi.
Now you could have just had the symbol like this where you could have put the number one to indicate
that you wanted the first data stream which is standard output to be written to date dot 60.
And if you did that massive Congratulations you're learning already.
But now that we've done it we are going to take a look at our file explorer here and we see a file called
Dottie XTi and we see that the date information has indeed been written into that file.
OK.
But now what if we wanted to just cut out the day of the week which in this case is Monday.
How would we cut out just the day of the week.
Well one way to do it would be to use the cut command.
Now you haven't seen the cook come on before but it works very simply and it's probably easier to show
you by doing.
First we want to read the date that takes the file into the standard input for the command.
So to do that we would type cut and then read into the standard input date.
Dottie XTi.
OK.
And you don't have to have the zero so you could just get with zero and just you know just do that have
the less than sign and then date takes.
And remember the space here.
This is optional.
Ok I'll probably just keep it because it looks a bit nicer.
Now what Cook will do what the cook does is it will cut up a file and give you specific columns.
So if we look at Dottie XTi you can imagine that the file is broken up into columns with a space between
each column.
The day of the week in this case Monday is the first column or the first field as it's known in the
command.
This would be the second field.
This would be the third field and so on and so on.
But we want the first field to make the cut come on and work correctly for us.
We think that two pieces of information using options.
First we need to give it the delimiter long form option so delimiter.
Okay.
And what that was a delimiter is is it tells you what divides the columns.
OK so we need to tell it that space is divide or delimit the columns because spaces are what divided
up these specific columns in The File.
OK.
So to do that we just type delimiter as along for a space and then in quotes put into the space.
OK so we're saying a space is what delimits this file or this input.
OK.
Then we need to say which field we want and now that we've told it how the file is cut up so we give
it again the long form option which is fields and then a space and then one.
OK.
And now what we've got there when we run that.
What we're going to see is we're saying to the Koch command.
OK read Date directx take.
It's broken up into columns with us each with a space separating each column.
And we want the first field.
Now when I press enter you can see that we get Monday as an output.
Isn't that awesome right.
That's pretty cool.
You've not seen the come on before.
It's very cool command but this this works but it's kind of clunky.
OK first we're writing the standard output of the date command to a file which takes up space on our
computer.
Right then we have to read that file into the command.
OK.
And maybe we would also after getting this data right we then have to delete this original file because
we don't need anymore which is another process that we have to undertake.
So doing it this way by saving the data into a file and then reading that file in two steps takes a
lot more typing.
It makes unnecessary files which you've got to remove or they just take up space.
It's just inefficient and awkward way of doing things.
So instead we can pipe the standard output of the data command directly into the standard input of the
cut command.
OK.
So if I just use the arrow key to keep what we have before.
Now instead of saying read into the read into the standard input command date XTi what I'm going to
do is I'm going to type date and then use this pipe symbol.
Now this pipe symbol you can find by holding Shift and then backslash on your on your most keyboards
anyway.
So yep that's the way it is on most keyboards.
But if it's not there on your keyboard if it's not possible by holding Shift and backslash just hop
onto a search engine and look for how to do the pipe symbol on your keyboard layout.
If you have trouble finding it you should should come up straight away.
But now what's happening is we're saying pipe the data from the date come on standard output into the
Kirkman's standard input.
Now because data up to 60 was effectively the standard output from the date command this is going to
have the same effect so will we press enter that we get Monday out.
And this happened all in one step.
So that's really cool we managed to take the data straight from the date command and pipe it into the
standard input of the command so that it can be operated on.
We gave the cook command some options that allowed us to cut out directly the name of the day of the
week.
Now I'm just going to press the up are OK and now I'm going to show you something really cool.
What we can do is we can actually put that data into file.
OK.
So we could actually save that using redirection into a file called today.
Xscape.
So check this out.
Using the date command to get all this information here.
We're cutting it out to get just Monday and then we're writing that data into a file called today that
tickety pretty awesome right.
So let's try.
Let's go ahead and press enter and know that that's gone out.
It doesn't come up on the screen this time.
And if we look in here we've got a file called today that takes t.
And if we click it we've now got Monday.
Isn't that awesome.
I think that's fantastic.
Now as a side note it doesn't actually matter where I put the redirection.
OK.
So I could have the redirection at the end here.
I could have the redirection over here and it would still work exactly the same.
OK.
That that works absolutely fine.
I could even actually put it in between the different options so I could put it here.
And I will also work exactly the same.
OK.
We're still getting today Dr. XTi with Monday inside.
So that's just something to bear in mind.
OK don't be scared about typing stuff wrong.
All of these are valid ways to do it but some are just a lot more readable than others.
OK but let's say that instead of redirecting we wanted to send the standard output of the cut command
to yet another command how would we do that how would instead of saving it into a file how would we
send the data from the command into yet another command.
Well it's simple.
You just add into the pipe.
OK so you just say OK let me cut that.
But no sorry let me just put under the pipe and then let's separate command.
I've got some options and then I've got some command line arguments and that's how that would work.
OK.
That this new command could take its own options its own command line arguments and it could also read
standard input from the command line so you can see how this works.
We take taken the day come and piping the output into standard input the cut command given the cut command
its own options.
Then we're piping the output into another command given that command its own options and its own command
arguments and so on and so on and so on.
OK you can just keep on going piping these things together doing what you want and giving them options
as you wish.
So this is what gives the the whole Linux terminal its power.
OK.
Up until now we've been doing things that are cool but not really necessarily useful but when you can
combine together really powerful commands and have them operating exactly exactly the way that you want
to impart the data between them and all over your computer it really gets amazing.
So you can see that this pipings can go on and on and you can see how to build a powerful pipeline this
way.
It's actually really straightforward you just pipe together different commands.
Isn't that awesome.
So let me ask you a question.
What if we wanted to actually keep the whole date in a file and then pass it into a pipe.
Well we can't simply use a redirection at the end here because we're already passing the the sum of
their part of the date command into the command.
Right.
So we can't really save it in a file because we're already passing it on down the pipeline.
And if we tried to do it if we tried to you know get rid of the end if we tried to just pipe the output
into day Dotti XTi if we do that then we just delete everything we've got in here.
So we can see the effect.
If I try this we'll see the all we get is just date dot t s t.
OK the whole data is saved in today duct tape.
But then there's nothing to pass on into the command.
OK.
This is because redirections a processed before pipes where in the shower.
So you find the redirection and do that before it ever sees the pipe.
OK.
And this basically breaks our pipeline.
So the data can't really go two places at once.
It well to make this work we're going to use a command called the T command and it's these kind of advanced
stuff that we're going to be showing you in the next video.