Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome back.
I left you with a bit of a cliffhanger in the last video where you learned all about the basics of piping.
Now in this video we're going to take what you learned about the basics in the previous video and in
this video we're going to level it up and teach you some advanced piping techniques.
So with the basic stuff you learnt last night's video about just taking the output of one command and
piping it directly into the input into the standard input of another.
That doesn't leave much room for flexibility whereas there's loads of really cool things that you can
do with your pipelines if you learn just a few more techniques.
So in this video we're going to go over those advanced piping techniques.
And by the end you have to make advanced pipelines using the t and x Ogg's commands.
So let's go ahead and jump into it.
All right so let's just have a quick recap of what we did in the last video.
So in the last video we use the date command to get loads of system information about our computers
clock and what we did was we passed that data into the cut command because we just wanted to cut out
the day of the week which is a Monday.
Now to the day of the week we have to say that this data is actually broken up into several columns
and each column is separated by a space.
Now another way of saying that is that each column is delimited by space that's a fancy word in computer
lingo.
And so what we did is we gave the the command a delimiter and we said the delimiter is a space.
OK.
And now once we've said OK Each column is split up by by spaces.
Which field do we want which column do we want.
What is the first column.
Now fields in the cut command are called effable columns in the cook commander called fields.
So we said Fields equals 1 and when we pressed enter that cuts out Monday.
OK.
So that's what we did in the last video.
Then I gave you a little bit of a challenge.
I said hey how can we go about actually saving this information into a file.
But at the same time also pass it down into the pipeline.
So how can we save it into a file but also pass it down into the cook come on so that it can be operated
on so we can get Monday out.
So we're trying to do two things at once so to do that we actually need to have another command called
the command.
So let's take a look at how the two command works.
So here's an image of how the tee command works.
Now put a link to the original picture in the video resources.
You can see here that we have a pipe between two commands so here's a command over on the left.
And we have another command over here on the right and in the middle we're using the command.
OK.
Now we haven't covered what the specific commands do.
It doesn't actually matter so much what I want to focus on is the T command in the middle and just on
that we're trying to pipe two commands together.
OK.
Now just like a T-junction in a pipe of water we can use the tee command to cause our data to flow in
two directions.
We can cause it to flow horizontally as well as flow vertically downwards into the files you can imagine
it working like that.
OK.
So this the team commander allows us to pass the data on to the rest of the pipe.
But it also allows us to keep it in a file.
OK.
So you can see here that we've got a commander on the left that is trying to pipe its data across into
another commander on the right in the middle there we pipe it through the tee command and the command
we give it a command line argument a file that DXi that could be any file name that you want.
And what happens is the data does pass all the way through from the standard output of one command to
the standard input the other.
But it also falls down.
You can imagine it falling down from your command line it like into a file called filed or ATX or whatever
file name you gave the command.
So that's how the command works.
In theory this is how this graphic works and let's go ahead and see it work in practice.
OK so never you understand how the t command works I just have a quick refresher of our command pipeline.
We have the date command which gives us a whole bunch of information about our systems clock and we
wanted to cut out the Monday or whatever day of the week it actually is OK.
So we take the date command and we piped it into the cut command.
Now we notice that the data is broken up into columns that are separated by spaces.
So we say hey come on we have a delimiter that's a space the data is delimited by spaces and we want
the first column or as the command calls it the first field and that gives us the day of the week which
in this case is Monday.
Now the challenge was we want to not only have that come out we also want to save the entire date AK
into a file called called full date Dotti XTi.
OK.
So here's how we would do that.
And then press the paroquet to get where we got before.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm just going to squeeze in here the command.
OK.
Now the command is going to put one of those like T-junction in our pipeline.
You need to imagine it in your head.
OK.
So what's going to happen is the data is going to pass all the way through the pipeline horizontally.
So it's going to pass from the date come on standard output and go into the standard input of the cup
come on.
So it's going to flow straight the way through.
But what the tee command is going to do is it's going to allow us to save the data vertically downwards
so you can watch it being like a big letter T A K like a big T-junction.
The date is going to go downwards into the file called full date.
Dr. XTi Okay.
So here we are today is going to go horizontal down ops either no internal about that is going to go
horizontally across.
OK.
And it's also going to go vertically downwards into a file called full day.
Dr. XTi because when we do that we see that the output of the day of the week is still happened because
that was passed through the cut Come on.
Come on spit it out to its standard output which is still connected to our terminal.
Boom we open up our file explorer we can see that.
Now we have a file called full date.
Dr..
I deleted all of the other ones we have before.
So we were starting afresh and now we have full date directx tape.
And when I open that well hey we can actually see that all of the data data has been indeed saved in
a file called full date.
Dottie XTi Isn't that awesome.
That's proper.
All right so what happened was the date command spatio all of its information all the way across the
pipeline and when it got to the teacup on the TQM I just took a snapshot of the data in the pipeline
and passed it down into a file called full date.
Dr. XTi so that file contains all of the data that's coming out the date command.
OK but then the data was passed on into the cut command which did some processing and that spatio the
day of the week which in this case was Monday.
No I've got a quick challenge for you OK.
And I think you can do it.
What are we to do.
I want you to instead of having the day the week spit out to the terminal I want you to see if you can
figure out how you can use redirection to actually cause that data to be saved in a file called today
Dr. XTi.
OK.
So instead of having the day of the week SpinSpotter to the shop bespattered to the terminal.
I want you to have it saved in a file called today Dr. XTi But also you still need to have the command
in he has to press the OK to get what you've got before and now do the redirection.
OK.
So I'm going to pull the video now and then come back and see how you did
How'd you manage it.
Did you do it.
Well this is how you this is how I'd go about it.
Right.
So I would just write at the end here because here's where the data is actually coming out from.
I would just have a redirection from standard output into a file called today.
XTi and it's literally just that simple.
OK.
So once we've done that if I go ahead and press ENTER we can see that when we open up our file commander
here we've also got a file called today Dr. XTi.
And inside there it has saved the data that day of the week which in this case was Monday.
Let me delete both files so we can see this in all its glory.
I've got no files and press the Parakey press enter.
And when we take a look we've actually managed to save all the data into full date doctor 60 and we've
also managed to save just what we wanted using redirection into today directx.
Isn't that awesome.
Right that's kind of.
That's really awesome.
So anyway so what we've got here is the T command basically takes a snapshot of the data that's flowing
through the pipe at that point and saves it in a file that you give it.
OK.
And then redirection will also do the same.
But once you've redirected standard output you can no longer pass it down the pipe.
OK so that's why we use the T command the command allows standard output to continue flowing down the
pipe but also allows you to effectively redirect it to a file and take a snapshot so that it's saved
there.
So another way of saying that is that once you've done redirection you can't do any more piping.
OK so once you've redirected standard output like we have here in the today text.
Ok we can no longer do any more piping down than a pipe I'm going to maximize the terminal we can.
Once we've done this redirection to 0.60 that's the end of our piping days.
But what we could do if we wanted to save all the data in today that takes to continue the pipeline.
Then what.
Then that's when the T command would come in.
OK so we do for example today docked here in the Teac amount and now we can continue to pipe.
Okay.
So just again if you do redirection of jackalope that means no more piping if you want to take a snapshot
but continue piping that's when you use the Teac amount and now I could continue piping on down.
Okay.
So I wanted to also cover the X Ogg's commands in this video but I think we're pushing it for time here.
I hope that that has made it clear what the tee command is in final summary here for the team and the
team command allows you to save a snapshot of the data and continue doing your piping whereas just using
redirection will save a snapshot of the data.
But you can no longer do any piping.
So if you want to keep building your pipeline but keep a snapshot of the data use the T command instead.
So in the next video what we're going to do is we're going to have a look at the X Ogg's command which
is a really powerful command that allows you to turn your pipes data into command line arguments.
OK so let's go ahead and I'll see the there in the next video.