Hello you beautiful people and welcome to Part 3.
Our final part of our discussion on piping now in part number one you learned about the basic concepts
of piping and you saw that piping is all about connecting the standard output of one command to the
standard input of another command.
And in part two you saw how you can actually pass data through your pipeline but also take snapshots
of the data as it flows through and save those snapshots into a file using something called the command
and the command is really useful because by doing normal redirection you break your pipeline but by
using the command you can save data but still keep your pipeline flowing.
Now we partnered with three we're going to take that understanding of piping to a whole new level using
something called the X Ogg's command.
Now remember piping is all about connecting the standard output of one command to the standard input
of another command.
Now not all commands actually even accept standard input.
Some only accept command line arguments and that's exactly where the X Ogg's command comes in.
The Exarchs command allows you to convert piped data into command line arguments for commands only except
command line arguments so that you can keep your pipe going without having to break it at any point.
So the Exarchs command is that missing piece it's going to make your pipelines basically indestructible.
So we're going to teach you how to use that and then we're also going to have a summary of piping start
to finish.
So make sure that these concepts really really sink in.
And by the end of this video you're going to be the master of piping concepts after you've probably
received the most comprehensive explanation of it that you'll be able to find anywhere on the Internet.
So there we are guys let's go ahead and jump right over now into a buntu and see this stuff in practice.
OK so let's take a look at the X Ogg's command works.
Let's say that we are again playing around with the date command for example and we're getting the data
that's coming out of our system.
Now what do you think will happen if we take the date command and we pipe it into Echo.
Now remember Echo is very simple if I just take Echo when I say give echo Hello it'll just say hello
back.
So what do you think will happen if I take the date command and pipe that into Echo.
Well you might think that when I press when when I press enter the date command will pass on the day
into Echo and it will spit out the date right and wrong.
Actually what happened is Echo doesn't accept standard input.
So what happened here this is a common mistake actually that people make when using pipelines for the
first time they try to pipe things into Echo.
Now Echo doesn't accept standard input.
In fact it only accepts command line arguments.
If I try to do this I type to echo Hello again even though I'm piping with the date command into it.
So I go ahead presenta you can see that it's only processed its command line arguments.
So the question becomes how could we pass the data from our pipeline into a command that doesn't accept
standard input.
Well the key is to convert the data from standard input into command line arguments so the command can
continue to work like normal.
So the way that you do that is that instead of pie instead of piping it into Echo directly you pipe
it into something called the X OGs command.
Now the X OGs command will convert the data from standard input and it will put it instead into a command
line arguments.
So now I do echo.
So I basically put it into exons and then give X args echo to work with.
When I press enter.
Now you can see that now it echoes out the date.
OK.
Isn't that cool.
Now I can also give echo its own its own command line argument so I could give it also Hello.
And what would happen is it will now process both except people process its own command line arguments
first.
So that's something to bear in mind but it did indeed Echo both of them out which is a lot better than
we have before now.
Now we can actually continue to pipe down because the data that comes out is still on standard output.
So basically X OGs is like a little plaster or a little fix for when for when a command does not accept
standard It does not accept standard input but only accept command line arguments you can use X args
to get around the problem ok and continue doing your piping.
So let's say that we wanted for it to echo out just the day of the week.
What we can do is we could say date POTA into the command just like we've been doing a million times
tell it that the delimiter is a space tell it that we want the first field and then you could pipe that
into Echo.
Remember this isn't going to work because Echo doesn't accept standard input.
So we convert the data from standard input into a command line argument using X args give tell X OGs
hey we want you to work with Echo.
And now we'll see that it pops out the day of the week which is Monday.
So let me give you a an example where this might take you this X Exarchs ability what it might be able
to do for you.
So for example if we take our full day got DXi far we've got some data in here.
Let me just create a new document here I'm going to call it Press Control and ask to save.
Yep that works.
I'm going to call it delete me.
Dr. XTi.
OK.
So I can make that call to delete me not to take them and we look we've got a new file in here called
Delete me not here.
Now there's a command that you'll be coming on to later on in the course in the in the section all about
and navigating the file system and things like that which is the section after this one.
But there's a comment in there called the r.m command.
Now they are in Cranston's for Remove it's the command that delete stuff.
And if I type delete me Datti XTi and I click end to watch on the left watch or just over here.
OK.
The file has been deleted.
So you'll notice here that we actually gave the r.m command a command line argument.
OK we talked on the command line.
We gave it a filename.
Now what we might want to do was you might want to have another file over here.
OK.
Called files to delete RTX these files to delete Datti XTi and in there I'm going to give it the names
of full date dot text.
And today that takes days if I put that in the full date RTX T.
And we're also going to have what was the other one today Dr. XTi OK.
So we've got a file that contains those two names.
OK.
Now we can read that file out using the cat command.
You've seen this before.
OK so if I do the cat command and I say files to delete you see how it gives me the output.
Now I can just pipe that information into the our income and nothing will happen.
OK.
Because the army command only accepts command line the command line arguments.
But what I can do is I can read the data and clear the screen.
What I can do is I can read the data from files to delete these filenames and Pessah into X args now
x args is going to convert that data into command line arguments for the current command of the r.m
command does except command line arguments.
So when we do that.
Notice if I just piped directly to the r in command it doesn't work it says it's missing an operand
it's missing a command line arguments.
OK but if I pipe it into the Exarchs command instead and then type r.m.
Watch what happens now over at the left.
When is it to come out the files got deleted because now the R M command could work.
What effectively happened is if we wrote our ram today Dr. XTi and full date dot cxi actually the other
way round because the file they were written in the other way round in the file.
It's as if we did this.
It's as if we wrote out this command.
This command here.
But instead we just read the file and piped the contents to another command.
So you can see that this is how you might potentially use the x command just as a bit of an example
rather than Rizzi you know just using the data command an echo all the time.
So over the past three videos we've covered a whole lot of stuff so let's just try and summarize it
all together in one place so that you can feel confident that you've got it all.
First of all you learn that piping is a process that connects the standard output of one command to
the standard input of another and by the way if you ever see these two words in orange SITD out in SDD
and from now on you know that means standard output and standard input respectively.
OK.
And it s t d e r r is standard error.
So if you ever see those things around.
OK.
So piping K'NEX the standard output of one command to the standard input of another redirection of standard
output breaks pipelines.
So if you're making a pipeline and you do some redirection you've broken your pipeline you could use
the pipeline from that point on will no longer work.
OK so some of that is just been redirected into a file by default it can't be continued to be passed
down the pipeline.
That is unless you use the T command so if you want to save a data snapshot without breaking a pipeline.
Use the T command instead and that will make basically an imaginary T-junction just like you might find
in pipes of water in your pipelines so that you can save your data and also having continue on through
the pipeline at the same time.
Now if a command doesn't accept standard input then as we know piping can connect standard output to
standard inputs so how can you still use that kind in your pipeline.
Well if you still want to pipe to it even if it doesn't accept standard input as long as the command
accepts command line arguments you can use the x OGs command instead and commands that you use with
the X Ogg's command can also still have their own command line arguments besides the ones that you piped
to it.
So you can still pipe data to it.
You can still pipe data as command line arguments and also give it its own arguments right there on
the command line but just understand that the ones that you type to be on the command line will be processed
first.
So that's a whole bunch of stuff guys.
This really is the most important part of getting good at the Linux command line.
If you can understand and you feel confident in what you've learned in the last three videos about piping
you have unlocked the crown jewel of using the Linux command line and you should be massively proud
of yourself.
And if you haven't then just go back watch these videos as many times as it takes for you to get it
down take some notes.
Practice try stuff out because I promise you the effort will be worth it and I'm really proud of you
for actually making it this far.
And so should you as well.
Now up next we're going to show you a little trick what's going to make your use of the command line
a whole lot easier.
And we're going to show you how you can use something called alias's to save your command pipelines
with easy to remember names so they can be just used much easier later on.
So once you've written a pipeline you don't have to write it again just use the name and it will come
up without any errors.
So for all the good stuff to learn about aliases and making shortcuts.
I'll see you in the next video.