Hello you beautiful people at the end of the last video I gave you a little bit of a teaser about something
called aliases.
Aliases are basically little nicknames for your commands or for your command pipelines that make them
a lot easier to remember.
Now in this video you're going to be learning how to create your very own command aliases.
So very exciting.
Now in this video I'm going to walk you through step by step.
Everything you need to do to create your own command aliases.
And by the end of the video you should have all the skills that you need in order to create easy to
remember nicknames for your pipelines so that once you've written them no matter how complicated they
are you can just use them over and over and over again without typing them all out just using instead
the easy to remember nicknames.
So this is super cool stuff.
And let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So the first thing you need to do to start creating your own command aliases is to create a special
file called bash aliases in your home folder.
So to do that to create the file what we want to do is want to click on activities at the top left and
then in the search bar here just type the word text and it should come up with the thing that says Here
text editor.
Just click on that and it will open up a new window where we've actually got a file.
Now there's a button at the top here where you can click that says save.
So I'm going to click save and in my home folder I'm going to type a file that starts that it needs
to be spelled exactly the way that I'm going to tell you.
OK.
So first of all you type a period or full stop.
Then you type bash B.
SH all in lowercase.
Then an underscore then aliases so a L R A S E S.
OK so that's bash underscore alias's with a period or full stop at the beginning.
Everything in lowercase and then go ahead and hit save.
OK.
So now we have our bash alias's file.
And actually I don't think for a minute we'll need the terminals so I'm going to close that as well.
OK.
So make sure it is spelt exactly as is appear.
Full stop then bash underscore aliases a Al-Ali a s.c.s everything in lowercase.
Once you've got the we should be all good to go.
So now you might be wondering why did we actually need to name the file with a full stop at the beginning.
That's quite strange we don't normally name files like that do we.
Well that full stop makes the file a special type of file called a hidden file.
So if we go back into the file browser here and we look in our home folder you'll see that the bash
alias's file isn't actually there.
Where has it gone.
Well it's a hidden file.
So it's kind of hidden but where it actually is if you click on this button here with the three bars
if you click that and then click on down here there'll be a checkbox that says show hidden files.
If we check that we'll be able to see that abash aliases fall has been created.
But there are actually also plenty of other plenty of other hidden files here that we haven't seen before.
But here we are here's our bash alias's file that we're currently editing as well as actually even some
hidden folders that maybe you didn't even know were sneaking around your system.
But anyway we don't need to worry about those fanatics just go ahead and click those three bars again
and undo viewing hidden files so it all disappears again.
So you know we don't have to continue looking at monsters under our bed and now we can go ahead and
actually keep editing the bash aliases file a case and another we're in bash aliases file making an
alias is actually really quite easy.
So here's the command that we want to make an alias for.
It's going to be a really long command with loads of complicated stuff in it.
But we can do this.
It's not there's nothing new it's just quite complex it's quite long so we're going can type the date
command.
We're going to pass that into the command.
We've seen this a jillion times right.
We're going to take that the delimiter is a space and we're going to get the first field.
OK.
Now we were also wanted to have a copy of that data.
We want to take a snapshot so we can take the T command and save that in a file in our home folder called
full date.
Dr. ex-state Okay so we're doing well so far then we're going to take a snapshot of just the day of
the week.
We're going to save that in our home folder in a file called short date tactics.
And then everything that comes out we're going to pass into the echo command but also give the echo
command its own argument.
That's quite a long comment.
Right.
So we're doing a lot of stuff in here.
But the point is that it's long because you can see how useful alias's are right.
So the only thing to make it work for your computer is instead of having Ziyad Well unless in the one
in a jillion chance that your name is also Ziyad and you chose it to be your user name on your virtual
machine which I think is unlikely.
But if you are semi message but otherwise just go ahead and change that with your username so that it
matches the correct path on your computer otherwise you're going to start getting errors like I said
if you if your username was you know Saly just change it to me.
Sally OK but mine was Ziyad so I'll keep it at that.
OK.
So this is the command that we want.
Let's make an alias for it.
Let's say for example we wanted to instead of typing out this massive command every time we wanted to
do it instead of just typing it out.
What if we wanted to just type get dates and that was going to be Alias.
What all we have to do is just type the word alias which is a special word then press a space then get
dates an equal sign and then an apostrophe on either side of that come on so you can see there's an
apostrophe here.
And there's an apostrophe here.
OK.
So like a single quote on either side of the whole massive command then alias at the beginning.
The name of the alias an equal sign and then quotes on either side of the massive command.
So what we're saying is hey I want to make an alias called get dates.
That is exactly equal to this command.
Now when we save it and close it.
So we need to close the the editor so we go with click on these three these three bars over here.
Click Close OK and close.
All of this in general I think and just drag that down and close.
And when we open at terminal one we reboot our terminal that alias should be loaded OK so I want you
to think of these alias's as being like your own commands.
OK.
So if we try and run the get dates commands shall we call it.
And if we go ahead and press ENTER remembering that get dates was the name of our alias we actually
get some output.
So that's pretty cool.
Now if we go ahead and look in our in our home folder we'll also see that two new files have been created
to full date dot text and short date dot text.
So let's go ahead and take a look in for date that text.
We've actually gone and got the full date.
All the data has been passed into that and sure date DOT takes.
He has had just the day of the week passed in is not awesome.
OK.
Because this has come from the alias if I delete those and go ahead and run to get dates come on again
we see that the files have been created.
One more time with the same data in them.
So this is super cool right.
Like instead of typing out that really really really long Aliase really really don't come and every
time we wanted to get that functionality because we've created an alias and basically given a cute nickname
to the command get dates instead of the massive pipeline we can now get the same functionality but in
a much easier to remember way and the way that's actually easy to reproduce.
So that's really awesome.
But now let me show you something super cool.
OK.
You can actually also use aliases in bigger pipelines.
So think of your aliases just being its own pipeline right.
If your alias if that mini pipeline that you save can accept standard input if the first command in
it can accept standard input then you can just pipe to the alias and run the whole pipeline and then
pipe out of the alias and continue on it's like having your own little pipeline building block.
So let me show you OK.
Let's say that we wanted to have an alias for our command that showed a calendar with one month before
and one month after the current month so that the con for that would be cow.
Then a one be one.
OK so after one month before one month and we get the current month with one month after I'm one month
before the case that's the command.
If we go and head back in here click these three horizontal arrows horizontal bars sorry and show hidden
files.
Click on our bash aliases files open up and go onto a new line in the file.
Let's create a new alias for that command.
OK so we're going to say.
We're going to call magic short for calendar magic.
I'm going to type an equal sign and then you can actually type some speech marks.
OK you don't have to have the single quotes.
You can have speech marks as well.
I'm going to type that cow.
Then the option.
Give it.
Number one is its own argument then a B.
Capital B then one has its own argument.
And we're going to output into a file in my home directory called Thing Dotty XTi And of course remember
to replace this bit with your user name that you're using on your virtual machine.
OK so we're going to call that magic.
But the cow command here.
Right.
The cow command only accepts command line arguments you can't piped to the call command by default.
So to make this a valid pipeline that you can access this this whole Cal magic thing a valid pipeline
that you can pipe to.
We need to actually put the X OGs command at the beginning.
OK.
So let's just do that.
If you don't know what I'm doing at the minute just bear with me OK which is making a building block
this whole thing that we can pipe to.
OK.
So that's what we've done right there now whatever is going to be piped to cow magic will actually be
piped to the X Ogg's command which will then convert the data from standard input which Cal doesn't
except to command line arguments which cow does accept.
And so therefore the whole pipeline will work.
It's going to be awesome.
Just trust me.
OK.
Let's go ahead and do this let's close that save and close the close the close everything and close
our terminal and reboot it.
The press control alt and t talked about terminal nine.
I echo 12 20:17 into Cowal magic what's going to happen is I'm going to be echoing this data as command
line arguments to the magic command.
So what we're expecting to happen is that we're expecting that we're going to get December 2017 the
calendar for it with a month before and a month after.
OK.
Save to a file in our home directory.
So if I press Enter we don't get any output.
But if we go into our files here we will see that there is a file in here called things that takes take.
We've actually managed to save the calendars for December so December 2017 one month before and one
month after into a fall called things that takes t in our home folder.
And the reason that happened is probably a lot easier to see if I actually get one of these hidden files.
No no.
I will I will keep them because otherwise I'll lose where I am.
But what happened is we echoed we basically passed to the ex OGs command.
Two pieces of information at 12 and 20:17 which were then given as command line arguments to the calendar
command.
So you can see how all this stuff is starting to tie together and we've made a mini pipeline called
cowe magic that will now be able to run a command whenever we want so we don't have to type out this
ugly thing we just have to know how magic and because we made it possible to pipe to the first command
in our alias the whole pipeline will work and we can use it like a mini building block in whatever programs
that we want to make.
So how awesome is that right.
Can you see how crazily powerful the ability to write alias's for pipelines and use those aliases in
the pipelines can actually be right.
The possibilities really are limitless with what you can achieve with that ability.
So let's just leave it there.
I'm going to leave your mind blown with that.
Go ahead and now take a summary of what we've learned about alias's.
OK so that's enough of being mind blowing for now.
I hope you're as excited as I am by what you've learned in this video that aliasing aliasing is an absolutely
incredible ability with really limitless potential if used in the right way.
So let's just have a quick recap to make sure that you've got it all down.
So in this video first of all you learn that an alias is basically just an easy to remember nickname
for a command or series of commands joined together in a pipeline.
Now to create an alias you need to first have a file called dot dash underscore aliases or in lowercase
in your home folder.
And that's where you actually put your data file that you actually put your aliases in and these aliases
therefore will be specific to your user.
Now as a bonus point you learn a period or full stop or a dot at the start of a file name makes that
file hidden.
So and you also saw how to turn on or off the visibility of hidden files in your file viewer.
OK.
Now inside the bash aliases file.
So that is actually quite easy to make an alias.
Right.
This is the way that you do it first you type the key word alias all in lowercase.
Then you put a space and then you put the alias name.
So as we get dates or it was call magic or whatever you want to call it that's your nickname.
OK.
Then you put an equal sign without adding a space with space at all between the alias and the equal
sign you put in.
So you just put an equal sign immediately.
Then you open some quotes.
These quotes can be either single quotes using an apostrophe or you know normal double quotes like you
would use for speech marks again without any spaces without any gaps.
Between the equal sign then you just create your pipeline or you use your command.
Again you can have options and command monogamists just like you normally would.
OK these can go on for as long as you want.
OK.
Now as long as you make sure that you restart your terminal you'll then have access to that alias forever.
And as another bonus point looking you look you get two bonus points in the summary should be should
be feel very spoiled.
But as long as you make sure the first command in that alias in that pipeline can actually be piped
to OK then you can just pipe to the alias pope to the nickname and you'll it as if you're piping to
the whole pipeline.
If I say the word pipe one more time I'm probably going to go insane.
But you get the point right.
If you make it so that your pipeline can be piped to either by using the X OGs command or by just using
a normal command that can accept standard input then instead of having to you can basically use the
alias that many pipeline as a tiny building block in some massive other pipeline that you're building
to create a really epic bit of functionality.
OK so alias is used in the right way with what you've learnt about piping and X args and all sorts of
stuff making these long pipelines is an epic epic ability.
So now you can build your own command pipelines and even save them for use later when you understand
that basically anything in the Linux operating system can be modified using command line.
You really are the crown jewel that makes the Linux operating system so amazing because anything can
be edited using the command line.
And you know had to create these come on how to use these commands and piped them all together to do
whatever you want.
You've really got a master key that take your computing to the next level.
But in order to take advantage of this all you need now are just simple building blocks to actually
build pipelines with.
Right.
So in the next section of the course we're actually going to be covering a whole bunch of those building
blocks because the next section of the Course is all about navigating your file system creating manipulating
files making folders copying and pasting files creating backups of your system and so much more.
But before we get into all that goodness I want to make sure that you understand everything that we've
covered in this entire section of the course first because it's been an incredibly foundational incredibly
important section of the course.
If you understand everything in this section you will not go far wrong with anything else you learn
when using Linux.
And I also want to make sure your Jewely congratulated for your amazing progress so far.
You really really deserve to have some recognition of what you've done in this section what you've learned
at how far you've come.
So in the next video we're going to have a celebration of your really impressive progress and a quick
recap of what we've covered in the section.
It's going to be awesome.
So review the section and some well-deserved celebration and praises.
I will see you in the next video.