Hello you beautiful people know the terminal is a very powerful tool that is designed to allow you to
issue what is known as commands to your computer.
Now the idea is that the computer will obey these commands.
We hope and make stuff happen as a result.
Now in this video you're going to learn how to issue your first commands which is very exciting but
as an aside this course is structured so that each section of the course has its own cheat sheet that
you can grab at the end of the section.
So don't worry about memorizing all the commands or rushing down to take notes to try out the commands
that I show you in your own virtual machine on your own computer.
And rest assured everything is all jotted down for you in the cheat sheets that you can get at the end
of each section.
That's awesome right.
So by the end of this video you will have run a bunch of Linux commands and you'll start to see a pattern
emerging in how Linux commands work.
So this is going to be a very important lecture it's going to give you that foundation is going to help
you understand what everything is all about.
So let's go ahead and jump into it.
OK.
So the first thing we're going to want to do is to open up our terminal.
There was a quick challenge let's see if you can remember how to do that.
Go ahead and see if within about five seconds or so you can open up the terminal.
You can do it using either graphical methods or if you're feeling particularly pro already use the keyboard
shortcut you learnt in the last video.
So you've got five seconds.
Give it a go.
Do you get it.
Well if so well done you're learning already.
Now I'm going to open up the terminal using the keyboard shortcut which is control alt and T and there's
actually a mental pop up.
Now I'm going to do it like that for most of the time from now on.
So don't be confused if you see terminal windows popping up all over the place as we go through the
course I'm just using the keyboard shortcut but to make the text easier to read on the recording I'm
going to view and click zoom in will make the font just that much larger.
OK.
So I should make it a bit easier to read when I type stuff.
But at our terminal windows open Let's run a fun command called Echo.
Now the echo command just prints out what you give it as an input.
So type with me the following command we're going to type echo.
OK then press space and we're going to type the word Hello.
Now when I press Enter I'm going to say it's the computer.
OK.
Actually run this command.
And when I press Enter we see Hello command to the computer.
So it's pretty cool.
Let's try that again.
OK.
We're going to say echo then type echo.
With a load of oze.
Ok then I get to press enter and what comes back is Echo.
Oh how awesome is that.
It's just like a cave.
So let's try now with another command called Cal.
So that's echo.
Let's try another command called Cal and Cao is going to show up a calendar on the screen.
So if we type cow just like that and press ENTER you can see that we get a calendar for the current
months for the current month with the with today's date also highlighted.
And now I'm doing this in October 2017 when you're watching this and doing it yourself it may be a very
different month but you get the point you type cow the default behavior is that you get the current
month with the current day highlighted but that's just the default behavior of the command.
OK now that makes Linux commands interesting is how you don't have to stick with the default behavior.
You can actually customize the behavior of commands to exactly what you want them to do.
So for example what if I wanted the calendar not just for the current month but for the current year.
But what I could do first of all I could type cow then 2017 and I can press enter and it's going to
give me the entire calendar for 2017.
And also it's going to highlight the current date.
That's pretty cool.
And with very little typing We got a lot more result of that.
Right.
But you can also give it something give each come on something called an option.
Now one option is something that allows you to customize the behavior of the command.
OK so I could type cow and instead of typing 2017 or I could just type dash y.
Now this would give the cow command the y option.
Now if I press Enter we also get the calendar for 2017 so you can see here cowled Ashwin gave us the
calendar for 2017.
Again highlighted with current dates.
So you've just seen two ways that you can customize icons behavior and give it input and you can give
it options and we're going to be going into a lot more detail about the difference between the two and
how they work.
But you may be curious at the moment as to what other ways you can customize commands but I'm going
to save that goodness until later at the minute I just want to give you a little bit of a bit of an
overview of some different commands that you can use on Linux so you can get comfortable with the typing
and pressing Enter and seeing result come back up on the screen.
OK.
So let's move on and take a look at another one for example.
You can see today's date using the date command.
So if we type date and press ENTER we see that we get today's date and time and time zone and year Pop-Pop.
OK so that's pretty cool.
It's quite useful command.
But at the moment you can see that we've got quite a lot of text not terminal.
Things are starting to get a bit messy.
We can clean that up a bit as well.
So to do that we can use the clear command if we type clear and press enter.
It's like we just cleaned up workspace and then we are we've removed all the text from the screen now
because the clear command is used so often there's a key there's a keyboard shortcut for it.
OK.
So if I just type echo and then put blah blah blah and you can see we've got some text come out of the
screen that the computer had blah blah blah but we can also use a keyboard shortcut to clear the screen
and the keyboard shortcut is your best control.
And the letter L.
Now we all would clear the screen and that's the way that I'm going to be doing it because it's a lot
faster and a lot easier than typing at the clear command every time.
But you feel free you do you just understand that if the terminal is all of a sudden having all its
text vanished that's what I've done I've just cleared the screen.
OK.
Now we don't have quite a few commands already.
So what if you wanted to enter a command that evented previously without having to type it out again
maybe it was a particularly long command we don't know what you can do is you can hit the up arrow key
on your keyboard.
So if I press the paroquet we see Echo blah blah blah top's back up if I press up again it's going to
go clear.
And again with the date again we see a cow and so on.
I guess you can keep pressing up and cycling backwards through the commands that you've already run
which is very very useful.
You can also look at your whole command history using what's called the history command.
So if you type history and press ENTER we can see all of our previous commands with the line number
associated with them.
For example we can see the line number for our echo command which is the number one let's say that said
that we are the one who was number one and not what you could do.
Instead of having to cycle all the way back up to number one like that.
What I could do is look a tide the exclamation mark and then one.
OK.
So exclamation mark on one.
And you can see that we've run echo Hello.
OK.
So let's let's have a look again and have a look at our history again.
We see now let's say we want to run echo blah blah blah.
The London flight is eight right.
So if I press the exclamation mark and press 8 and then press enter we see we get Echo blah blah blah.
So you can see that that's a bit of a shortcut to save you going back through potentially hundreds of
commands that you've run.
And you know you can you can run them a bit easier like that.
OK.
If you want to run the most recent come on that you've done you can just press exclamation mark exclamation
mark.
And again we see Echo blah blah blah has run again.
Now this history file can get quite long.
So if you want to clear the history of this it's kind of a two step process.
You can type history and give it the C option.
OK.
Then add a semi-colon then type history and give it to the w option.
OK so what that does is it clears the history and then actually writes those changes and makes them
permanent.
So when we do that and clear the screen and we look at history we can see that all we've got is just
a history quite literally and it's not something for reference for you it's not particularly important
but you've got to in this video if you want to refer back to it.
OK.
Now finally let's say we want to close the terminal.
Well to do that we could of course click the X button at the top right over here.
But you can also type the exit command and make yourself you know just look that much more pro So if
we press exit.
We can see that the terminal has now closed.
And also you could of course use the Control D keyboard shortcuts if I press control and D we can see
the terminals also closed as well.
Like I showed you in the last video and that allows you to type commands operate the terminal and also
close it without ever having to take your hands off the keyboard.
So there you have it you jump right in and I've now ran a whole bunch of Linux commands inside the terminal
so well done.
You've got your feet wet and we're moving as I mentioned to you you can get a cheat sheet which covers
all of the commands that we've covered in this video and all the other commands that we're going to
cover in this section of the course.
At the conclusion lecture of this section but the use case of these commands that we've covered in this
lecture may not be completely clear at this point.
And that's OK.
I wasn't trying to teach you all like a whole bunch of commands in one video.
What I wanted to get across in this video is that commands are executed by typing some weird text in
the terminal and pressing the enter key.
You've also seen that commands can be they can do a whole lot of different things and they can also
be customized for different behavior but they all seem to follow a semi similar kind of structure.
You type some text maybe you got some options maybe some input and you press enter.
Now being able to understand that structure is of incredible importance to mastering the Linux operating
system and leveraging the power of the terminal.
So the next video I'm going to show you how commands are structured in Linux and what we're going to
cover next will serve as a critical foundation for pretty much everything that we're going to learn
going forward and pretty much everything that you ever learn when you're using Linux if you use Linux
before but never really felt as though you've you know you got it or you felt that some stuff was missing
in your understanding it's probably because you weren't shown what I'm about to show you next.
And if you're new to Linux this is going to be the best place to start to make sure that everything
goes smoothly and you start to see the pattern of how the Linux operating system and the commands are
designed rather than just memorizing a massive list.
So for that super important stuff I'll see you in the next video.