HELLO YOU BEAUTIFUL PERSON.
Well.
Well you must be feeling super proud of yourself right now right.
You've come so far in this section of the course so to fully celebrate that I wanted to make a video
and have a quick recap so that you can soak in all the awesome stuff you've learned in the section of
the course.
So you started off with the very basics and you learned how to open and close the terminal using graphical
methods and by using And now beloved keyboard shortcuts.
And it was all very strange to you at first but you jumped right in anyway and you started typing and
using your first commands you saw the date command the Cal command and the echo command.
And you saw how to clear your term history.
We don't want any spies looking at history after all do we.
They we're making progress but it was all kind of weird and you probably weren't too sure of what was
actually going on when you run a command.
So then you learned the difference between the terminal and the shell.
You learned that the shell is what interprets the commands that you type just like you interpret the
meanings of words that you read.
And when you understood what commands actually were you learned the general structure of a command.
Learned the commands follow a command name options arguments structure.
OK.
Now because it became clear that although commands follow a similar structure they do vary quite a bit
in their usage.
They each have their own specific options and use cases and it would be impossible to memorize them
all.
So you learned how to look in the Linux manual you learned how the manual was broken up and you saw
how to search for terms and read the manual pages and how to learn new things for yourself and find
things as and when you need them rather than having to memorize everything.
So it's like having your own personal search engine for your computer which is pretty incredible in
my opinion.
Now then we took our discussion even deeper and you learned that commands can take input a standard
input and command line arguments and they can get output via standard output and standard error data
streams.
So I had to redirect these data streams to wherever you wish and how to pipe together different commands
to build powerful pipelines.
I hope to use the T command and the X Ogg's command for extra pipeline flexibility.
And this really is amazing how far you've come in such a short amount of time.
So I want to make this video to congratulate you on your progress so far so well done you little computer
genius you now in the next section you're going to learn about navigating the Linux file system and
you'll also learn some new building blocks to use in your pipelines.
But before that I have a project for you to complete the project will challenge you to build your very
own Linux command pipeline.
Now it's going to be awesome and it will serve as a badge of honor that you have learned everything
that we've covered in this section so that you can feel confident moving on now in the next video I'm
going to be giving you your project brief.
So congratulations once again you're doing amazingly.
And I'll see you there.