Hello you beautiful people.
The last video you got stuck right in and use the most powerful tool on the Linux operating system.
But as they say with great power comes great responsibility.
So in order to maximize your control over the Linux operating system you need to get a solid understanding
of what's going on when you type your commands.
So over the next few videos we're going to be doing a bit of a deep dive on what is actually going on
when you run your commands and also go into detail on how the commands are structured so that you can
understand how to use them properly.
Now if you do already have some previous experience but didn't feel as you quite got it or that something
is missing in your understanding it's very likely that you aren't 100 percent clear on the stuff that
we're going to be covering in the next few videos.
So this is super important stuff.
Now whether you do have some previous experience or a complete beginner to it I really want you to pay
your best attention to the topics that we'll be covering in the next few videos because they are so
critically important to your understanding of the Linux operating system.
And if you do understand what we cover in the next few videos everything you do in Linux will start
to make a whole lot more sense.
So be very very excited that we're going to clear this stuff up.
Now in this video you're going to learn the difference between commands the terminal and something called
the shell.
These are very important distinctions that will underpin basically every single thing that you do on
the command line.
And by the end of this video you'll have understood the difference between the terminal commands and
the shell and you'll have a much richer and deeper understanding of what is actually going on behind
the scenes.
When you use the terminal.
So this is going to be a critically important lecture.
Let's go ahead and get into it.
So what is actually going on when we type a command.
Well to understand this we need to know the difference between a command and something called the shell.
The commands are just text.
But when you press enter the meaning of that text is interpreted by a computer program called the shell.
OK.
So let's take a real world example.
If we see the word here on the left rasboras on a physical level that word is just the letters are a
s p b e r r r e s and just like any other word.
If you can't read the language it won't mean much to you.
Right but if you took this word and you could for example read English then what would happen is you
would you would see that text and you would interpret it for meaning and what might come out is this
fruit.
Ok you'd see that text and you would match it with this fruit the raspberries.
But there's a process in the middle of interpreting that text into specific meaning and that is the
job of the shell.
OK.
So to make this a bit clearer let's say you took the word gift.
And you read that word using the English language and the meaning that might come out might be the idea
of giving someone a present or something on their birthday.
Ok so you might say you might get this meaning coming out from reading the word gift but instead of
reading it in English with an English shell.
So we call it let's say you took exactly the same word gift but this time you read it with a German
shell.
Now instead of a present coming out the meaning that might come out of that if you read it in German
would be the poison which is ironically not the best gift but you can see here that the text is exactly
the same but the meaning that comes out is different depending upon the shell that interpreted it.
OK.
As another example let's say we took the word smoking smoking if you read that again in an English shell
the meaning that would come out would be the idea of using a cigarette.
But if you took exactly the same word and in this time passed it through a French shell.
OK.
Using the analogy here of human interpretation what would come out would be a tuxedo which is a fancy
type of clothing.
So you can see here the text can be exactly the same but the shell interprets that text can give it
different meaning and that is exactly the same on your computer.
So what about the terminal that we now understand the difference between a command and the shell.
So what's the terminal for.
Well the terminal is nothing more than just a window into the shell.
So let's make this a bit easier to understand.
So if I asked you how would you type commands on to your show without opening the terminal Well you
couldn't write.
And that's exactly what the terminal is the term that is kind of like the middle piece in between using
come out in between typing commands and summon them to the shell.
You can't really type commands anywhere unless you've opened a terminal and that's all is what you're
doing is you're typing commands in the terminal and you press enter and then they are submitted to the
shelves of the terminal is kind of like the middle piece.
OK.
And there are actually different types of shells so different types of shelves just like there were
different types of human languages can actually interpret the same command in different ways.
But fortunately there is one type of shell which has been which is the most common type which is called
the bash shell.
So if you've ever heard the term bash shell scripting or bash scripting or something like that it means
writing programs and writing scripts that can be read by the bash shell and Linux.
Most Linux distribution use the bash shell and aboon buntu definitely does by default.
So that's something to bear in mind that there are different types of shells on Linux.
They can interpret commands in different ways but the most common one is the bash shell.
So there we are we've got some standardization there.
So to summarize commands a RealAge the text that you type in the terminal and when you press enter that
text is interpreted by the shell.
Now the shell is a program that translates that text into into actions for the computer.
Now this means that different shells can actually interpret the same text differently which might cause
some problems but fortunately most Linux machines use the bash shell.
So there is consistency across most machines and as we said as well the terminal is just a window to
the shell it just it's just the middle piece that allows you to type your commands and submit them to
the shell.
And as a bonus piece of information your commands are actually also case sensitive.
So if you type a command in all uppercase if the shell isn't expecting to see that it will probably
give you an error.
So you need to make sure that things are spelled in exactly the correct way.
OK which has the benefits of allowing you to have more more options because slight differences can give
different functionality but it means you have to be really careful on how you actually type your commands
if you want them to work the way you want them to.
Now what's coming up next is because we're going to spend a lot of the time in this course typing commands
and submitting them to the shell.
I don't want you to go through this course and just have to memorize loads and loads and loads different
commands just like pretty much every other cause makes you do what you're going to do is we're going
to take a bit of time to understand what commands actually are and how they are structured so that you
can start to see a pattern behind everything you can start to look at the commands as a type of language
rather than just random text on the screen that you've got to memorize.
Now it's likely you'll probably not have been shown this before so this is going to be a complete game
changer in how you actually approach learning the Linux operating system and learning the terminal.
So I really can't wait to show you this it's going to be really really really helpful.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.