Hello you beautiful people.
In the last video you learn the difference between the terminal and the shell and you've also seen how
commands are structured on quite a general level.
We mentioned that commands follow a general structure like command name Vincent options and then some
inputs.
But like we saw each of the Linux commands is implemented slightly differently and they behave slightly
differently.
So other than memorizing a jillion different implementations of things how can we actually know how
to use each of the Linux commands properly.
Well the answer is to use the manual pages known as man pages for sure.
Now Linux comes with an incredible set of manual pages that will detail the workings of pretty much
everything on the system including commands.
So in this video we're going to be covering how the manual is structured now because the manual is massive.
Having an understanding of the structure behind it is going to make it so much easier to navigate because
then you'll know not only what is available in the manual but also where to look for it.
So by the end of the video you'll have an understanding of the manual structure and which sections are
probably going to be most important to you and you'll also have a cool cheat sheet to take away with
you that pretty much has all the notes and all the all the top information from this video.
That's quite exciting.
So let's go ahead and jump right into it.
All right so the first thing you need to know when you're looking at the manual structure is that the
manual is broken up into eight sections and each of these sections deals with a specific type of thing
that is on your Linux operating system.
Now the manual is absolutely huge and be just it would be impossible to deal with if it was all just
in one big lump.
But breaking it up into several sections that makes it a lot easier for you and I to manage and some
where we're looking.
So we can actually find what we're looking for.
OK.
So let's go through each of these eight sections and have a bit of a bit more understanding of what
they do.
OK.
So let's start with section number one.
So section number one is for user commands.
Now these are commands that can just be run from the shell by any regular user.
You don't need any particular administration privileges or any root privileges to be able to run these
commands.
Anyone can use them for things like the date command the command and so on.
These are the kind of command that would come under user commands and pretty much any command that you'll
use day to will be in there.
OK.
Section 2 is for system calls.
Now this is a more advanced section.
So this is this contains programming functions that can be used within an application that you write
to make calls to the Linux kernel which is a very low level part of the operating system that we'll
be discussing actually later on in the course.
But unless you're doing some rather advanced stuff that actually plays with the operating system and
the hardware on your computer you probably won't use Section 2 but it's there and that's what it's for.
Same kind of goes for Section 3 which is about C library functions.
Now these are libraries for the C programming language.
And these are functions and libraries that provide interfaces to specific things on your computer such
as graphical user interfaces or other libraries that you might want to use if you're writing some C
code that you want to have access to your computer with then that's the kind of stuff that you will
be looking at in the in section 3 but if you're just a regular user like me you probably won't need
to do so.
Section 4 is devices and special files always got the word special in it.
But this is about how the different device is on your computer are managed.
So things such as CD drives or things such as random number generators or things such as U.S. ports
and stuff like that.
This is how they're managed and how you can access those using using command lines and things like that.
So anything to do with the device isn't going to be in Section 4.
Section 5 is an interesting one Section 5 is about file formats and conventions so if you've ever opened
up a file on your computer and just been like whoa what is that.
Looks like an absolute mess.
I have no idea what is going on how can I possibly use this.
That's what Section 5 is for Section 5 is about all the different formats and the conventions of specific
files and on your computer.
So you know formats for word documents or formats where PDA documents a format for specific configuration
files if you want to start configuring things on your computer so customizing stuff.
Section 5 is what you're going to use often because it'll show you how each of the special files works
and how they're structured and which you data structure you can change them.
Right.
So that Section 5 section 6 is about games.
Any games that are installed on your computer they have their own section and different commands and
so replicable to those sections 7 is more miscellaneous stuff more Uncategorized stuff.
So it's usually stuff like protocols or file systems and information about those.
If you know what they mean then maybe you want to check it out.
If you don't then don't worry about it you'll probably never come across it.
And Section 8 is lilted of all the stuff to do with system administration.
So this is like the reverse of section 1 Section 8 is all the commands that can actually that actually
require root privileges and administration privileges to be run on your computers this is things like
changing passwords.
This is things like you know really editing important stuff on your computer setting up automation and
things like that.
Whereas Section 1 the user commands is stuff that anyone can run.
Section 8 requires privileges in order to actually run those functions of those commands.
OK.
So those are the eight sections.
And as I say this information with more explanation is actually in the cheat sheet that you can get
in the resources section so make sure to check that out after this video.
But the main sections that you're actually going to be using Section 1 which is the user commands will
be using that all the time in this course and you will be using it all the time pretty much whenever
you use Linux day today.
Section 5 is usually what you use if you want to start editing stuff and configuring things.
You'll get information on how to edit the stuff and what to edit in specific configuration files using
Section 5 and section 8 when you want to set up things like automation or make some rather advanced
changes to your computer then you'll use Section 8 which is all the System Administration stuff that's
when you want to do stuff that normal users shouldn't be able to do all the time.
It's like changing patching other people's passwords and stuff like that creating users for the system
and things like that.
OK.
So Section 1 Section 5 and section 8 are what you will likely use most often.
So there we are that's a that's a structure for the manual does take a quick summary of what we've seen
here we've seen the man Linux menus broken up into eight sections and more information about each of
the sections is actually in the cheat sheet that you can find in the resources.
But now that we've got an understanding of each of the sections and we see how the manual is structured
Let's start actually using it.
OK.
So in the next video what we're going to do is we're going to take this information about the those
structures and we're going to see how you can actually search the manual and read the manual pages to
learn how to use new commands.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.