Hello you beautiful people know in the last video you learned about the structure of the intox manual
and you saw the way that it was broken up into eight sections.
And those eight seconds each deal with a different part of the Linux experience.
Now we're going to take that theory from the last video and we're going to turn it into practice.
In this video.
So in this video you can learn how to search the minute and discover new commands and how to access
the manual pages for those commands.
And you're also going to learn how to read them so that you can go out there and independently learn
how to use new stuff.
So by the end of this video you'll have the independence to search for new commands and learn about
how they work.
And this is going to put you in the driver's seat because it makes it possible for you to gain more
control of your Linux system because you can start learning independently about how everything works
rather than waiting for a random chances that you randomly bump into learning new commands.
You can take a lot more of an active role in your learning and your development of the Linux operating
system.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
OK so now that you know that the manual is broken up into eight sections How would you know what section
to look in to find what you're looking for.
Well let's say that you wanted to look up information about the which command first to search the manual
you would have to use the man command that a man command is short for the word manual.
And it's the command that deals with everything to do with the manual basically.
And this is why they're actually called man pages because it's the man command that looks through the
manual.
OK.
Now that's the command name.
So we're good at that.
Now we need to give it any options if necessary.
Mark are you going to use the k option which is what deals with searching.
OK so we've got some unnamed options now.
It needs an input and the input that we're going to give is the search term.
So we type which.
OK.
So we got a command name we've got our options we've got our inputs the same general structure that
I was setting up before but now what we're doing actually is using the man come on to search the manual
for this search term the search term here called which.
Is going to look all the way through the manual and find anything that might be relevant to that search
time.
It's like your own mini search engine for your manual.
So if Representer we get quite a few lines of output here.
OK.
So let's let's have a look at what this is on the left here.
You're going to get the names of certain manual pages.
OK.
Every single one of these is a manual page that is appropriate to this search term.
And on the right you get a bit of a synopsis about the actual page so you can pick which one might be
most appropriate.
OK.
And the other thing is in the parentheses here you get the section number of the manual that that page
is in.
So for example this command at manual page is in the first section of the manual which means it's a
user command whereas this one is in the 8th section of the manual which means that it is a more system
administrative kind of thing.
And this one is in Section 5 which is going to be a file file configuration how the files are structured
and things are that information about how files are structured so that we can actually see at a glance
whether it actually suits our needs or not.
And if we decide that we want to take a further look it seems like this one is exactly what we're looking
forward to the use a command section and it's a command that locates a command.
We can actually take a deeper look at that by using the map again.
Then the section number.
So the section number is 1 and then we type the search term.
And so the page name which is on the left there which is which.
OK and if I press enter.
We've opened up the manual page for the which command.
It's only very small and once we've opened that to close it and get back out we just press the q key
on the on the keyboards or press the letter Q And I'm back on my command line.
So for example we could open up this small section here this soul thing by doing MAN 6 because it's
Section 6 salt and I press enter and it opens up that that manual page for salt which you can see at
the top right there.
OK.
Now because the first section of the manual is used so often you don't usually have to type the number
one even so instead of typing Man 1 which is a nice Shoko I can just type the word man.
Can you type man.
Which which will open up the same page the same manual page and you can see that it is indeed in Section
1.
OK so that's a shortcut if you see that something is in Section 1.
You don't need to talk the one you just type the actual name of the page.
So like a page we've got LCF right.
LCF is in section 1 man LCF and we see that we all know in the LCF man page in section 1 which means
that it's a user command.
OK.
So that's how you would open up a manual page.
And up next now we're going to take a look at how you would actually read it.
OK.
So let's take a look at the man page for the which command.
So I'm going to talk man.
And then which.
And because it's actually a command that I've used very recently I could have just pressed the arrow
key a couple of times and I get back to the same result.
OK.
So I press man which press enter and we've opened up the manual page.
Now we can see that this manual page is actually broken up into the following sections of the top we've
got name then we've got a synopsis then we've got a description that we've got options.
Then we've got exit status.
OK now the sections a man page may include all examples.
See also section an environment section things about Bogues things about office things about reporting
bugs history of the command copyright things.
Stuff like that.
OK but this is what we get in this specific manual page because they're not always structured the same
way but they usually follow this kind of structure.
OK.
Now in the name section we see that we are dealing with the which command and we see a little bit about
what it does and this is actually what came up when we searched the manual in the first place.
OK this is exactly what came up.
We saw the name and then this little piece of information on the right hand side.
OK.
Now in the description section this is where you this is where you really see what the common does in
the description sections of every important section and it gives you a much more in-depth description
of what the commander actually does.
This is likely going to be one of the most useful parts of the man page for any command.
And as it will try to explain what the commanders in plain English.
OK so you've got the which command description there and here you've got these in the synopsis section
we can see a layout of how to actually use the command.
So German when I was telling you the each command is structured differently and you need to read the
manual pages to see how to use a command.
Well this is the section of the manual page that will tell you how to use the command.
The synopsis section.
So for the which come on we can see the first type which OK.
The command name and then we see the A option in some square brackets which will come into in a minute
and then some kind of file name.
And then three dots although also known as an ellipsis afterwards.
So let me explain what this stuff means.
OK so first we enter the which come they will just type which then we have the option which is optional.
Now we know it's optional because it's inside the square brackets in a man page.
If something is inside square brackets that means it's optional.
OK you don't have to enter it but you can.
OK.
Now next after that once we've entered our optional option we.
Next you have to enter the name of a command that you're actually looking for.
Now you can see so you enter a name when you looking for example which may be decay and then echo.
OK.
That would show you where the echo command was.
But you also see this ellipsis Oh these three dots that these three dots mean that you can enter more
than one file name.
So in other words the command can take more than one input.
Things are starting to fall into place now.
Right so how do you know how many inputs the command takes will you look at the man page you look at
the synopsis and it will tell you how many inputs it takes.
OK.
Now just to prove it.
Just prove this.
We're going to take what we've learned here.
And we're going to apply it.
OK so I'm going to go back and clear the screen presence by holding control in now and we're going to
see we're going to try and use the command to find the data command and the command at the same time.
OK.
So we've used the which command.
We didn't give it the option but we didn't have to because it's just option just optional because we
because it was in the square brackets and we've given it a one far name and then another I say if we
press enter that we see that we get two outputs and then it's found the locations of the date command
and then the count command.
We didn't need to run the command twice because if we look at the man page it tells us we can actually
give it more than one file name.
OK.
So that's really really useful and maybe not maybe something we wouldn't have known had to do.
We had not looked at the man page.
And as I said the things inside square brackets in the main page will be opened up again.
Things inside the square brackets are optional.
This kind of stuff you don't have to have but you can have and if you want to know what it does you
just go to the Options section.
So if I put in the option it says it'll print all the matching pathnames of each argument so all matching
pathnames so is short for all.
So what I could do is I could type which I could do.
Which date and cow but I could type dash.
And see if that does any difference.
It actually and it doesn't make any difference.
But it will show us all of the different all of the different results.
So maybe you know when I told you about searching searching on the path maybe this will allow us to
look in folders that were later on in the path if they had the same name as where they were earlier
on.
OK.
So there we go.
Now there's other the symbols in the manual pages such as angle brackets.
So these kind of things.
Right.
So if you have something inside here inside the manual page.
So if we have like which And then it was like this and then you had something ok inside angle brackets.
Anything inside the angle brackets is mandatory.
That means you have to have it.
OK.
So if you see something inside angle brackets that means you have to have it and you can't miss it at
all right.
So just bear that in mind.
There's also the pipe character.
So if I have an option here and it was something like say you had the f option.
OK.
Because there's a pipe character between the two options.
That means OK you have to pick one or the other.
OK so the pipe means one or the other.
You cannot have both.
So I couldn't type I couldn't type which which Dasch a death date.
OK I would have to type which dash A or which dash f couldn't have both.
That's what happens if you see something inside.
Inside angle brackets.
OK some second time I think again.
So the angle brackets with a pipe in between them.
OK so what Beduin so far.
OK.
It's probably what you'll come up with most of the time.
So these are all the different things that you'll see.
You'll have the name.
You have some options.
It will tell you which ones are optional and which ones you need and which ones cannot be combined with
others.
You will see things that may be a mantra inside square brackets and anything with a dot dot dot after
it means you can have more than one thing.
So if it's sad like this it was a file name was in it and then dot dot dot that means you can have more
than one file name when you use this command.
Now I'm actually going to put a PTF in the resort in the resource section for this lecture that lists
what the different symbols mean.
So you can use it if you ever need a quick refresher but it's pretty much all you need to remember.
OK.
Just the anything in square brackets is optional.
And with a pipe in between it you can only have one or the other anything and square anything in angle
brackets is mandatory.
And I think with dot dot dot after it you can use more than once because pretty much all you need to
know.
And if you want to know how to look up what different options do to scroll down to the Options section
in the main page and it'll tell you exactly how to use them all.
OK.
Awesome So we've covered a whole lot of stuff in this video and you should start feeling a lot more
comfortable using the command line already in this video.
So have to search the manual using the man command with the k option and after that you can give it
any search term that you want.
And the command will search the manual for that search term and give you a list of results as well as
what those results are and where section of the manual page they're in.
So I had to access those specific manual pages and also how to read them for specific command structure.
So we saw how Tota actually use the which command using its manual page.
And we saw the different symbols that might come up in the manual page to tell you how to use it.
But I've attached cheat sheet in the resources section for this video that I massively encourage you
to use and keep on hand because it's going to give you an explanation of each of the different symbols
that might show up in a manual page so that you can keep that to hand.
And you know make sure that you don't forget anything.
But to ensure that you don't forget anything.
Up next we're going to have some practice what we're going to do is we're going to go together and we're
going to look at we're going to search for a new command and we're going to read about how it works.
We can look at it's manual page and we're going to take that learning and actually apply it and show
you how how you would take a man page that you've never seen before and learn how to use it.
So we're going to be applying what we've learned in this lecture about reading manual pages and apply
it to a completely new command and go through it together.
And after that you should definitely feel as though hey any command or any manual page that I've come
up against I'll know how to read and know how to use which is going to give you a massive boost of confidence
and a massive boost of independence for you to explore and learn more about the Linux operating system.
So let's go ahead and jump into the next video and get some super super cool practice.