Hello you beautiful people know in the last video you learn how to search the manual for specific keywords.
Open up manual pages and how to read them to learn how to use specific commands.
But there was quite a lot of stuff in that video and a lot to take in.
So in this video what we want to do is we want to give you some practice.
So in this video we're going to take a look at a completely new command that we haven't seen before
and we're going to learn how to use it.
We're going to search the manual for it.
We're going to learn how to use it using the synopsis in the manual page.
We're going to read through its various options.
I'm going to try some of them out and see how you can customize commands and stuff like that.
And the idea is that this is going to show you how to independently search for stuff using the manual
we're going to put the whole process together we can take everything we've learned put it all together
and show you how you would learn about a new command from scratch.
And the idea is you can have the independence to search for new stuff and learn how it works and that's
really where the value comes from the manual.
It's not having people randomly show you things that they find cool is being able to go out there and
find stuff that you find cool and learn how to use it independently and it can take your Linux abilities
to a whole new level.
So let's go ahead and jump into it and start learning about our brand new command.
OK so what we're going to do is we're going to look at a command that will allow us to list out what
is in a folder also known as a directory.
OK so we want to come and that will list out a directory's contents.
OK.
So now that we know that.
Let's go ahead and search for what might be available so the first step is to search for what might
be available in the manual and you might have to try this multiple times.
OK you might not get the search terms available right away you might have to try different words and
different keywords but let's try that.
So let's try this type the man come and give it the k option and then we tell what we want to search
for.
Now I'm going to put in quotes list directory contents.
OK.
And the reason I put it in quotes is because I want to search for this search term in one go.
I don't want to search for the word list then the word directory than the word contents.
I want to search for list directory contents in one go.
OK so once I do that I press enter.
And here we go.
We get some results.
OK.
Now they all seem to pretty much do what we want right.
They all seem to say list directory contents but the one that I'm specifically looking for I've heard
about online is the l s command.
OK now the ls command is one that we will come onto as well in the layout section of the course but
we can see that it's a user command because it's in the first section of the manual.
So we could open it using MAN 1 LS but because it's in the first section we would have to have even
have the one we can type man.
S And here we go.
Where in the manual page for the ls command.
So there we are now right at the top.
We can see the where in the press command is in the first section of the manual which is apparently
user commands and we can see the name of the command is ls and it lists directory contents and that's
from the name section.
Now looking at the synopsis section we can see that if you type L S then you can have multiple optional
options.
We know they're optional because they're surrounded by square brackets and you can have multiple of
them because they've got the ellipsis after it and then you have multiple optional filenames or paths
to directories and can have multiple of those because we can see the dot dot dot.
But the one thing that you might notice is because everything else is optional right.
The only thing you actually need to enter is the ls command itself and it will work.
So let's try that.
OK let's try and see that we don't even have to give the command any input so if we press lower case
Q to quit We're back in.
We're backing out of it all.
Now as I said the thing we need to do is enter the Alaskan itself.
If I just type LS I press enter that it has indeed listed all the contents of our home directory which
is the directory that we're currently in.
So how cool.
OK now go back in the man page just go back in the main page.
We can see that there's a whole bunch of options that we can use we can look down in the description
section.
It says here that list information about the files which is the current working directory by default
sort's entries alphabetically.
If non of these options or the sort option is specified and mandatory arguments to long options are
mandatory for short options as well.
OK so that's fair enough.
Now we've got loads of different options in here.
OK loads of them let me just scroll through loads of them guys.
OK.
So memorizing all these is just not possible.
Just don't even don't even try.
You're not going to be able to do all that and even if you did there were thousands and thousands of
Linux commands so it's kind of a waste of time to do it all.
This is what you need to know how to use a manual page effectively.
OK.
There's a whole bunch of options.
One that I might like to show you which is a good one is the l option.
OK.
Now of course you can browse through these and have a look at what they do.
But you've got the option here which stands for long listing format.
OK.
So let's try that.
Sounds pretty cool.
Let's see what that means.
If I type ls and give it the l option or press enter.
We now see that everything is kind of listed in a much more detailed fashion.
This was put before and this is the output.
Now OK so we've got much more detailed view of what's in our folder now to explain what this means a
bit later in the course.
But for now I hope you can see that the process that you might follow for discovering a new command.
OK we search for manual pages we browsed a few of the options and we tried them out as well as seeing
how to actually use the command in the first place.
Now let's let's have another look in.
We can see that this is a bit it's a bit difficult to read.
Perhaps if we look at the ls command again and we scroll down we can see that there's another option
here called the hate option which stands for human readable I guess you can see here we've got a short
form option dash h or a long form option dash dash human readable.
And this is how you can tell whether whether an option has a long form or not because it will move right
next to it in the manual page.
OK you may want to set some options have long forms and some don't.
And this is how you can tell.
And it says that with the l option and or the s option this will print human readable sizes of files.
For example one kilobyte to integrate four megabytes two gigabytes etc..
OK so let's take a look at that here.
This column this column here is actually all the file sizes.
And it just says 4000 a nice six or eight thousand nine hundred eighty or whatever it might be.
OK but to make that human readable you can type LS dash L and then give it the option as well and we'll
see that.
Now it's said because it's four kilobytes eight point eight kilobytes and so on and so on.
OK.
But as well because we have a long form option and we don't have to just type hey we might type page
but we could also type dash dash human readable.
I think it was like that.
Let me check if I type.
LS It's dash dash human human readable.
I'm Pop-Pop I apologize human Dasch readable.
OK.
And there we go.
Now we've got exactly the same output that we have before you say.
So you can see here the way we use a long form option which means now we know it's a bit easier to read
what.
Well you know what that means than it is to just see what hate means.
OK.
But it kind of makes the command a bit more difficult to type so there's a bit of a tradeoff there.
But you get the same output.
OK.
So you can see just how useful reading the man pages actually is and if we just go back into the ls
command and be clear the screen go back into the ls command and scroll all the way down.
You will see a section if we we keep scrolling down it's a long manual page much longer than that which
come on right.
You'll see a section that says that is called See also.
OK so this section here that says See also it's got a hyperlink and you can click on this hyperlink
or any hyperlink that's in a manual page by holding the control key and left clicking OK.
Now if we control the left click that's going to do if I if I clicked it right.
Have to wait I think there we go.
It's opening up.
So I clicked it multiple times but it's opened up in the Firefox browser.
The link that was in there.
OK.
So it's going to give you more information about the command as long as you have internet access.
OK so that sometimes in manual pages there are there are links that you can click on so there's another
one here for example.
Another one here.
If you hold the control key and click them and then you will open up in your browser and you'll be able
to see what they're pointing at.
So that's very very useful.
And that's something you'll definitely want to do if you want more information.
And as a final know although you can find pretty much information on pretty much all the commands that
you'll ever need using the man pages you can't quite get all of them.
So some commands are defined directly in the shell and don't have man pages for them.
So to find those commands you will need to use the help command instead of the man.
Come on.
Let me just show you what I mean.
OK.
So for example one of them is the cd command and the cd command is one you will use all the time.
Actually it's used to change a directory.
You'll see this in the next section of the course.
What about navigating the file system.
But if I type man CD it's like there's no manual entry for the cd command but if I type the help command
and then do CD we then get something that's very similar to a man page and we can see how to use it.
Here we get a description.
We get the options and so on.
It's like OK so it works pretty much just the same as a manual page.
It's just you have to use help instead to find the commands that are that need the help command to use
if you just type help and press enter.
You get a big list and every single one of these in here is need needs the needs the help command to
see it.
So for example his CD ok for example if we do P.W. day of here if we do man PWT there actually is a
man page for it.
But if for one of those commands it didn't come up with a man page you would just type help.
PETER BEATTIE And it would give you basically the same basic like a very similar kind of output.
So if man doesn't work and you know the command is correct use the help command instead.
And there's a lot of other things in here like for example doing wild loops in the in the shell for
loops and other things like that.
OK so it's it's quite it's quite an advanced thing more about the shell rather than about the programs
that are installed on your computer.
OK.
So that's just something to bear in mind.
Now another thing that has actually come to my mind in the ls command here notice this is this works
for pretty much all commands.
Notice when you've got a long form.
So for example almost all or block size or ignore backups when you have a long form come on like this.
They tend to break up the words with a dash.
OK so ignore dash backups block dash size almost dash all all you know down here full dash time group
dash directories no dash group Human dash readable.
OK so when you're making a long form option.
When I wanted you know the human readable one instead of going human readable like the mistake I made
before because human is one word and readable is another word is going to be human readable.
And that gives us the output.
OK so that's just something to bear in mind with regards to spelling and things like that.
But the main thing to remember when you are reading these manual pages is each Linux command is designed
to do one thing and do it extremely well.
That's why you've got a the LS kind with so many different options.
Anything that you can possibly imagine to do with listing things out of directories.
The LS command is going to be able to do it.
OK.
So that's why the manual pages have a lot of information to really get the information out of that.
Unfortunately if you want to become a master of the ls command or you know even just start using any
new command there's going to be no shortcut to reading.
Unfortunately I wish there was.
You can skim read and sometimes they give you quick intros and quick starts to commands and things like
that in the manual pages but for all these options if you want to learn it you're going to have to read
it.
OK so there's no other way around that.
So that's how you will go through and you'll learn about a new command.
So let's do it really quick in quick succession.
We wanted to learn about a command that shows you how to direct your content so we use man with the
k option list directory contents.
It came up with some possible page names.
The sections they were in and the explanations.
The ls command caught our eye we noticed it was in the first section.
So we just typed man ls and gave us the manual page we saw that yes it lists directory contents we see
a quick description and we saw how to use it.
You have to type the ls command.
The options are optional you can have multiple of those and the files are optional and you can have
multiple of those.
So we saw that actually you can just type the ls command and you get some output but there are plenty
of other options.
There's loads of things in here.
One thing that we liked was the idea that you could have a long form option.
OK so the long form option we found it whereas it's down here we found it under L use a long listing
format.
So we had to look at that.
We do ls dat L We got lot.
We also saw that you can have long form options as well.
OK.
One other thing is that you can see here there's a lower case which gives you one option and uppercase
which gives you another option.
And here while you've got a lower case b gives you one option an uppercase B gives you another option.
That's very common.
So you need to make sure that when you are spelling things in Linux you get the case correct.
So for example Anastacia will give us that.
But if I do start capital L I didn't even do anything.
OK.
So you need to make sure that you get that stuff right and just just for curiosity what does the capital
L say if there is a capital L option.
Yeah dereference when followed when showing falling for mation for a symbolic link.
So information for the file in the link for information for the file the link references rather than
for the link itself.
So there you go.
OK so you need to make sure that your case is correct.
Things have to be spelt precisely you have a very sharp eye and not make mistakes and make sure you're
doing stuff right because the power of these commands is so so powerful they can do so many different
things but you just need to make sure that you enter them correctly.
OK.
So there we go.
That's a quick summary of this video what we're going to do in the next video is we're going to actually
be moving on from the manual.
And what we're going to be showing you is how to how commands take input and actually give output because
one of the most powerful things that Linux commands that you do is to train different commands together
to make up super powerful command pipelines.
Now because each command is amazing at what it does when you can chain them together chain these each
of these separate commands that is amazing what it does but chained them together you can break create
some incredibly powerful functionality with very little effort.
OK.
So I'm going to show you how to do that.
But first we need to take a little bit of a look into how commands take input and give output so you
can actually start building together these Capan and pipelines.
You need to understand how they take input and give outputs for all that good stuff.
We see you in the next video.