Hello you beautiful people are welcome to this section of the course.
All about how to install and manage software on a Linux computer.
Now Linux is an open source operating system and the great thing about that is that there are around
the world millions and millions of software developers who are creating software and all kinds of fantastic
stuff and making it available for free for people to download.
So that's pretty cool that means we can benefit from that a little bit.
Now Lileks has some amazing ways for you to gain access to this software.
I mean this section I'm going to show you how to do it.
So in the section you're going to start off with a lot of what Open-Source actually means.
Are you going to show we're going to show you how you can see actual source code for some commands that
you've already seen in the course and then you'll learn how to use the software repositories to search
for and install new software.
Keep that software up to date and also had to remove it when you no longer need it.
So we're going to show you the whole package.
Now usually when talking about software management on Linux courses just tell you into this command
and this command and this command with union you just got to memorize it which is useful and all but
it never really shows you you know the meaning behind it or leaves you feeling like you actually understand
what you're doing and why you're using a certain command.
So in this section you're not only going to understand what commands to run you're also understand how
your software manager is working under the hood to help you install update and manage software in your
new Linux system.
So by the end of the section you have a wonderfully in-depth and practical understanding of software
managers and you also have the practical know how to get more shiny new toys to play with than you can
possibly imagine.
So for all the good stuff I'll see you in the next video.