Hello you beautiful people.
Now one key thing that probably brought you to work with Linux is the idea of open source software.
But what does that term really mean.
Well in this video we're going to talk about the new project and what it actually means for software
to be open source and the history of the whole open source movement.
So let's go ahead and get into it.
OK.
So the first thing that we probably need to understand is what Linux actually is when we hear the word
Linux we probably think of a whole operating system that we use as being the Linux operating system.
Now surprisingly this is actually not the case and Linux is actually just one of the pieces of the whole
operating system the kernel.
So let me explain.
On Sept. 27 the September in 1983 a person called Richard Stallman announced that he was going to begin
developing a operating system that was similar to the Unix operating system but made of entirely free
software.
Now the operating system was called the new operating system spelled g and U which stands for Ganu is
not Unix which they like to call a recursive acronym.
OK.
Now in nine in January 1984 Richard Stallman quit his job in the Artificial Intelligence Lab at the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology so MIT to work on the Ganu project full time in the aims of creating
an operating system made of completely free software.
Now the term free software actually refers to several freedoms that the software gives the user rather
than being free as in money.
So when you hear the term free software think free speech and not free lunch.
Now these freedoms are the first.
First one is the freedom to run the program as you wish for any purpose.
The first freedom the second freedom is the freedom to study how the program works and change it so
that it does the computing as you wish.
Which is what freedom one is.
OK freedom one is that the program will do what you wish.
Freedom to me is the freedom to study how the program works and to change it so that it does as you
wish.
Now access to the source code for a program is a precondition for this.
You can't study how a program works and you can look at its code.
So having access to the source code is a precondition for freedom number.
The third freedom is the freedom to redistribute copies of the software so that you can as they say
help your neighbor and freedom not before is the freedom to distribute copies of your modified version
of your software.
If you modify it you can redistribute that Wishings to freedom number 3 of helping other people.
But by and.
Apparently by doing this you can give the whole community a chance to benefit from your changes.
And again access to the source code is a precondition for this.
OK so if you want to modify software and redistribute it you need to have access to the source code
in order to be able to change it.
Now there's a license that legally provides a user of software with these freedoms and is known as the
canoe public license or the GPL.
Now are several versions of the Gonu public license or the GPL but at the time of recording the GPL
version 3 is the most modern version.
But in 1991 the new system was almost finished but there was still one part missing from the new operating
system and it was an important part.
This final piece is a major part of every operating system and it's called the kernel.
The kernel is responsible for allocating the resources on the computer's hardware that is required by
the software that is running so it's the interface layer between the computers hardware and the applications
that it's running.
OK now at this time in 1991 a man called like Linus Torvalds was completing his MFC thesis at the University
of Helsinki in Finland and as part of this work Lenas invented a Unix like kernel called Linux and it
was called Linux after his own name.
But everything in the Unix world kind of ends in an X..
So Linux ending in the next.
Is Linux OK.
And after being VEIDT after being invited by a fellow student to go see a talk by Richard Stallman who
is also a prominent activist at the time Lenas released the Linux kernel under the version 2 of the
new Public License or GPL thereby making the Linux kernel free software so Fang's to the Linux kernel
the new operating system was complete and and was fully runnable operating system made of entirely free
software.
With those four freedoms we talked about before and it began to gain popularity and it in fact the Linux
kernel that is used today on on Android devices and even Chrome OS so if you ever hear people say oh
Android runs Linux or Chrome OS runs Linux what they mean is they use the Linux kernel to interface
between the software layer and the hardware layer of your computer.
But because the Linux kernel was the final piece it kind of got a whole lot of attention and the rest
of the work that went into the new operating system was kind of forgotten.
But because what we run when we run a distribution like a buntu or any other Linux distribution is actually
the new operating system and the Linux kernel.
It was recommended that in order to give the group project its credit instead of just calling the whole
thing Linux we should call it new.
Plus Linux.
In fact there is a command called the you name command that will actually tell you loads of information
about your computer such as what hardware it has and what operating system that it's running.
So if you run the unit in command with the o option it'll tell you your operating systems.
If we run that we see that we can we get Ganu slash Linux as the operating system.
Sounds pretty cool right.
OK so with that history understood we now know pretty much all of the commands of you so far in the
course such as the ls command of the find command and so on are all part of the new project and to give
the users the freedoms that free software provides.
The source code needs to be available to read because access to the source code is a precondition for
those freedoms right.
So in other words the software must be open source.
Ok so the source code must be open be accessible.
It's open source.
So how come we have a look at the code that our computer runs.
Well it's actually all freely accessible on the canoe project's official Web site Ganu dot org.
So if I just open up a Firefox browser here and when that boots up we head over to the new dot org.
We'll be able to see what I'm talking about so here we are.
Has Firefox.
Let's go to Ganu dot org and press enter.
There we go.
So you can read all about the philosophy behind the Free Software ideology in more detail and you can
see here it's telling you to try new Linux here.
But if you head over to the software section if we click on software here and scroll down to a part
that says all good new packages.
Here it says org new packages.
You can you can see here that there's every This basically links to every bit of code that is run on
a new system including a free software version of the Linux kernel itself which we can find under the
Linux lb. package say we are Linux lb..
OK that's the that's the package that's the full downloadable folder that contains all of the source
code for V for the Linux kernel itself.
That's pretty awesome.
Now for all the commands that you've run so far this is the ls command grep find whatever it might be.
OK.
You can find those under the core utils package that we'll call you tell.
So that's where you can find the stuff in there in that call you tell us package.
And in the next video we're going to download the call utos package modify it and install a new version
of the ls command to our computer which is going to be super super exciting.
But first let's just take a quick recap of what we've learned in this video.
OK.
So in this video you learned about Richard Stallman beginning the development of the new operating system
in 1983 and the idea was to create a Unix like operating system that was made of entirely free software.
And you learn that when we say the words free software we mean software that provides users with certain
freedoms so think of free speech rather than free lunch.
OK.
Now the Fourth there are four freedoms that the free the free software gives the users so gives the
users the ability to run programs as they wish for any purpose.
It gives the users the ability to study how a program works and change it so it does the computing as
they wish and access to source code is a precondition for that and it gives the users the ability to
freely freely distribute any copies they get so that they can help other people.
And it also gives the users the ability to distribute modified versions of the software that they create
other people.
So this allows the whole community to benefit from any changes that a user makes.
And again access to source code is a precondition for that as well.
Now these freedoms are legally provided to users using the new Public License or the GPL.
And as I as the time of recording the the third version of the GPL GPL version 3 is the most modern
version of the license and open access to the source code is a precondition for giving these freedoms.
So when have software has openly accessible source code it is known as open source software so you can
say that free software is open source but not all soft or not all open source software is free software
because while people might let you see the source code that doesn't mean they necessarily give you the
freedoms required to modify and distribute it.
They might just let you see the source code OK but the free software does does require open source software
so it works one way but not the other.
And you've also learned that in 1991 the new project was almost finished but it had a important missing
piece which was the kernel and the kernel is the part of the operating system.
The interfaces between the hardware and allocates resources from the hardware depending upon what software
requires it.
And in 1991 Linus Torvalds created his own version of a kernel and called it the Linux kernel and released
it in 1991 under the new Public License version too thereby making it free software.
So the Linux kernel was the final piece for the new operating system and now the two tend to work together.
So when you download a buntu or when you download any other type of Linux distribution what you're actually
downloading is a version of the new Plus Linux operating system.
So henceforth we won't just call it Linux we'll call it the new Linux operating system.
OK so in the next video now that we understand this little bit of a history lesson we understand about
the freedoms and what open source software is all about.
We're going to play with some source code.
OK we're going to download and take a look at some of the source code for some core commands.
Modify their code and install that modified code on our computer and see how they behave differently.
So it's going to be amazing and it's going to really allow you to see what open source free software
is all about.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.