Hello you beautiful people.
In the last video you saw how you can compile source code from scratch and install it on your machine.
And this is a great process for understanding and customizing the software running on your computer.
But for most everyday things it's usually just a bit too much work.
So what if you have a library of software that you can browse and have all pre-compiled and ready to
go with a push of a button or one of a command.
Well that's exactly what the software repositories and package managers are for.
And in this video we'll be covering what they're all about.
So in this video you're going to learn about the different software repositories that are available
on the buntu and how to search them using the online Web sites.
And by the end of the video you'll know what the different repositories are.
And you also know what a package manager is.
So this lecture is going to be jam packed with useful information.
Let's go ahead and get right into it.
OK so the first thing we need to know is what a software repository is.
So think of a software repository as a big library filled with software.
Then when you go to a library you can search for books you can read about the books you can look at
different versions of the books and you can compare which books that you might want to borrow and then
check them out at the library.
And a software repository is like a library except you don't have to give the software back.
And even better when a new version of the software comes along you can automatically update that piece
of software and all the software on your entire system to the new versions that are available with a
simple command.
And this helps keep your system secure and reliable and is also totally epic.
Now in a buntu there are four different repositories and each repository stores a different type of
software and they are described on the main web site for buntu which is a buntu dot com.
Now if we head over to help the buntu dot com for a slash community for Slash repositories with a capital
are known for its rateable into the capital you put a link in the resources by the way.
If we head over to that we'll see information about the different repositories.
OK so you see a section here that says what are the repositories and you can see that for a buntu there
are four main repositories.
Now the main repository is the repository that holds all the software that is actively maintained and
updated by Canonical and Canonical is the company that created a buntu.
Now all the software in there is free as in freedom and is also open source.
OK.
Now the main repository is the most reliable repository and you should try and select from suitable
software in the main repository at the first instance where possible.
Now the second open to repository is the universe repository.
Now software in this repository is also free as in freedom and it's also open source.
However instead of being maintained by Canonical it is maintained by the buntu community and as a result
it is therefore theoretically maybe less rigorous and more prone to bugs than the main repository.
But most of the time it's fantastic.
In my experience now the third repository in the open system is the restricted repository and the restrictive
repository includes proprietary software and drivers for company specific devices such as wireless cards
and so on.
Now this repository helps ensure that the device on your computer are more likely to work out of the
box.
Shall we say.
But the software is usually proprietary and therefore doesn't usually give you the freedoms of the other
software it gives you.
Also you might or might not be able to directly examine the source code of the software in the restricted
repository and this depend.
This depends on the specific use case.
And the fourth and final repository is the multiverse repository non-motorists repository contains software
that is restricted either by copyright or legal issues.
The software in the multiverse repository might or might not have accessible source code.
You can see here that the buntu philosophy is generally about giving the user choice about what software
they want to use.
There are two repositories that are free and open source which are the main and the universe repositories
and there are two other repositories which which aren't free at open source or where the software is
unlikely to be so.
So to some people using non-free software is abhorrent and completely unacceptable whereas to others
it will be fine if it gets the job done.
No buntu leaves that choice up to you.
But if the distributions such as Fedora only include free software in the repositories and do not include
software that is non-free.
Now this could cause reductions inconvenience but it has other benefits.
Now buntu leaves the choice up to you as to what you prefer.
And now that you've been informed about the free software debate you are in a better position to choose
for yourself.
So now that we understand what the for buntu repositories are and the differences between them let me
show you where they hang out online.
No I don't mean social media but there's a link called packages door open to dot com.
So if we head over to that here we can browse through the list of packages and we can see different
links depending upon what version of a buntu that we're running.
Now the code name will change for every new release of a buntu in alphabetical order.
So for example the current one is called artful aardvark or artful for short.
And you can see what the code name for your distribution is.
By using this command in the command line.
Open up your terminal and you type it.
LS B underscore.
Release a K and you give it the option and it will.
It will print out all the information about your buntu distribution and you can see that mine is called
awful Aardvark and it tells me at the bottom here the code name is artful.
So I would click on the artful link which you can see here to open at see what packages are applicable
to me.
But you can click on whatever code name is appropriate for you when you watch this video.
OK it all works basically the same.
Now in here are all the packages of package categories OK so you can see a whole bunch of categories
in here.
You can see for example we've got things for web servers.
You can see things that we've got for fonts we've got editors we've got documentation databases administration
utilities and a whole lot of programming languages Peifer and text processing video.
It just goes on and on.
Ok so many different things.
And these are just categories.
OK so this blows the different packages inside each of these categories.
But if we scroll down we'll notice that there's a couple of important links down here.
We've got the all packages link.
We've got the compact compressed text list so this one here is just a.
If I open it in a new tab we can see that it's just a kind of text file here with a list of every single
one of the packages.
And I downloaded this text file when I was preparing the course and ran it through the word count command
and counted the amount of lines after cutting any header information and found that there was 74000
and sixty packages which is crazy.
But you know it's there for you to play with.
I'm just going to close up but we're not interested in that for this video.
What we're interested in is this link here that says all packages and if I click that it'll open up
a web page that shows you all the packages so let's just wait for that to load up a second.
So there we are.
So now we get a web page that gives us a link to each available package in a buntu.
And you may notice that it shows you in square brackets which repository the things came from so we
can see here that this zero HD package came from the universe repository.
And if we scroll down we'll be able to see some that come from other repositories as well we see and
we're getting a lot from the universe repository B.S. here.
We've got one coming from multi-verse.
And if you find a package that doesn't have anything in a square brackets next to it that means it's
from the main repository.
So for example there's a lib bench and you can see it doesn't have anything next to it.
That means it comes from the main repository.
Guess that's just something to be aware of as well.
But for now for the purposes of this video let's just go ahead and click on the top link this this package
called Zero a day.
And when we click on it will notice that a new web page opens and we see that the package is called
Zero ID.
We can see the package name or the top.
And then in these parentheses we can see the version number of the package.
And then we can see in the square brackets the repository that the package has come from.
And as I said if there isn't any such information then it's from the main repository.
OK.
And as we know the universe repository contains most content free and open source software but it's
maintained by the community and doesn't receive any formal updates or maintenance from the buntu developers
at canonical.
Then underneath that we can see a list called other packages OK that are related to this package and
we can see that we may have required version numbers in these parentheses here.
So for example this DP K.G. package must be greater than or equal to version 1.1 5.6.
Okay.
And you can see that there's quite a few different packages that are related to this one.
OK.
And you can see that they have a special symbol at the front as well.
And we can see that red means that it depends on this package.
OK so the red dot means that the zero Adey package depends on these packages.
So that means in order to install 0 A.D. We need to install all of these packages with red dots in front
of them as well.
If we want zero 80 to work OK but the red dot isn't the only symbol that can appear next to a package
in the package is less we can see that there are other symbols as well.
OK.
So you can see on the key up here that the green diamond next to a package means that zero A.D. would
recommend you to install another package.
So let's make this a bit more general.
That's called a package that you want to install which is our case 0 8.
Let's call that package.
Ok then let's call a random package in the other packages list package B the Cape.
So if package a recommends package B that means that in order for package a to function normally we
should get package B but package a will function without it.
OK then the blue square would say that package a suggested to us and other package.
OK.
So recommends means that it will function without it but we recommend it for normal use.
Dependence means it won't work.
If you don't get these packages recommended means it will work but not not like how you know it should
suggest package is just some entirely optional stuff that things you might like to check out.
OK.
And the final one is the enhances anything with a black dot means it enhances the current package in
some way or another maybe new through New features.
But again it's not required.
OK.
And if we scroll down to the bottom of this page we can see the sizes we can see what size the package
is to download and we can see what size it is when it's on compressed and installed and we can also
see what what the files each package contains which is useful so you can click on that.
You can see a list of each of the files that each package contains and you can see that there's different
packages for different computer architecture.
So for example if you've got a computer architecture that as an EMT 64 architecture you can download
this one package and if you've got one for the 386 computer architecture you would download this package
and you can see the computer's architecture by opening up the terminal and typing you name dash.
OK we can see that in our virtual machine we have the.
We're running on an x 86 64 architecture.
Now I am 64 and X 86 64 are the same.
So we would get the HMD 64 package is most appropriate for us here.
Now if you just get X 86 then then you download the IDE 386 package because that's probably the one
most and most appropriate for your computer.
So they might be thinking wait a minute Ziyad.
Hold on hold on hold on.
Are you saying that in order to install software I first have to search through thousands of packages
then find out what dependencies it has and after that I must ensure that I download all of those different
packages and satisfy their dependencies and so on and so on.
But before I download all of those I need to make sure that they're all the right version number and
that the packages are appropriate for my computer's architecture.
You have got to be kidding.
Well that's what I'd be thinking anyway.
But no the good news is that there's a command line tool installed on your computer that deals with
all of this stuff and it's called your package manager and the actual program differs from distribution
to distribution.
But on a buntu the package manager is called apt spelt a P T which stands for Advanced packaging top.
And this is what we're going to do use to do all this hard work for us.
And in the next video you're going to see how to use it.
But first let's have a review of what we've learned in this video.
So in this video you've learned that a software repository is kind of like a library but for software
except you don't need to give the software back.
Now it does differ for other distributions but in a buntu there are four main software repositories.
So this is the main repository that contains free and open source software that is actively maintained
by the Ubuntu developers.
Does the universe repository that also contains free and open source software but it's maintained by
the community instead of the Ubuntu developers.
There's the restrictive repository that contains proprietary software for device drivers.
Now software in this repository isn't likely to be open source although it might be but it's not actively
maintained by the developers.
And finally there is the multiverse repository that has software that is limited by copyright or legal
issues.
Again it's unlikely that the software will be open source in the multiverse repository but it might
be.
Now with your knowledge about free software the canoe project and so on.
You can decide for yourself whether you will only use free software from the main or universe repositories
whether you are happy to use the software from the restricted on multi-verse repositories aswell but
to leave that choice completely up to you.
Now when we wanted to see a list of packages available to us we headed over two packages dot to dot
com and a linker that is in the resources section.
In case you're interested and we saw all the packages were opened were broken up by our distribution's
code name.
And you can see the code name for your distribution by entering the LSP underscore release command with
the option and we saw the command name was artful but yours might be different depending upon when you
download it open to him when you watch this video.
Now all the packages are organized by a theme or sections and you can see a full list of packages by
scrolling down to the bottom of that page and clicking on the appropriate link and his package tells
you what repository it comes from in square brackets next to his name.
But it has no square brackets next to name.
Then it comes from the main repository.
And when you click on a package you'll find that you get more information about it as well as information
about other packages that are related to it.
Now some of these packages will be required for that package to run.
And these are marked with a red dot and cold.
They are the one package you set to depend upon these packages.
Some will be recommended packages and required for normal functioning and these will be indicated by
green diamonds.
Some will be suggested packages which are there just for interest and is indicated by blue squares and
some will be called enhance that will enhance the packages functionality in some way and these will
be indicated by black dots.
And finally we discussed that due to the complexity of managing dependencies and ensuring software has
the correct version number and so on software management is usually done using a program called a package
manager.
Now package managers differ from distribution to distribution but on a to the package manager is called
apt.
Which stands for Advanced packaging too.
So in the next video you're going to learn how to use the advanced packaging tool to upgrade your system
and search for new software now using a package manager is a critical piece of using a new Linux system
and luckily it's also super easy.
So for incredible superpowers beyond your wildest dreams I'll see you in the next video.