Hello you beautiful people.
Probably one of the most confusing things for new users of a new Linux operating system is understanding
how to get new software.
Now all other operating systems like Windows or Mac everytime that you want to install a piece of software
you probably just use to downloading an executable file opening it hitting next next next next next
a load of times.
Avoid re avoiding reading terms and conditions but agreeing anyway and celebrating internally when your
new software is installed in Linux it works a bit of a different way.
I mean you still celebrate internally when the software is installed but you tend to install it in a
way that is much more integrated standardized secure and scalable.
That is possible with the other operating systems but to get those benefits from using a package manager
will first need to let go of our preconceptions from Windows and Mac and actually get a solid understanding
of what is going on in Linux package management because it's not the same at all.
But it is a lot better.
So in this video you're going to learn about how to search for packages using apt but building off our
existing knowledge of the software repositories.
And we're going to show you how you can search the software repositories using the apt package manager
and you also get to learn about how the package manager uses caching to speed up performance and ensure
that you have a fast installation experience.
So by the end of this video you're going to be able to know how to search the software repositories
for new packages and that's going to give you the fundamental understanding that you'll need in order
to install them.
So let's go ahead and get right into it.
OK so as of now we understand that there are a bunch of packages that exist and that we'll be using
a package manager called apt to download and install them.
So far so good.
So let's start off by getting the apt program to search for packages.
And let's say that we want to search for packages that will help us when working with Microsoft Word
files.
The Microsoft Word files have conventionally had the extension dot doc X so it's fun all the packages
that are relevant to the text doc x.
So to do that we would type the command.
Apt dash cache.
OK search doc x.
OK well we did that we see that we get a few results back with one package per line when we see the
for each package we get the name of the package on the left.
So you can see we've got one here called Doc ext to TXI.
We've got one here called libber patchy and so on and then on the right we get a short description about
that package so this will turn Microsoft Excel files to plain text and this one is a general markup
converter.
OK and it's the Libres for that general markup converter so you can see at a glance what what is available.
For example if we wanted to search for things to do with text we could always use grep and search for
the word text and we would get just a few results there so you can also narrow this down using grep.
OK so it appears here that we may be interested in Rizwan here called Doc x t x take.
OK so how would we get a bit more information about what we could do if we claim a script is Doo's is
use apt cache show Doc x x t.
So instead of upcast search and then a keyword we're going to use apt cache show and then the package
name and when we enter that can see that we get a whole bunch of information about that package.
This is exactly the kind of information that's good to pipe through the last command to make it a bit
easier to deal with.
There we go so we can see the package name is Doc ex-city XTi.
It's available for all architectures gives you the version number and it also tells you where it's from
so it's from the universe repository and the text section that tells you the maintainer's with the contact
information tells you where to report any bugs and it tells you loads with the stuff.
Down here is also a description and it says it converts of XML files to plain text.
It gives you more information doc doctor Dr. T is a tool that attempts to generate equivalent ASCII
text files for Mochis of docs documents.
And you can read that if you wish.
OK I see you can see by using apt cash so we can see plenty of information about the Doc X TXI package.
So that's a really useful ability there.
Now let me show you something.
So we've done all that with access to the Internet right.
So if I click up here you can see that I've got a connected internet connection when I'm trying to disconnect
my virtual machine from the internet and try that again so I'm going to turn off my connection and I
can see now I've got no internet connection whatsoever if I open Firefox and will probably see it tell
us that there's no internet connection.
If I go to somewhere like I don't know that say YouTube dot com it determined that the server is not
found because there's no internet connection.
OK so with that let's try and do it again.
OK let's search for the term Web server because if I do apt cache search I don't want the term Web server
because there's because those two words in here.
I'm going to enclose them in quotes here so they go as one search term rather than two separate search
terms.
If I didn't have quotes and a web server it is if I search for web on its own and then server on its
own.
But I want to search for web server together.
Like I said apt cache search and we get actually a whole bunch of results.
Let me clear the screen and pipe through last to make it a bit easier to handle.
But actually wait a second isn't that quite strange.
How was apt able to search for all these packages without having any Internet connection.
Mm hmm.
And there appears to be a package here called Apache 2 that gives us the very popular Apache web server.
OK.
So let's try and get more information about that.
OK so it's called Apache to the stewe apt cache show Apache 2 and piped up through Les just to make
it easier to read.
And yeah we managed to get information about about how strange to even get detailed information about
the package.
So how is that possible if we don't have an internet connection.
Well if information is not stored on the Internet and it's not being downloaded from the Internet then
it must be stored somewhere on this computer and it is.
So this information is stored in something called a cache.
Now what's a cache.
Well having come across you may have come across the word cache when browsing web sites and you know
when you browse it gets a bit slow.
So you decided to clear out your browsers cache to speed of performance.
But what is a cache exactly what a cache is a kind of storage place for information that's supposed
to be efficient and easy to access.
To explain this let me tell you a little story.
So let's say that you wanted to keep looking at a certain web site that it was called the VW or awesome
site dot com.
OK.
Now without a cache every time that you wanted to visit awesome site dot com your computer would send
the requests all the way across the Internet.
So a computer knows a web server that holds all the files for WDW.
Awesome site dot com and this web server could potentially be across the other side of the world and
sending messages back and forth can take some time.
But to say that you visit awesome site dot com and your computer sends the message all the way to the
web so that there happens to be on the other side of the world after its long journey.
Your request arrives and it waits patiently in line behind all of the other requests that have arrive
there first.
So after dealing with all the other requests that have come before you in the queue the observer will
ask How can I help.
And your request would say Can you give me a copy of your home page please.
And the web server would reply.
Sure.
Let me find it for you.
It's such as around for a little while and then goes on you go and transmits.
Bit by bit a copy of that file all the way back to your computer over the Internet across the entire
world.
Now you can imagine the whole process might take a bit of time wouldn't it.
And with that a cache the next time that you want access to the reader would up.
Awesome site dot com the same thing happens all over again.
Your quest to see the side of the world.
Wait in line and the file is sent bit by bit all the way back across the world.
And this happens again and again and again.
Now imagine that it's not just you but thousands or even millions of people all at the same time requesting
awesome sight.
Dot com I mean it is awesome after all.
And if everyone in the world has to do the same process over and over and over again you can imagine
that the web server might start to become a bit overburdened.
The queues get really long.
There's a backup on the data highway and your Web experience just slows way down.
So to fix this problem that's where a crash comes and that's what crashes come in.
OK.
So instead of being the only one copy of the file stored on the web server instead.
The very first time your request comes back your.
It will keep a copy on the local computer in what's called a cache.
The cache is nothing more than a place to store files locally so that you get performance benefits later.
The second time that you want to visit or visit or some site dot com your computer doesn't need to shoot
messages all over the Internet.
It realizes the awesome site dot coms files are already in your cash.
And then it just looks in the cache on your computer locally and loads the page which is much much faster.
Now the only issue is that the cache must be kept up to date with what's on the actual web server.
Otherwise you keep viewing an outdated copy of the files.
So that's what a cache is now that we in the want to caches.
We now understand the reason why the command is called apt cache.
OK.
And when we run at cache search what we're doing is we're telling the apt package manager to look inside
the cache for any packages matching the text that you give it.
So if we did apt cache search text it's looking inside its cache or packages that match the word text.
And if we run apt cache show Apache to it's going to look for the Apache to package in its cache and
bring up all the information that it's got about it.
So where is this cache then.
Well on a buntu the cache is located at slash var slash apt slash lists.
So if we C.D into their let's go ahead and take a look.
OK.
Such var slash opt slash sorry slash var slash lib slash Opt. slash lists.
OK so now we're in there.
If we take a look we can see there's a whole bunch of different Listen here let me just list them out
into the last comment.
And we can see that we've got a whole bunch of files in here that are actually just lists of packages.
Now these are the lists of all the packages available from repositories that have enabled on my system
and the lists also cover specific type of packages then let me clear the screen and let me just maximize
it as well and lists again.
But piping it through the last command with the capital an option and this allows us to have some line
numberings which will be make it a bit easier to explain what I'm talking about.
So here we are we've now got each of the lines with some line numberings they can see that are so many
different lists in this folder.
OK.
Each with a specific each containing less of a specific type of package depending upon where it came
from and what type of computer architecture it for.
Now a lot of mine start with the G-B dot archive dot to dot com.
OK.
Now that's because my nearest open to archive server will be in the UK because I'm based from the UK.
McCain MGB is for Great Britain and because I'm in the UK that's where it sends its requests because
it's a bit more efficient to send your requests to a server that's closer to you but yours might be
different depending upon where you are in the world.
OK so if you're in the U.S. it might say something like US DOT archived or buntu dot com and so on.
So don't worry about not having G-B that everything else should be more or less the same though now
on line 3.
There's a list of available artful for packages so for the OR for code name version of a buntu you can
see that we've got the binary packages or the precompiled packages that are for the AM the 64 computer
architecture from the main repository.
OK.
And if we take a look on line 15 we can see that we've got again for the artful version we've got the
binary pre-compiled packages for the HMD 64 Kopitar architectures a 64 bit architecture from the restricted
repository and you can see here we've got some from multi-verse and so on.
OK so the lists are broken up very specifically by where they came from and what they're for.
OK.
Now these are not the packages that are installed on my computer but they are the packages that are
available in the software repositories that I've chosen to access these.
I don't like these lists of packages that I have installed but their list of packages that I could install
for the software repositories.
OK.
So let's take a take a quick look at one of these files that are injured.
So let's say that we want to edit the entry for the GCC package that we downloaded a couple of videos
ago.
Well we know that it's going to be in the main repository because it's open source and there is free
software but it's not maintained by the community.
So we know that gcc should be the main repository of this pre-compiled and it's therefore a binary package.
OK we didn't have to download GCC and then compile it we just installed it straight away in the last
few videos which means that pre-compiled.
So if we look for the list that we see that's for artful main directory main repository with a preconfigured
pre-configured 64 bit binary.
Let's have a look for that regardful and we see from main our main binary HMD 64 so it should be in
this list.
So if I just copied out OK and I could this and I open up with Nonno.
So I do Nano and paste that if I can.
There we go.
So now if I press Enter say that we've opened the list and we've got a whole bunch of different packages
in here and you can see that this is starting to look but the results from apt cache show and that's
exactly what happens.
That cache will search through the files and print out the information regarding that package.
So now that way in this fall what do we just go ahead and search for the package called GCC.
So the way we can find that easy instead of just searching for gcc you can notice that the actual package
bit starts with the word package then a colon then a space then the actual package names.
Let's try and do that for gcc.
So we're going to package code space.
Gcc if I press enter will say we've ended up at the GCC package and you can see that we get all the
information about the GCC package that we installed a few minutes ago.
OK in the last video so.
OK.
And it comes up.
So let's change the priority from saying optional here to saying optional but awesome.
OK so if I if I save that right that far opposite same permission denied because this is a special file
going to open it with sudo.
OK so it's open it with sudo nano where you can do that and just press the barricade and type sudo at
the beginning and enter your password then we're going to search for package package code on gcc that
we are now instead of having it say optional.
I would say optional but also with the exclamation mark of course save the file and exit.
OK.
Now if we just close the terminal open it up again.
Now if we do opt cache show GCC and maximize the term a little bit piped up through less
we can see here that it's pulled the information for GCC and the priority is optional but awesome which
is fantastic.
How cool is that.
So you can see here that what's actually happening is you've got a cache I guess I'll place a folder
on your computer that stores lists that your package manager can search through regardless of whether
you've got internet connection or not and that is located at.
Slash var slash lib slap slash slash lists.
OK.
So if we go that a massive difficulty to say if you look in there you've got all these different lists
each for specific purposes.
OK.
And because we wanted to look for the GCC package we used a little bit of our understanding of repositories
to and the GCC package would be located in the main repository because it's it's probably it's maintained
by Canonical because it's so old you see you've got the it's pre-compiled is ready to go so it's going
to be binary and we aren't HMD 64 can be practical.
So that's the list that we're looking at.
So we kind of took this this file here this file name which is very long but it's a file name than the
last.
And we took a look at it with natto and we opened it up and we are open to enter my password.
So we open it up and we saw that this is where when you try to show more information about a package
the package manager gets his information.
And we looked for the GCC package OK and we found out that this is where it is.
And then we edited some of that information to demonstrate that this is exactly where the information
is coming from.
So if we now look at apt cache show GCC we can see that now that information is no longer optional.
Awesome but it's just optional.
Like I said you can see a bit behind the scenes how your package manager is working.
So now we understand that for performance benefits app it saves a cache of all available.
Two packages on your local system in the slash var slash lib slash Opt. slash lists directory.
OK.
And that's called the apt cache.
OK that folder is called the apt cache.
And by searching the apt cache using apt cache search and there's a search term Aptos search all of
the lists in those in that cache in a folder for any package names that have something to do with that
search term so we will search the package name and the package description in all of those lists and
return to the package names with a little snippet a little description of each package so that you can
look for more information if you want.
And you would look for more information using apt cache show and then the package name that app cache
search would give you back.
This will show you detailed information about the package OK things anything from the size of a description
to what it does who the maintainers are where to report bugs and everything that you could possibly
know about that package.
Now all of this is done using lists that are installed in the cache so lists are downloaded to the slots
of our slash lib slash and slash lists folder and all of those files in there are just lists of packages
and they all have basically the same format.
But that's where everything is saved and it just uses the lists in that folder to produce all this functionality.
But this makes us wonder how did the lists actually get into the cache in the first place.
And just like any cash it must be kept up to date.
Otherwise new packages could be released and you wouldn't know.
So how do we keep the catch up today.
Well you're in luck.
These questions and many more will be answered in the next video.