Hellova you beautiful people.
So in the last video I left you with kind of a cliffhanger with some burning questions that we have
about how apt package manager works.
How does the cache get there in the first place.
How can we make sure that the cash is kept up to date.
Well these are the questions that we'll be answering in this video by the end of this video you'll know
how to update your cash.
And you also know how to use that cash to upgrade all of the software on your system to the most uptodate
level with one simple command.
And this is going to be so awesome and I'm sure that you are you'll begin to see why package managers
are far superior to the simple wizards that you may be used to using.
Now I can't wait to show you this stuff.
So let's just go ahead and get right into it.
OK.
So how do the lists in the cache actually get there in the first place.
Well these lists are actually downloaded from servers somewhere on the Internet and these servers are
maintained by credible sources and contain up to date lists of all existing packages.
And as we mentioned in the last video in order for our cash to be functional the files in the cache
must be the same as the files on the server.
This is especially important for the software repositories.
So I think with me about the Linux community for another there are millions of people around the world
all contributing to this massive body of software and creating things all the time.
This massive body of people contributing simultaneously to the software repositories and products that
software changes a lot and it changes often.
Bugs get fix security holes get patched.
New features get added.
Documentation is codified and so on and so forth.
Now sometimes programs get developed so much that they require new dependencies in order to work.
And in spite all of these changes keep in all the software on your system today and managing everything
yourself manually would just be a complete nightmare.
It just wouldn't work.
There's too much room for a person to make a mistake and too much stuff to keep track of.
But fortunately you don't have to.
The apt package manager has a way of using the cache to make sure that all the software on your system
is completely up to date.
And here's how it works.
So the first thing you need to do is to update your cash and to do that you'd run sudo apt get update.
OK and that's the command you'd run.
Now notice how we need to use the sudo command at the beginning here.
Now that's because we're going to make changes to important files on our file system and we need administrator
privileges in order to do so.
And instead of apt cache we're using apt get because we're going to get data from the repositories so
we'll be getting the updated lists and update we'll update the lists and our cash to make sure that
the package versions in there are the same as the package versions in the repositories.
But of course in order for this to work we need to be connected to the Internet.
So I relabeled our internet connection before recording this video.
So if you are following along make sure you re-enable yours too.
And if we run now so sudo apt get update it will ask us to enter our password because we are using the
sudo commands or we enter that and we press enter and you can see that it's getting loads of different
lists from the buntu repositories and it's downloaded them and installing them.
Now it's going to be updating our cash which might take various amount of time depending on how long
it's been since you've updated.
But ours is gone and completed now.
So now that we've updated the cache will have the most up to date package numbers and dependencies for
all the packages in cash so that we have an up to date cache.
What if some of the software on our computer is out of date.
How can we upgrade our software to the newest versions that are in the new versions of the package lists.
Well that's actually really easy and quite magical to be honest.
So to upgrade every single piece of software on your system that you install from the repository is
all you need to do is type.
I play the screen sudo apt get upgrade.
OK now this will run through so Representer.
This will run through all the package lists and see all the software that we've got on our system and
it will tell us what's out of date and what needs to be updated and it also tell you how much needs
to be installed and so on and it asks for approbation to continue.
If I press yes.
So this is going to run on through the updated cache and see what packages on your system are behind
it and figure out what new dependencies need to be installed and which ones are no longer required.
They'll tell you how much space is required and so and so before asking your permission to continue.
But now that we've given it permission it will go ahead and start updating every piece of software on
the system or download the required packages unpack them install them and remove the old versions automatically
for every single piece of software on the entire system that was installed using the repositories.
This is an incredibly powerful automated system and this is really the beauty of using a package manager.
You don't have to go to the Web site and download manually each piece each new package like you might
have to do on Windows or Mac.
We've got to download the new installer or click for updates on each different piece of software.
Now all you have to do is want to upgrade upgrade everything that was installed through the repositories
will be upgraded to the newest version levels which helps you with security.
It helps you with having the most modern features and it's just absolutely.
And also if you use Krumm you can schedule this stuff to happen on a regular basis as well so that's
a useful thing to bear in mind.
Now this might take a varying amount of time depending upon how long it's been since since we've upgraded
our software and because I haven't actually done it on this virtual machines it will take quite a while.
So I'm going to do is I'm going to cut the video here and come back when it is done.
And just like that into commands.
All the software on our system has been upgraded and we can actually see that the Firefox logo has been
updated to look a whole lot more epic.
So notice how the system also didn't need to reboot all the software that we've installed that the repositories
has been upgraded and it's ready to go.
So all we had to do was update the package list using sudo apt get update and then once we updated it
or waited it was sudo apt get upgrade and then we upgraded all the software to the new versions.
So do know that sometimes you will need to reboot your system when you do these updates but this is
kind of unusual but sometimes it will need to happen.
But it's important to note that you should always update your cache before you perform an upgrade and
make sure that the upgrade occurs using the correct software versions and everything is updated uniformly.
So to update your cache you've run sudo apt get update and what this will do is it will download the
most updated versions of the package lists from the two servers into your cache that is stored on your
computer.
So in order to do that you need to have an internet connection.
But once you've updated your cache by downloading the most updated package lists you can upgrade all
of the software on your system using sudo apt get upgrade.
And what this will do is it will make the package manager look at all the software that is currently
on your system and compare it to what is available in the package lists and then the package manager
will automatically download and upgrade all the different packages that can be downloaded in order to
update your system to the most up to date level so this will download any new versions of packages that
remove old versions it'll download any new required dependencies.
And this just helps you know increase your system security.
It helps give you maximum functionality and it's all round just fantastic but something that you need
to bear in mind is that you need to update the cache before you upgrade because otherwise you'll be
upgrading all your software to lock the most up to date versions and you want to be able to update your
software to update versions in order to do that you need uptodate package lists so to update those lets
you update your cash and then when you've updated your cache you can operate your software.
So bear that in mind.
Always update your cache before you upgrade your software.
Another important thing to bear in mind here is that you can only upgrade software that was installed
through the repositories.
OK that is possible on a Gonu Linux system like we did in the previous videos where we modified the
ls command.
You can download packages manually extract them and compile them and install them yourself.
But because that process doesn't happen through the repositories and package manager you lose the ability
to keep them up to date like we are doing here.
So therefore if you can download a package from a web site and you can also get it from the absentee
repositories make sure to get it from the repositories because then you can make sure that it's up to
date.
Make sure you always have the best features available.
Using this automated process so as of now we've discussed how to search for software had to update caches
and how to upgrade software.
But we haven't discussed had to actually install new software.
Well with all the understanding that you have now that's actually going to be really easy for you so
I'll save that little gem for the next video.