So in the last few videos we've been learning a whole lot about our package manager and how it works.
And we learned about the cash and what it's for we've learned about how to update the cash and how to
upgrade all of the software on our system to the newest versions using the package manager which is
all super awesome stuff.
But how can we install new packages.
That's what we want to know.
Well with the background that you've gained from the previous videos install it will be really easy
to understand and not just something that you have to memorize.
And by the end of this video you will know how to install new software from the command line.
So let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK.
So whether we know that our cash and system are fully up to date let's go ahead and install some new
software.
So let's say that I've heard of a program called X eyes and X always apparently makes a window with
some funny eyes pop up that follow your mouse cursor around the screen.
And I think this is interesting and I want to install it.
So do that first we need to know what package the excise program comes in.
So let's search the cache for it the way that we do that is we do apt cache search for excise and it
will give us every package that has something to do with excise.
And we've heard of this package called x 11 apps let's say and we like ah that's the one I've heard
of let me go and have a closer look at it.
So we do we do apt Cash show x 11 apps.
OK.
So you give it the name of the package here and that will give us a bunch of information.
But let's just clear the screen and pipe that through less so we get a bit of a closer look.
OK.
And when we open this here we can see that actually that we get a lot of information about the package.
But down here in the description it says that this package provides a miscellaneous assortment of X
applications that ship with the X Window System including And it will tell us that we've got something
tools for manipulating bitmap images something for a tool that tells you when you have new e-mail and
so on.
And then there's a one here called X eyes and an excise is a demo program in which a pair of eyes track
the pointer.
So that's what we want and we realize that actually we want to have a look at this is also another one
called X man which is a manual page browser which you know might be useful as well.
OK so now we're pretty convinced we want to install the x 11 apps package.
How can we do that.
Well it's actually really easy to do if we get out of less is just when we clear the screen or we've
got to do type sudo apt get install X 11 apps so we just enter the name of the package.
Now notice that we're using apt get a gap to install the package because we want our package manager
to get data from the internet and not just from the local cache.
And we also passed the package name that we wanted to install which um because we want to install X
and iPhone apps we typed x 11 apps in there when we press enter.
We see that it would ask for a password which we enter and then the package manager is going to go ahead
and install the new packages with many dependencies that are actually required.
Now sometimes it might ask for your permission if it needs to install a lot but because its only installing
about 600 kilobytes it was like Here let me just go ahead and install it.
It has a provision for something that so small OK but that has nothing to do the package is installed
and its as simple as that now.
X 11 apps is a precompiled package also known as a binary package.
Now most packages are binary packages which means that the code that make the software has been precompiled
and ready to go beforehand so you don't have to do any of that configure make and make install stuff
that we did a few videos ago yourself.
Like I just installed the package from the repositories and you're done.
And what's better the package will also be tracked for updates so you can update the package if new
updates are made available.
How awesome is that.
Now let's try out our new software.
So we wanted to use the x is program.
So if we just play the screen and type x is in there and press enter.
You'll see that we get these funny googly eyes pop up on the screen that follow our most surrounds if
I put the most down here.
What was it got scared away the eyes if I pop him up here then it will follow around properly not as
fluidly as I'd like but I'm going to put that down to us running this in a virtual machine.
But if like you know it does follow a whole lot nicer.
But that's pretty cool right now.
The awesome thing is the way that you wouldn't you install will come with its own man page self-disclose
excise here.
Then if I do man X eyes you'll see that he's actually now also got a manual page installed that says
follow the mouse X demo.
And it's also got some options.
You can even control the excise program from the command line and we can see here that there is a there
is an option here called Center which allows you to choose a different color for the center of the eyes.
So for example if we do excise thinking at the center option and tell it I think it's two dashes center
blue upslope maybe just one maybe just one dash.
There we go.
Now the center the ice is blue and I want you to know is here is the way that look when you open the
exercise program graphically.
You don't have the option to change the color of the eyes.
Right.
But from the command line you can change that and a whole lot more.
So this is highlighting for you just how powerful the command line is and how it does give you more
abilities than is possible with a graphical editor.
And if you can edit the color of googly eyes then tell me what really is the point of having a computer.
Now the S11 apps package came with quite a few other pieces of software inside one of which is called
X man which you might find useful.
Now X man is a graphical window for looking at the manual pages.
So if we get rid of excise here and close it and then we type X man we'll see a window pop up over here.
Now you can search the man pages using this if we click on manual page right there and open up a bigger
window and if we click on the on the options at the top here if we hold down the mouse button it shows
the menu to hold down the mouse button and you'll see this dropdown menu.
Then if you go on search and let go of the mouse that is if we click the search thing.
And now we can search for something in here.
So this is for example if we take a look at LS and we try to look at it as a manual page then it'll
open up the LS manual page and you can browse through it here.
So this is a great more I guess graphical way of taking a look at the manual pages than you do with
the command line.
But you know which I guess it just makes it look pretty and you can also look at the sections so you
can look in user commands and you can see all of the user commands here.
And if I wanted to look at let's say the the address to line command or just click on that and it would
open up so it's a nice graphical way of browsing through the manual so that's something you can play
around with if you like.
And one thing I also want to highlight is how by installing one package the x 11 apps package will actually
installed multiple different pieces of software which is super cool.
And we didn't have to do any compiling we didn't have to do any configuring or had to do was make sure
that our package list was up to date using sudo apt get updates and then or wait to do them whooshes
sudo apt get install and then a package name and that's it.
We can we can rest assured that we've got the most up to date version of that package and it's also
it's also we didn't even have to find out if the package was suitable for our computers architecture
and decide between you know 386 or am 64 that was all catered for automatically which is awesome.
But all of the software in that package was pre-compiled.
So what if we wanted to utilize the freedoms that free software gives us and access the source code
for a package and modify it while accessing the source code from the repositories it's also very easy.
But there are a few edits that you need to make.
So for all that freedom goodness I'll see you in the next video.