Hello you beautiful people and welcome to this video where we're going to be talking about how you can
download the source code for packages.
So at the minute all we've been able to do is download and install precompiled binary packages but we're
interested in how we might be able to go about getting source code so we can exercise the freedoms that
free software gives us.
And it's actually a very easy process in order to do so or what to do is as an administrator.
So with the sudo command open up in natto the slash at c slash apt slash sourses doc list file.
Ok now in here when you enter your password you're going to be opening up a configuration file the package
manager uses to determine which repositories and which package files it downloads.
In other words which source is it downloads.
OK so what we're going to do in here is you'll notice that there are lines that start with Debb source
or Debb dash S or C and those lines have a hash in front of them.
What I want to do is I want to just delete all those hashes on those appropriate lines.
And what this will do is it will activate the ability for your package manager to be able to download
source code which is deactivated by default just to save efficiency basically.
So we're going to Haven't done that.
I'm going to press control in 0 to save the file or press X control of X to exit.
So then what we've done is we've said to the package manager hey why don't you go ahead and download
the package lists that contain source code.
Ok but to be able to get those things in the cache we've got to update our cash.
OK so all I was do sudo apt get updates and it's going to go ahead and start downloading all the source
packages here.
So you can see that this is is installing all the source packages into cache.
This is a very useful thing because now we can we're almost ready to be able to download source code.
OK so before we can download source code we need to install one more package which is so to get installed
is going to be the package dash dev package the DP K.G. dash dev.
You install that you type yes when it asks you and there we are we've managed to now it's going to go
ahead and download and unpack that package and now we can go ahead and install source code.
It's literally that simple.
OK so we've been messing around with the excise package I made over to the desktop and we've been messing
around with the excise package.
How can we get the source code for the for the excise package or the exercise program.
Well it's contained in the x 11 apps package.
So if we do sudo apt get and we used to do install right we do install X 11 apps right.
That's how you'd get the pre-compiled binary version.
But if you want to get the source code it sort of instead of install just put source and you'll see
that it goes ahead and downloads these packages to contain source code.
Now we can actually go ahead and enter these using CD.
So if we CD into the package and take a look around we can see there's is a folder here for X eyes and
if we take a look in X eyes a CD X eyes will be seen here that we've got the source code for the exercise
program so you can see we've got our config file that we can can use to configure our new C-compiler.
But what we're interested in right now is this excise Dotsie which is actually the source code for the
exercise program and we can take a look in here and read the source code for the exercise program.
It's literally that simple.
OK.
All we had to do was go ahead and change our slash ETSI slash ops slash sources.
Dart last fall and in here just uncomment all the lines that had that had a hash in front of them for
Debb source.
And those are the repositories that allow you to actually download source code to view and comment all
of those and then update your cache using sudo apt get updates then what you've downloaded all the new
less We've got to do is install the is install the DP K.G. dev package and then you get to go in there
from now on if you ever want to download any source code and all you've got to do is sudo apt get source
and then a package name.
OK.
And that is all you need to know in order to be able to download and play around with source code.
But one thing that you should bear in mind is that if you go into the source code packages and you actually
compile them you'll lose the ability to install them that way you'll lose the ability to keep them updated
with your package manager.
So therefore if you have the choice to install a package through the package manager or install it from
source make sure that you install it through the package manager and through the repositories rather
than compiling it yourself.
But this is a really cool way to be able to go ahead and take a look at how code works and maybe incorporate
it in your projects.