Hello you beautiful people.
Now as you know there are two sides to every coin.
And now that you've learned how to install packages to your system in this video we're going to be covering
how you can uninstall packages from your system and make sure that your system is squeaky clean.
So let's just go ahead and get right into it.
OK.
So in the last few videos we've been messing around with the x 11 apps package and we're going to continue
using that as kind of our guinea pig for this video.
So to uninstall a package in a boon to the most basic way to do it is to type sudo apt get remove and
then the package name.
OK so because we are talking about the x 11 apps package we just type sudo apt get remove and then x
11 apps.
And that would remove it but that's not the preferred way to do it.
OK.
And the reason is when you install packages there are sometimes configuration files that come along
with the packages and if you just remove the package using sudo apt get remove then the configuration
files are left behind on your system taking up space and not being helpful.
Now this can be useful if you want to install the package again in the future and want all your settings
to be the same but it's still not really the preferred way to do it.
Instead to remove a package and all of its configuration files what we do is instead of typing silap
get removed we type sudo apt get Perge and then the package name.
Like I a pseudo get purred.
Excellent apps now the purge will remove the package and its configuration files.
So always use Perge whatever you want to install a package.
So if I go ahead and do that it's going to go and say hey I want to remove this is OK.
I press yes.
I will go through and remove x 11 apps and any of its configuration files so you can see here it says
purging configuration files for x 11 apps.
OK so it's gone ahead and done that.
Now that will have the 11 apps package 100 percent removed from the system.
But sometimes when you install packages you need to install like 10 other different packages as dependencies.
OK so you need in order to get the package that you want to install to work you need like 10 other packages
or maybe even a hundred of the packages in order to get that one package to work.
And we call those extra packages dependancies.
So if those dependencies are no longer required but you don't know what they're called How can you remove
them.
Well you're in luck in order to remove packages that were installed as dependencies but are no longer
required for any other package on the system.
You can just do sudo factory the screen sudo apt get auto remove and that's it.
So sudo get or to remove now or to remove will automatically remove any dangling dependencies that are
no longer required which helps you save space on your systems if I do that it's going to tell me there's
actually not any that need to be removed but you can save a lot of space in this.
So bear in mind this is all happening across hundreds or even thousands of different packages on your
system and having the package manager keep everything in order automatically is a really great asset.
I'm sure you'd agree it beats doing it yourself anyway.
Now whenever you download and install a package or a copy of the package is saved locally on your computer.
Now if this package is then unpacked and stored on your systems that's how it works when you install
a package download itself as a compressed archive then unpacks itself and installs itself on your system.
OK.
Because that two step process not only has a package installed on your system but a compressed version
of it is also saved at least compressed files usually take up space and aren't really necessary if you
already have the package installed and because they're just you know an archive like the wrapper that
comes with the stuff.
OK.
So you can actually save yourself massive amounts of space between gigabytes of space just by deleting
these archives.
OK.
Now these archives are stored.
If we go that slash var slash cache slash apt slash archive.
So if we go there and take a look we can say there's quite a few little deadfalls here some compressed
archives saved and then you can see the one for x 11 apps even though we've actually removed it from
the system.
And you can see how large these are by doing ls with the El-Hage command.
And you can see that there's a total of about 10 megabytes in there and that's not much.
But you know this can easily grow to gigabytes after you keep installing packages on your system.
It can get quite mad because every package you install comes with its own dependencies.
And even those dependencies are saved as copies so you can really save a lot of space by removing the
stuff from here.
Now you don't have to even be in the folder to remove them so if I just head back to our home directory
and there you can see where our home directory if we run sudo apt get clean that will delete all of
the packages from that directory.
If we had back up into the slash var slash cache slash and slash archives into an address we can see
that either.
Or been deleted even though we weren't in that folder.
So if you want to get rid of all that stuff do sudo apt get clean.
But sometimes you don't want to delete all of those for whatever reason and you only want to get rid
of the stuff you want to get rid of those packages those those those archives but the ones for packages
that can no longer be accessed from the from the actual Aponte repulsive areas that this is usually
for systems that are very old and want to keep their cash going for years and years and years and then
from now and then just trim the leaves and get rid of the deb packages that can no longer be downloaded
for whatever reason and to do that instead of using sudo apt get clean.
You do use auto clean now as just to highlight clean gets rid of everything of those in the archive
cache that is different from the from the list cache.
By the way that's just a this is just a storage space for for saved archives and packages and stuff
so this is a completely different cache.
But clean will remove everything in there and auto clean will check what's in there and only delete
the ones that you can no longer download from the repositories to make sure you don't have stuff in
there that you'll never use again.
So they have a no nonsense guide to uninstalling packages.
So let's review.
OK we discuss at the most basic way to review packages is to use sudo apt get remove and then the package
name.
But this is not recommended because it leaves behind configuration files.
Instead use sudo apt get Perge and then the package name.
OK now when you install the package it's likely the other dependency packages were also installed in
order to make that package work in order to get rid of those dependencies and automatically remove them
from the system.
As long as they're are no longer required you would use sudo apt get auto remove or to remove any unwanted
and needed dependencies.
OK.
And just because they were used for one package and you loof that package doesn't mean they're no longer
needed for another.
But don't worry about that.
The package is going to take care of all that for you OK.
And you also learned that when a software package is installed it is first downloaded and saved on your
system in a compressed archive.
This archive is safe on your system even if the package is installed.
And that means it's taking up space.
It's not like the wrapper or the packaging behind the actual thing that you want.
OK so to clean up all the packaging and clean up all that stuff what ever do is sudo apt get clean and
that's going to delete all the compressed package archives and save you a heck of a lot of space.
You'll be surprised sometimes even gigabytes at times.
But perhaps you don't want to clean up all of those packages for some reason and instead said you just
want to clean up the ones that can no longer be downloaded from the buntu repositories.
So for that you use sudo to get auto clean.
OK so there you have it.
Beautiful people you know.
Everything that you will ever need to know about package management InnoCentive and they've done so
unbelievably well that in the next video I would like to congratulate you and have a recap of what we've
learned.
So for some well-deserved praise and a recap I'll see you in the next video.