Hello you beautiful person and welcome to this very exciting section of the Course all about automating
tasks using bash scripts and Crohn.
Now up until now you've been learning how to do commands one after the other on the command line.
But sometimes however you want to complete tasks that require multiple steps.
So instead of just memorizing the steps and entering those steps those command steps every single time
you need to complete that task.
You can instead write those commands into a text file known as a bash script and then just run the script
again.
And when you run the script each of the commands in the script will be run one after the other from
top to the bottom so the show will start at the top of the script and work its way down through the
script executing all of the commands on the way.
All right.
So in this section of the course you're going to learn how to create and run your very own bash scripts
but you're also going to see how you can schedule those commands and backflips to be run at certain
times using a really handy scheduling program called Krumm.
Now bash scripting is a whole massive field in and of itself.
So this won't be an overly detailed section of the course but I hope that by the end of the section
you'll have the fundamental concepts and understanding of what bad scripting is all about so that you
can start writing your own simple script.
You also know how to schedule and automate commands and scripts.
Any time you choose by using Krumm book and combining these two skills will allow you to truly set your
workflow on autopilot.
So now that you've got a quick heads up about what's going to be covered in this section let's jump
right in in the next video by learning how to write your very own scripts.