Hello the beautiful people and welcome to this very exciting section of the Course all about bash scripts
and in the next few videos you're going to learn how you can create your own bad scripts which are incredibly
useful tools that will allow you to automate your workflows.
Now learning about bad scripts is a massive field in and of itself and it would require its own course
to cover properly.
But by the end of the next few videos you're going to have the fundamental understanding required about
how bad scripts work and how to create them so that you can begin automating your workflows using the
commands that you've learned so far in the course.
So it's going to be an incredible an incredible piece of learning for you and to let you understand
how you know what bash scripts or how to use them or you know how they basically work so it can be very
very exciting.
Hope you're ready to gain some serious superpowers so let's not let's not mess around anymore.
Let's go jump right in and start making our very first batch script.
All right so let's go ahead and make a simple bash script.
Let's do that.
All we need to do is just make a text file.
So to do that let's go ahead and open up Nonno on our desktop and make a file called our script doc.
SH OK.
So all I'm doing here when I give the file SH fartleks file extension is just making it easier for us
to see that this is a bash script and with SH being short for for the bash shell.
OK.
So if I open and press control and O to save it you'll see that the script has popped up on the left
and if I just close that and clear the screen we've now got this file.
Let's take a closer look at this file.
Let's see if it's anything special to the shell.
Using the file command.
If I do file script SH We see that it's not it's nothing special as far as the shell is concerned.
It's just an empty file.
It doesn't matter whether this was done sage or datcha sublime or dot whatever.
OK.
So with that piece of information let's go ahead and open our script and let's do the most important
thing that you need to do.
When ever you write a new script.
OK.
You need to tell it that this is actually a special file and that this file isn't just a text file.
It needs to be read using a certain interpreter there interpreter is something that will read a file
and interpret each of the lines in that file as a certain type of code.
OK.
So instead of just reading cat OK if I told this that this is a bash script it would read this is the
cat command instead of just Katter's And you know the animal.
OK if I read eg if I typed echo it would interpret this file as the echo command.
It wouldn't just interpret it as an echo that you hear in you know when you are in a cave when you show
into into a hole or somewhere like made of stone.
OK.
So this is the important part we attended that this isn't a normal text file.
It needs to be interpreted as code and more specifically as a bash script.
So to do that you need to first type what's called the Shabangu.
Now the Shabangu is a hash.
So.
And then Abangan exclamation mark and a hash symbol the exclamation mark is called the Shabangu.
And then you type the path to the interpreter.
Now the bash interpreter is at slash bin slash Bash.
So this is our first line.
We type the Shabangu hash bang.
OK.
Then slash bin slash.
BASH Now that that slash been slash Bash is the path to abash interpreter and we can see that if I close
out of nano by using the command and typing Bash and we see that we get slash been slash bash as the
path to the bash shell.
OK.
So what we're saying here is hey this isn't a normal text file.
You need to interpret this file using the bash the bash shell interpreter run this is a bash shell script.
And the key is this line needs to be the first line it cannot be the second line has the absolute first
line and the Campione space is on the line so you finish the line right away.
OK.
And when we save that.
Now if we look at the script with the with the fork and we see that it is now a shell script.
In fact I'm a born again shellscript never born again shell is bash.
So you've got born again shall I born again.
Shell is bash.
So this is saying it's a bash shell script and it knows that because it's got this this Shabangu line.
Now if you know anything at Python programming you'll know that the Python programming language is also
an interpreted programming language and the command to run something is a Python script.
On on on Linux is Python 3 OK for Python 3.
So if we type which Python 3 it'll tell us the path to the to the Python 3 interpreter just like it
did for the of Jupiter.
And if I copy the Open up script again and I write the shebang line again and write Shabangu.
So shebang and then I paste in there the path to the Python interpreter.
So sloshy uses rapin slash Peiffer and three and save the repped.
If I now look at scripts you can see that the shell sees that this is now a Python script so that's
how you would do this kind of stuff if you wanted to write a script in the Python programming language
because we want to write a bash script which is going to give it the path to the to the bash interpreter
which is a slash being slash bash save that.
And then when we look we see that it's again a born again shell script bash script.
OK so with that important concept understood Let's go back to editing bash cryptanalysis clear the screen
in nano.
Now anything that we write in here with this special line added anything that we write below will now
be interpreted as they do in the normal shell.
So for example if I write Ecko and then something like.
Hello world.
OK.
This line will be interpreted as a command.
It's as if I just typed echo Hello world in my shell.
So let's see this in action.
OK let's save the file using control.
Oh OK.
And now if we type bash script we see that it's run.
Hello world.
How cool is that.
Right.
So it ran the commands that are inside there.
Now we can do what ever we want in our script.
Let's just try and add more stuff.
OK let's let's let's open it up with another.
And now let's clear out this echo thing let's just get rid of this using the cut command the control
OK or just go to the whole line.
That's a nice little shortcut for deleting a line.
Now let's actually use in here.
Let's let's try and create a file a folder called Magic.
OK on our desktop now inside the magic folder we're going to make one hundred files and then we'll use
the ls command to get information about each of those files and save it to save all the information
to a log file on our desktop.
OK.
So what command.
Here's a test for you know what come on would we need to create a folder called Magic on our desktop.
Well M K D I'll come and write the Moktar command.
So let's make a director this type.
M d I are on our desktop.
Let's make a file called Magic.
OK so that's going to be our magic directory.
Now we need to make 100 files in it.
So what might we do that.
Well we might move into the Directory so we might move into the magic directory using CD then we might
touch I guess 100 files of file one to 100.
OK.
That might be what we do.
So far so good.
We've created a file called a folder called Magic.
We've gone into the folder and then we've created 100 files.
Now let's let's like you know create Let's use the LS command to get data about each of those files.
So if we use the ls command and we let's say give it let's say we want to use long form information
and human readable information and save all that to a file on our desktop called magic dot log.
OK let's leave it there.
OK so what we've done we've used the make We've made a directory on our desktop we have changed into
that directory we've created 100 files and then we use the last dash El-Hage command on our.
I should actually.
Good thing I checked.
I should check our magic folder and then redirect all the information into a file called Magic don't
log.
So if I save that they're closed.
And now we we can see the contents of this file using the cat command just like any other file we can
do and we can see the contents.
But now let's go ahead and actually run it.
OK.
So if we try to bash our script buah Did you see that we've managed to create a folder on the desktop.
Inside there there are now 100 files and if we look in this magic dot log file we see detailed information
about every single one of the files inside that folder just like we told the script to do so isn't that
absolutely awesome right so this is how bad scripts work you basically type in the commands that you
want it to do just as if you were typing them in in the in the normal shell.
But the benefit is we now have this file that we can keep and do stuff with whenever we want.
Said you can actually you know save that for later.
Now this should be a moment of amazement for you.
So think about this for a moment.
OK.
In Linux you can control anything using the command line whatever you want whenever you want to change
whether it be your desktop background whether it be the font color whether it be you know messages that
pop up when you log in you can change anything using the command line.
OK.
And you can write scripts to hold command line commands.
So therefore you can write scripts that can do anything on your computer and save them for later.
And you can run them whenever you want and bash scripts are therefore part of what give you complete
customized ability of a Linux machine and they are incredibly incredibly powerful tools.
So you've seen in this video how to make a bash script but in the next video what we're going to do
is we're going to do it all over again and we're going to show you how you can write a batch script
to make regular backups for use that's going to be very very cool.
I'm going to show you how to run it in a much more convenient way as well.
So we're going to break the video here and in the next video we're going to pick it up again by showing
you how to make a bash script to do backups.