Hello you beautiful people.
Welcome back to the second part of our discussion about making your very own bash scripts and in this
video we're going to make another bus stripped and that's going to allow us to back up all the folders
in our home directory and we're also going to show you how you can set up your script so they can be
run in a more convenient way.
So let's make another bash script.
We're going to call it back up.
Sh on our desktops we're going to type nano then back up our DOT sh.
I mean there we're going to add as the very first line as Shabangu line and our shebang line tells the
shell to not read this code not read this far as a text file but instead to interpret it as a bash script.
So the way we do that is we type a hash then a banks or hash and then an exclamation mark.
And then the path to the interpreter that we want this file to be interpreted with and that is going
to be a bash shell which is located at slash Ben slash Bash and we can check that if I close out of
that.
And you go back to our command line by typing which and then bash We can see slushed been slash Bash
is where the bash interpreter is located.
So with that if we open back up our backup script we can now underneath here start writing commands
that will make up our script.
Now we want the script to him to compress and archive all of the folders inside our home directory or
at least the downloads documents desktop pictures and videos folders because they're the best.
So let's just let's see how we might do that.
I mean if you remember from what we learnt at the end of the last section to make this happen we'll
need to use the tar command and we need to give it a few options.
So for example we'll give it the C option to create a new god archive.
The the option to make it speak to us and the option to tell it that the next argument is going to be
our it's going to be our all kuffar and we're going to call it back up dot tar dot Zed.
OK.
But to make it compressed using Jesus.
Actually to give it the Zed option as well.
So we're going to compress it through Jesus up into a file called backup Doc tor doc Jesus.
But then we need to tell it what we want to actually store.
And this is what we're going to tell it.
We're going to say hey I want you to put in there we to want to put in there everything in our home
directory we're going to put in our documents folder downloads folder Iowa desktop folder pictures folder
and our videos folder.
OK.
So what we're saying here is hey use the Torkham and compress it.
Be verbose tell us what's going on zip zip through Jesus up and make the file called backup doc Todd.
Geez.
And inside there put the documents down those desktop pictures and videos folders from our home directory
using a bit of brace expansion to save some typing.
OK.
So that's it.
And then when we run our boss script if we do bash backup dice page you'll see that it's giving us some
output and now we've got a backup top target file on our desktop so it's not very cool right and you
can see here all the files that have been added into the into the interior into the backup folder now
in there we gave it the v option here for verbose and that's what we got to seal the output on the screen
maybe we don't want that so if we just get rid of the V and let's say we remove a backup dot tautologies.
And now we run again.
You can see that now we don't really have as much output from it but we've still got the backup file.
So you can see here.
One benefit of writing these things in scripts you can save and edit the behavior of those scripts over
time as your needs evolve and that always can be there for you to run.
For example we might not like the fact that this message comes out on standard error so we can just
go back into our backup Dyess page and redirect this this command standard error to place called slash
dev slash note which basically gets rid of it.
OK so we've redirected some of them to slash dev slash no which is the place on a file system called
the bit bucket that basically just deletes whatever is sent to it.
And now if we try to run bash backup up sh clear the screen we're running now so that we can get no
output.
But if I delete this backup archive and run it you can see that the backup is still created but now
we don't get any error.
So you can see that you can customize these these scripts as time goes on.
So we don't want to draw attention to a bit right now is how we can make running the bash scripts a
bit more efficient and user friendly.
So at the minute what we're doing is we are on our desktop where the bash script is located in the background
and then giving it the path to the bash script which at the minute because we're already on the desktop
it's just back up to our stage.
When I run that we get the the the required output.
But that's kind of a bit of hassle because if we weren't on the desktop then we would have to give it
a different path and we have to in the background there's a there's a better way to do it in just one
step.
OK.
And this is how you set that up so what you do is you go back to your home directory and you can see
in here that we've just got our normal folders.
What you do is you make a directory called been all in lower case like I've been.
And you can see that's been created.
And you what you do is you move all of your shell scripts into that folder it's moved from our desktop
the backup.
Files are backup Dyess.
We're going to move it into bin folder.
OK so we're moving from our desktop the backup S.H. folder file into our bin folder because you see
it's been moved from there.
I mean we now go into our bin.
We see the backup Dyas pages in that.
And actually I'm just going to rename it from backup to stage into just backup.
OK.
So now we've just got the same file called backup and if I run it it'll still work.
So there's nothing wrong.
It's just renamed it a little bit.
OK.
Now I need to make this so that it can be run from the command line.
OK so what we're going to do is two ways to do this.
First of all we can open up in our file browser we can go into bin and then we can right click click
properties go in permissions and then click allowing executing file as program.
OK.
That's one way to do it but I'm not going to do it like that for now because I want you to learn the
terminal way.
So what you do is you type the C Hage mode command never see Hach mode command sense for change mode
and what it does is it allows you to change the permissions that a certain file has.
And then as the second argument type plus X which means give it executable permission so add executable
permissions and then you tell it the file.
So just backup when I run that's what we've done is we've added executable missions to the backup.
Now when I look at it with LS You can see that it's gone green.
OK.
So that means that it can be run as a script.
Now the cool thing about this is that if we close to actually we're going to do as well just to make
it a bit clearer if we go back into backup what we're going to do is I'm going to save make sure that
the backup is always saved on the desktop.
That's just going to make it a bit clearer to demonstrate what's happening.
So what we're going to we're going to close the terminal and delete her backup here.
OK.
And now I notice I'm in our home directory OK but if I type back up we can see here that we're getting
an error saying that the backup program is not currently installed.
And if you remember what I told you a long time ago.
Right the start this course when the shell says it can't find something that means it's not on the shelves
search path.
So we need to edit the shell search path to include recently created bin folder.
Now the way that we do this is we're in our home directory.
If we go ahead and use the Nano command I want you to edit the dot Bash RC file so the doc Bash RC space
is all lowercase will open up this very important file.
Now if we scroll all the way down to the bottom and Odelein down there this is what I want you to write.
OK.
And what is the right path in upper case then an equal sign then some double quotes or two double quotes
and inside those double quotes dollar sign paff a colon then Dollar Sign home in uppercase slash been
OK.
So let me explain this a little bit.
So what we're saying here is a variable called Path.
We're going to have a path equal to what the path currently is then a colon then our home folder slash
been so the bin folder in our home folder is going to be added to the path.
And when I close that we write to the boss Aussie close it and if we close our terminal and open another
one.
What that has done if we echo the path what Pat has done is it has added Slash's home slushes Ziyad
slash been to our path.
Now that means it'll be able to search for our backup script in the path just like it would any of the
command center when I run back up.
You can see the ascript has just been run and it has now created the backup so if I if I right now go
into our bin folder and I create another file called Hello for example and in there I tell it that it's
a bash script with the shebang.
And I say echo Hello world.
OK.
And save it.
And then I give the file executable permission so S.H. maade plus X Hello.
See that it's gone green.
Now I can be anywhere in my file system.
I could be in my documents folder.
OK but if I've run.
Hello.
You can see that hello world networks and I can pipe these to wherever I want to redirect them so if
I redirects it to a file called haloed text here on my desktop there we are.
We've now got I Farkle haloed activity on the desktop and wouldn't know basically creating our own commands
so isn't that awesome right.
We've got our own our own commands on anything that we put in this bin folder if we have executable
permissions we can run it just like any other command.
So that is incredible.
But now you might be thinking OK Ziyad this is cool and everything but what's really the difference
between an alias and a script.
So remember aliases are things that you put in your in your in your back aliases file.
This one is dhaba Batia aliases file.
And if we if we take a look in there what we're doing is we are you know setting command names and we're
giving them those commands mean.
Why didn't we just make a make an alias and we say backup equals toss dash C-v Zed f of you know to
our to our desktop and then pull back up dot top dog Zed and say we want in there we want our desktop
and our documents and we're and I download pictures and videos and then close it.
Why don't we just do that and say I'd like we you know we know how to make aliases.
Wouldn't that work the same way.
Yes it would work the same in this instance because we have a one line script like I'm going to close
out what I'm going to do.
And that's because we have a one line script so aliases can become you know of the same as one line
scripts really.
But the good thing about scripts is that scripts are designed to contain more than one command line
was.
Aliases are usually just to give more convenient names to just one command line.
Now secondly scripts can have more complicated programming constructs such as loops if statements and
functions.
Now if you've never done any programming before.
Suffice it to say that scripts are more heavy duty than alias's can be OK.
And thirdly scripts can be scheduled to run at any time.
Using cron and not scheduling part is what we're going to focus on in the next video so over the last
couple of videos you've seen how to create your very Ambala scripts.
And the key about bash scripts is that they allow you to store useful command sequences in files that
you can use later on.
Now because anything on your computer is changeable and editable through the command line and because
you can save the series of commands that can do specific functions you can create you incredibly powerful
bash scripts that can do whatever you want and save those backups scripts for later by using the fundamental
skills that you've learned in the last two videos.
Now a key piece of information is that bash scripts must have the Shabangu line telling them that the
file needs to be interpreted as Bash commands using the bash shell interpreter which is located at slash
been slash Bash.
Now this shebang line is the first line of every script and there wouldn't be anything above it and
there mustn't be any spaces in the shebang line the text that's highlighted here in Orange.
So it must come just as you see it there and it's the Shabangu line that turns your regular text file
into a bash script and tells the shell to interpret everything in that file as Bash commands.
Now if you wanted to make a Python script you could put the shebang line something like flashbang slash
slash use a slash been slash Python 3 and that would allow the script to be interpreted as a Python
program.
But this is how you do it in orange here for bash scripts they've also seen how you would make scripts
runnable just like regular commands.
And you saw how you would make a BIN folder in your home directory and add each script to that bin folder.
You would then give each of the scripts executable permissions using the S.H. maade command and add
that bin folder to your Shell's path by editing your bash RC file.
And this allows you to run scripts just like regular commands so we type back up and our backup script
run we thought hello hello script run and this will also work for Python programs as well.
Now as an aside if you're interested in learning more about the Python programming language then go
to the last video of course where you have some discount coupons for all my courses including my best
selling Python course the python Bible which will take you in a project based way from absolutely no
previous Python experience all the way to writing 11 Python programs.
So for me interested go ahead and check that out.
But the bottom line is that scripts are more powerful than aliases and scripts that can be run at any
date or time that you like which allows you to automate your workflows.
And it's precisely that scheduling that will be coming on to in the next video.
So in the next video you're going to learn the true power of shell scripts by learning how to automate
them using an incredibly useful utility known as Krumm.
So to learn how to schedule automated tasks I'll see you in the next video.