Hello you beautiful people and welcome to this video.
We're going to take what you've learned about bash scripts in the last few videos and supercharge it
by using Crohn to make those scripts run on a schedule.
It's going to be super awesome.
And over the next few videos you're going to make some bad scripts and schedule them to run automatically.
And we're also going to top it off by showing you how you can schedule automatic backups of your files
so epic right.
So by the end of the next few videos you're going to be able to automate your workflow by scheduling
your scripts to run where ever you want.
And this really does open the doors to untold awesomeness going forward.
So let's go ahead and jump right into it.
OK so crumbed is a command line based program that is used to schedule tasks.
Now Krumm gets its name from the Greek word Cronos which means time.
In case you were wondering so Crohn actually has quite a good name for a scheduling program right now.
Each user has what is known as a crutch tab which basically is just a text file and each cross-tab lists
which commands or scripts will be run automatically by that user.
And it also lists when they will be scheduled to be run now to edit the front of your user you just
open a command.
Open a terminal and type Krumm tab dash.
And the option is for edits and when you open it you'll see that the tab begins to open.
But if this is the first time the opening opens up it might ask you what editor you want to use.
So we're going to press one for Nonno and press enter and we will see that now we've opened up from
tab in nano.
Now the first thing you'll notice is that there's a lot of text in here and this is a kind of introduction
to how chrome tabs work.
But these are commented lines and what I mean by that is they are not interpreted by the cross-tab as
actual valuable information.
And you can tell that because they start each line with a hash and that allows you know people to write
what they want in a file like you know some notes but it's not interpreted by the actual by the actual
cron utility.
But down the bottom each Krumm tab is a Cantab is broken up into rows and one row is for each command
or script that you want to schedule and each row will have six columns.
So the first five columns are schedule information and the final sixth column is the command or script
to be run at that scheduled time.
So you need to get to the bottom and to enter your information.
OK.
Now this is really one of those things that's easier to be shown than explain.
So let me show you how this works.
So let's say that we want to run a command that just outputs the text Hello World to a file called Hello
directx t on our desktop and we want that command to run every minute of every day all year round because
for some reason we just really like saying hello.
OK.
So to make this happen we need to enter a new row in our Crohn top.
And so here we are we're on a new row and there are six columns in that row each column being separated
by some blank space.
OK.
So let's take it step by step.
Now the first column of the row is for the for the minutes of the hour the you want the command to run
on.
So let's go to the first column and we could put any number we want in here as long as it's a valid
minutes so we could type 15 for example.
Now this would make the command run at 15 minutes past the hour.
So things like 12 15 to 15 915 7:15 and so on.
OK.
Now the numbers for minutes can go from zero to 59 because that's what numbers for minutes do on a normal
clock right.
So they can go from 0 to 59 now because we want the command to run every minute.
We'll just put a star in there to say run any minute.
OK.
No no this isn't exactly like a wild card.
And the star happens to mean any in this case.
But crosstabs don't really support other wild cards so don't put symbols such as question marks or you
know the brackets in there because they won't work.
OK.
The star is only what's accepted and it just means any value.
We don't really care.
OK.
So the first column is the minutes of the hour the next column is the our number and we could put numbers
like for example 11.
So this would make it the command or whatever we scheduled to only run at 11 a.m. each day.
We could put 14 so that it would only run at 2 p.m. each day.
Now the numbers here are based on a 24 hour clock and can go from 0 to 23 and we but we don't mind particularly
what our command runs us which is put a star there as well.
But if I put for example an 11 in the law in the hour column and a 20 minute column then our command
would run at 11:20 a.m..
So the first column is for the minutes and the second column is for the hours and by the way it doesn't
really matter where we place these columns as long as there's some space between them.
OK so we could like you know separate them out like that with more than one space but as long as there's
some blank space in between each of the columns Crohn isn't too fussy about how about the half the stuff
is laid out.
So I mean just try to make it a bit clearer which column we're filling in here.
So there's the first column is minute second column ours and so on I'm just going to kind of spread
out our stuff a little bit here.
So we got a bit of a nicer layout but we don't really care about the minute superstar there.
We don't really care about the hours.
So I put a star there too.
Now the third column is the what we see here.
DOMA is the day of the month.
So if we put a one here then it would only run on the first day of the month.
And so for example if we had a 20 in the minutes column and we had in the I was called we had an 11.
And here we had a let's say 10 in the third column then this one of a command that we gave it would
only run on the tenth day of the month at 11:20.
OK but it would run all of the months of the year but only on the tenth day of the month.
At 11:20 a.m. But again we don't really mind what day of the month so we'll put a star there.
I will put a star in the other columns as well.
There we go.
So just let me lay this out a bit nicer.
Ok cool.
Now the fourth column is actually the month itself.
Now in here we can put numbers so we could put one.
Being January 12 being December and all the other months in between.
But you could also do it using text.
So for example in capital letters like John for January FEBE for February I could do may or D.C. for
December.
So three letter months can be used as well for the months if you write them in capital letters.
But here we don't really care about the months or what is going to put a star as well.
And so just to see how this is all coming together if we had 20 in the first column and we had in our
column we had an 11 and in the day the month we had a 10.
And in the month we had a you know J UN for June then this command would run on the 10th day of the
month on the 10th.
Sorry on the 10th of June at 11:20 a.m..
OK.
So that's that's how that works.
We're going to replace them again with stores.
OK.
So as I say the cross-tab doesn't really care about the amount of space is just that each column is
separated by at least one space.
OK.
So there we go the next column is the day of the week now the day of the week can have numbers from
zero to six with zero being Sunday and six being Saturday.
But as well you can do this.
Doing text using three letters for each day of the week so you end would be Sunday.
IMO it would be Monday.
Th she would be Thursday and Saturday would be Saturday and so on.
OK.
So let's say if we had a Sunday in there and the month was June and the day of the month was 10 and
then the hour was 11 and then the minute was 20 then this would run at 11:20 a.m. on the 10th of June.
As long as the 10th of June on that year was a Sunday.
OK.
So you can see how you can become incredibly specific with how you schedule your commands to run but
you can also be very general and very relaxed as well.
The cross-tab the Trani utility is amazing for that kind of stuff.
You can be very expressive with your scheduling.
So there we go where we're going to set those back to store because we don't care what day of the week
it is we want this on to run all day every minute.
All year around so we don't really care.
So those are the first five columns and these first five are scheduling information.
OK.
Now the final bit is actually where you tell it the command or script that you wanted to run.
So the sixth and final column is the command to actually run.
Now we said that we want to command the output Hello World to a file called Hello directx T.
Let's say on our desktop.
OK so how would we write that.
Well we might right echo.
Okay then.
Hello world.
And then with a pen that is somewhere on our desktop a file called Hello Dottie XTi case if I just expand
the window here you have to see it better there we go.
So you can see here that we're just saying this is just the command basically echo Hello world.
And put that on a funnel called haloed ATX take.
But we are using the two arrows here to allow whenever this command runs.
It will append to the file so we can see extra data being added each time the command runs.
OK.
So when we save the Krumm tab so crumble make sure that this command is now run at every minute of every
hour of every day of the month for every month no matter the day of the week.
So this command is going to run every minute all year round because if we press control an hour to save
that file and I exit you can see here that we get a message saying that it's installing a new cross-tab
and we can see here that Hello Dr. XTi has actually just been has just been executed.
OK.
So if we take a look at you can see that it actually just ran right.
Then we can see that it's actually executed hello world and put it inside inside the inside the file.
Now if I run the date command you can see the we've got about 40 seconds until this command runs again.
So I'm going to do is I'm going to cut the video here and come back closer to the time when that runs.
OK so here we are we can see that it's just gone as literally as I press day.
That's awesome.
It's just past the minute so if we look in there now we should see that we now have two rows of data
so fingers crossed.
Yes we do.
We now have two rows of data in there because the the the current app has executed again.
Right at the top of the hour.
And and we'll just continue to wait until the next minute passes and it will continue to run that it
will continue to run the command over and over and over again and fill up this Hello Dr. 65.
OK.
Now when when that actually runs we'll see that more data has been added.
We've got about 18 seconds or so so if you can wait with me for like 18 seconds we'll see this happen
OK.
So let's see if we go we see another 11 seconds or so.
And now if I if I check here now we can see that it's five seconds to go five seconds to go two seconds
to go.
It should have done it now.
So if we look inside.
Yes.
It's run and it's added another row to the file and I didn't touch anything I promise.
So the Akron tab is working.
Hooray.
OK we've just made it run a command over and over again.