So let's take a look at our Cantab again this go from tab with the option and we've opened it up.
It's remembered that nano is our editor and just so just in case you're interested.
If you go on to your home directory and you look at your your all the files with stash and there's a
hidden file here called selected editor and it's that file that stores your preference for for Ed..
So in here if we look at DOT selected editor you can see you can change that if you want by putting
the path to the editor that you want to have.
Or alternatively you could just type the select at Edit command and it would give you the choice again.
OK but I'm going to keep it to Nonno and leave it like that but that's how you wanted to change the
editor later on maybe you get better with another command line editor.
That's how you can change it.
OK.
So let's go on cross-tab dash.
And now what we're going to do is we're going to look at some more advanced options more advanced ways
that you can do some scheduling.
OK we can add as many rows as we like in this country and they will work exactly the same song and make
a new row and look at some more advanced scheduling opportunities.
So for example let's say I want to run something exactly at the hour and 15 30 and 45 minutes past.
OK.
So I don't just have to have one option here I can have zero comma 15 comma 30 45 that's going to be
my first column.
Right.
So this is going to be the minutes I can have a zero past 15 minutes past 30 minutes past and 45 minutes
passed.
Notice how I've got commas but no space is not left of any spaces because spaces separate the columns.
OK.
So that would be like my first my first column could you know then space this stuff over.
So I got a bit more space and now I could say OK run it and every hour every day of the month every
month.
Of the week.
And then whatever command I wanted to happen here says something like you know Hello Echo hello for
example and this would run at exactly as the hour turned and 15 minutes past the hour.
Thirty minutes past the hour.
Forty five minutes past the hour a quarter to the hour.
OK.
Or I could just say more simply run every 15 minutes and the way I do that is Star.
Then a slash 15.
OK.
Now that says run every 15 minutes I can say one every five minutes by Star slash five or every three
minutes star slash three every seven minutes star slash seven OK all stars lost 15.
Like I said for every 15 minutes.
What about a run every 15 minutes every three days let's say.
So what I do is I'd keep the hours the same and I'd go to the days of the month option and do star slash
three.
OK now.
So every three days so let's say on the first of the month the fourth of the month the seventh of the
month and so on on those days it'll run every 15 minutes.
OK.
So you can see how this kind of works here.
What if I wanted the command to run once a week at 23 59 on a Sunday only in December and January 23
59 on a Sunday but only in December and January.
Well do we do that.
Let's make another row.
We'd say let's say 23 59 so 59 is the minute the hour is going to be 23.
It doesn't matter which day of the month it doesn't really actually that the month it does my only Januarys
and December so generous in December's day of the week only Sundays.
OK and we can say because we can.
OK.
So there we are now what we've got twenty three fifty nine every day.
So what this is going to do Tony 3:59 injured in January in December but only on Sundays.
So there we are and he's going to echo because we can for example now there's a great Web site called
Crohn tab dot guru.
OK that you can take a look at and play around with to see what different cross-tab expressions mean.
And I'll put a link to it in the resources section.
It's awesome.
OK.
But a great use of chrom is to schedule automated backups of the file system.
So let's say we want to run weekly backups every Friday at 23 59 for every month of the year.
So if I delete these these examples here it is.
So 23 59 on Fridays for every month of the year.
So we know that 59 is the minute we know the hour is 23.
It doesn't matter the day of the month like numerically it doesn't matter whether it's the first or
the seventh.
Just every Friday and every month of the year but only on Fridays.
And then we'd put the command which is going to back up our stuff.
OK.
And you know that's how it would work.
And we know how to do this because we can make a script for it.
OK.
So let's save our cross-tab so far just like that.
And do you because it's Roche rifleman's lines but if I actually look just by the way what we've been
noticing that if I look in haloed ATX t you see we've got so many more of Hello worlds being edited
that as Accaron command that we set before has been continuing to run.
That's really cool.
It's automated and it's running in the background.
All right.
So let's set up the script that we want to run.
Now you remember in the last few videos when I was telling you about bash scripts we made a folder called
bin and inside that bin folder is where we started putting our scripts and we had this one file called
backup.
Let's take a look inside that backup script again.
Well in here what it does is it compresses into aana into a archive on our desktop and every single
one of the contents of our documents downloads desktops pictures and videos folders and it also outputs
some the error like the standard error Lovi the log messages that come from the command into the bit
bucket.
So they just sent it to to the void.
They then no longer print to the screen.
OK.
So this is good this is this is going to do a backup for us.
Let's say that actually instead of sending them to the desktop let's say that in our in our home directory
let's say let's say we made a directory called backups.
OK we got about that wrong.
So if I rename back ups to two houses into just backups with one S..
There we go.
We've now got a folder called backups.
OK.
And let's say we wanted to save the backups in there.
So if we go to the bin folder and we add a backup script now we can say OK go into our desktop go to
our backups folder OK and then save the backup dock.
Geez.
OK that's good.
And that's good for that.
But what we want as well is we want to also log the date and time that the backup was created into a
log file.
Now the way that we can do that is we could use the date command and we could append that data to a
file in our backups folder called let's say backup backups don't log.
Why don't we say that case we're going to call it backups doc log and that's just going to keep in there
the date and time that the last block happened.
OK so if we save that actually we could we could make it a bit more advanced.
We could actually.
Let's leave it like that.
Let's not make this any more complicated than it needs to be.
OK.
So we're going to take that data and we're going to append it to our backups not log file and you can
see here that I'm using the double arrows to make sure that as the script runs each time it's going
to it's going to add it.
So the fall gets longer as time goes on.
OK so we've now got this script that we wanted to run.
And if we've run it just we just want it back up from anywhere.
If we run back up you can see that now if I just put this back to a normal size if we go into our backups
folder we've now got backups tautologies.
And we've also got this backups doc log fiber with that with Nonno backups don't log.
You can see that it's logged the day in time.
OK so if I just remove remove everything in here using Ahram you can see they've all disappeared.
OK.
So good.
We know that script works.
Let's try and add it to our crumb tab.
OK.
So here we are we've said that we want every Friday at 23:15 and we want that.
We want that script to run.
So how can we do that.
Well the way we can run that is because it's a bash script we'll type the background so just bash like
that and then we'll give it the path to the script that we want to run.
So in our home directory in the bin folder we're going to run the backup script.
So that's all we've got to do right we just type bash and then give it the path to the script that we
want to run and then that script will now run at 23 59 on a Friday.
But to save you waiting all the way to 23:15 on on next right.
Let's go ahead make this run every minute so we can watch it happen again.
So look what I'm going to do.
Nice.
Haycock I guess I'm going to cut the line and uncut the line and then cut the line again.
That's a nice copy and paste.
And I'm going to make this run every minute.
OK.
So if we're ever going to change all of these stars K that we go.
Now that should run every minute now if I write the file and close it you can see it's installed the
new crop top now in backups.
There's nothing in here but if I look at the date we can see that we've got about 40 seconds until this
runs again makes me very excited I'm sure.
So we've got about 30 seconds so I'm going to cut the video here and come back close to the time.
So we always take a look and it's just gone past the minute.
So let's take a look at our backhoes folder and hooray we have indeed run our script correctly and if
we look inside the log folder if we look at backups top log we can see that it ran at just past the
third minute of today.
So the reason it runs at just the minute past it's just a like like you know there's just one second
error.
I think it's just a clock thing.
It's you know the computer can only process things at a certain time resolution and one second is really
not that much of a bad error.
OK.
So it'll be you'll tend to see things like this.
I think it actually does run at exactly the time the minute goes but the date command takes just about
a second or so to run or something like that so it has a slight delay.
But really one second is not bad at all.
So now we have indeed ran X-amount and look where it might it might even happen again.
It might even happen again.
So if we wait four more seconds one more second.
Yes.
Now we look inside our backups dot log backups dot log will see that another one is run again just one
second past the fourth minute.
So now we are making backups every single minute.
But that might be a bit of a bit of a bit of a burden on our computer here.
So let's just go ahead control K to delete the line and then we can save our job and leave it so that
it just runs at 20 3:59 on Fridays.
So there you are guys how awesome and how epic is that.
Some show you can see the power of combining together bash scripts and Crohn scheduling to control what
ever you want about your computer.
Now these two skills together are incredibly powerful combination.
And you now have the foundation in how they work.
So let's have a quick recap of what we've learned in this video.
So in this video you took a look at how to use Chrome to schedule when commands and scripts should be
run and you learn that every user has what is known as a crosstab and then you can edit Krumm tabs using
the crosstab command with the option with the standing for edit Now types a text files that are broken
up into many rows and you can have as many rows as you like and each command or script has its own row
and each row has six columns.
The first five columns are scheduling information and the sixth and final column details which comando
script should be run at that scheduled time.
So the columns are for that for the scheduling columns you've got the minutes of the hour.
So for example if you put 15 in the column the commom would only run at the 15 minute of each hour.
So it's things like 11:15 215 315 and so on that then you've got the hour itself.
So that's a number that you can put in 24 hour clock time.
So from 0 to 23 you've got then the third day of the column is the day of the month.
So again from one to the end of the month whatever that might be.
The fourth column is the month.
So that could be numbers with one being January and 12 being December.
Or you could just type in capital letters the three letter version of the month so J.N. for January
DC for December and so on and the fifth column is the day of the week.
So that could be zero to six with zero being Sunday and 6 being Saturday also and to 7 a Sunday.
Again if you wanted but a good way to do it is just to enter the day names.
So and being Monday SE1 being Sunday is a three letter day names.
OK.
And you also saw some advanced ways to schedule this stuff as well.
And a great place to look at these these scheduling things is to look at a Web site called cross-tab
dot guru I'll put a link to that in the resources section because it's a great Web site for you to practice
setting up these scheduling conditions and it also will become useful for you at some point in the future.
And as I should mention what columns can be separated by as many spaces as you like or Crohn ones is
that you separate each column by at least one space.
But feel free to format each rows however you'd like.
OK.
And you also saw in this video how to use Chrome tabs and bash scripts to schedule automated backups
of your home directory which is an incredibly useful thing to make sure that all your files stay safe
and built upon what you learned in the last section about file compression and archiving.
That's super awesome as well.
Now the key thing that I want you to remember from the last two videos is that in Linux practically
anything can be edited using the command line.
Now since you can write bash scripts to execute these commands in a controlled sequence and then use
cron to schedule when the script should be run you have the necessary toolkit to do what ever you want
on your system whenever you want to do it which is a crazily powerful combination.
All you need now is a bit of imagination to decide what you might like to do.
Now bash scripts are a whole massive topic in and of themselves so we only really had time to scratch
the surface and cover just a small bit of what they can do in this course but at least now you have
an understanding of what bad scripts are how they work and where you might use them.
And if you'd like me to create a specialized course on just bash scripts and then send me a message
and if I get enough of you saying that you want that then you know I can I can potentially put that
together for you.
But for what we've learned in this course so far I want to make sure you get some practice in using
it.
So in the next video you're going to be getting the brief for your next project assignment.
Now will be a rather simple and fun one this time to allow you to go off and try writing bash scripts
and crunch apps for yourself so you can get a hands on understanding of how these incredibly powerful
skills work.
So for the brief of your next assignment I'll see you in the next video.