Hello you beautiful people.
And welcome to this video.
We're going to be getting you set up with virtual box on your computer.
Now virtual box is an amazing piece of software that allows you to run what are called virtual machines
on your computer.
Now virtual machines other than having a totally awesome sounding name allow you to run virtual computers
inside your computer without affecting your actual computer so they're perfect for running things like
new operating systems and trying them out without affecting the way that your current computer works
so running a virtual machine through virtual box is going to create the perfect playground for us to
try the Linux operating system that is affecting the way that your actual computer works.
So nothing can actually go wrong so it's the perfect playground for us to try out the software.
So what I want to do is always a head over to the Virtual Box website which is not virtual box dot org
for Wiki for downloads.
I put a link in the resources section for this video or you could just have it or you could just head
over to your favorite search engine and just search for Virtual Box download and it will likely be the
first link that comes up.
And when you click it you'll come to a page like this.
OK.
Now here you go find some some links to some specific executable installer files that I want you to
download a case if you're on Windows I want you to click Windows hosts if you're a Mac and we to click
OS 10 hosts OK and if you want if you're already on Linux you basically don't need to install Linux
do you so you can just skip this entire section and move on to actual learning stuff.
But here we are if you want Windows click Windows if you are on Mac I was 10 but I'm on Windows Sangli
click that and you can download and install a file here.
OK.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going to just save that in my downloads folder but you can save that
wherever is best for you but I can save it in my downloads folder and it's going to download and install.
And it's going to install Virtual Box for us.
OK.
So that's going to headend downloaded what should be in just about two seconds or so.
There we are.
It's downloading I'm going to click that or head over to my downloads folder and double click.
However however I wish I could double click the ticket with the same thing and it's going to open up
this install a wizard which were just going to basically power through guys.
So I'm going to click next here.
Going to click next again.
And then it will ask you where do you want to put some shortcuts.
I'm just going to have a shocker in my Start Menu and on the desktop but I don't really want one in
the quicklaunch bar but make sure you have this one here.
Make sure whatever you choose just don't uncheck register file associations just leave that with a tick.
OK that must stay the same.
Be play around with the others depending on how you want your system set up where you want the shortcuts.
It doesn't really matter.
You can remove them anyway but you know your preference then go ahead and click next.
It's going to say hey we might need to access your network interface.
Just say yes don't worry about that whatsoever.
And click install.
It might give us the pop ups.
Go ahead and click yes to any pop ups that come up or click install or just give it permission whatever
it means just go ahead and do it.
It's just going to be giving virtual virtual box the ability to have your virtual machines access the
Internet which is usually a useful function.
So just click yes to whatever it asks for and then it will come to the installation complete screen
and there'll be a tick box here that says start virtual box after installation.
Make sure that that has a tick in it and click Finish and it will go ahead and open up a virtual box.
There you are guys that's how you go ahead and install virtual box.
Nice and easy.
Click click click click click process.
So now that we've gone ahead and install virtual box in the next video we showed you how you can set
up your own Linux virtual machine.
So folks watching this video guys you've now got virtual box installed on your machine.
Let's go ahead and set you up with Linux.