Hello the beautiful people and welcome to this video.
We're going to be getting you set up with your very own Linux virtual machine running a specific flavor
of Linux called a buntu.
So flavors of Linux are called distributions in the Linux lingo and we're going to be getting you set
up with Ubuntu distribution of Linux for your virtual box virtual machines.
So we're going to do is always a head over to the window with a bullet to dot com for download for its
last desktop.
I will be putting a link in the resources section and for this video or you could just head over to
your favorite search engine and search for a button to download and it'll be the first thing that comes
up and when you click on it you'll find a page that looks like this.
Now we don't want you to do and is going to give you multiple options of what version of a buntu you
want to download.
But I want you to click on the most up to date option.
So for example here I've got I've been to seventeen point ten.
Now one interesting thing you can actually tell when the buntu releases were released by just looking
at the version number Sahira can tell that it was released in 2000 and 17 in the tenth month which would
be October of here.
For example I can see that this was released in 2000 and 16 in the fourth month which is going to be
April.
So the more up to date version numbers mean they were released later on.
OK.
So what we're going to do is we're going to click in it will.
Anyone going to click on to 17:10 but you just click on whatever is most up to date for you it will
not affect your experience of the course the entire cost will be the same for you regardless whatever
version you pick but you might as well have the most up to date version.
So when you click download and it can open up another page where it's going to ask me for a few donations
but I'm going to say unfortunately that I'm not going to donate any money here today and I'm going to
be taken to the download.
And but you feel free to do whatever you want to do.
OK.
And then it's going to start to download what's called a disk image file to my computer and I'm going
to click and save it in the Downloads folder for myself.
You can download it wherever you want.
And you'll notice that a download starts to begin.
Now these ISO files used to be 10 usually tend to be quite large usually on the order of gigabytes so
you can see here that this is 1.4 gigabytes in size.
So this might take quite a while depending on how quick your Internet is.
Now you have to wait for that to go ahead and downloads what I'm going to do is I'm going to cut the
video here.
I'm going to come back when it is downloaded so just be patient with it she won't ever have to really
do it again.
And so once it's done it's done.
So just wait for that thing to download and then unpause the video to follow through with the rest of
the set up.
OK so the download has gone incompleted and now I can go ahead and install the virtual machine so you
can see that we've got this disk image file saved in my downloads folder.
And with that there we're going to go had an open up virtual box virtual box.
This is where you can set up virtual machines and try to run and you can have more than one switch is
going to create a new virtual machine.
I'm going to call it a buntu because I am imaginative and call it and you can see it's it's found the
type which is Linux and a buntu 64 bit which is which is what my one was.
And if yours was a 32 bit download then go ahead and click to 32 bit.
But I think by default it should be a 64 bit so I'll leave it at that.
Now I get hit next and it's going to ask me for the amount of memory or RAM in megabytes to be allocated
to the virtual machine.
Now an important thing to note here that this is only allocated when the virtual machine is running
when you turn the virtue when you close a virtual machine.
It will.
It will be given back to the host computer.
So don't worry about this too much just give it a generous amount so let's say up to about let's say
about three quarters or 80 percent of the green distance you don't want to go all the way up to here
because this might make your system stutter a bit and jittery a bit.
So just take it most of the way up to the green to the end of the green but not all the way.
So leave some buffer room there.
OK so I'm going to leave it at that.
Do it by.
This isn't a perfect science.
Just go ahead and do it by then is going to ask you about a hard disk now that you can imagine is that
this virtual machine is thinks that it's a computer and a computer needs a hard drive space.
OK.
So what we're doing is we're creating an imaginary hard drive that this virtual box is this which machine
is going to think is a real hard drive.
But it's actually just a file saved on our actual computer.
OK.
So what we can do is we get to create a virtual hard disk now.
So this creates it and it says what type do you want it to be just leave it as the first option a virtual
box disk image or leave it just like that.
And then it's going to say do you want it to be.
Do you want the file dates to be dynamically allocated or fixed size and dynamically allocated means
that when when the data fills up on my imaginary harddrive the fire will get bigger and fix size means
that the file will be that size no matter what.
Even if it's basically empty for efficiency sake let's just have it dynamically allocated.
And then you can call it whatever you want and store it wherever you want by clicking this this arrow
here to change where you want to save it but just leave it as the default if you don't particularly
fast and it doesn't really matter massively and how much size you give it I tend to just give my 20
gigabytes that's usually more than enough.
But you can you can just choose what's all right for you.
It's you know as long as you've got something above one or two gigabytes you should be absolutely fine.
So so I'm just going to have 20 gigabytes there for it as an imaginary hard disk and I'm going to click
Create.
OK.
So we're almost there and we're very very close.
We've got to do is click on settings to set up a few more things so to make sure that are to make sure
that our virtual machine has just a bit more power.
What we're going to do is we're going to click on settings go to System and click Proceso the processor
tab and increase this to two cause if you have them.
So two processors or up to the end of the green here.
So what I'm going to do that just basically allows the virtual machine to just have that bit more performance.
OK.
And everything else should be the same except when you click on storage there's one final thing to do.
So on storage This is where we're going to basically insert that disk image so you can imagine that
the imaginary computer booting from that Douban buntu image into a real computer.
It's a bit confusing but just follow with me it's click on storage then you'll see this bit here where
it says controller ID and it will have a disk that says empty.
OK.
So click then click on this desk at the top right click that and it will say choose virtual optical
disk file says Click lock then we'll go to my downloads folder and click on ribband to seventeen point
ten disk image that we downloaded or whatever disk image version that you downloaded you're able to
version click open.
And now that's that's all set up.
Click OK.
And we're basically all good to go.
So that's all set up ready to go and in the next video we're going to run you through.
And the final bit of the installation which is setting up the actual buntu machine when it boots up.
So for all that goodness I'll see you in the next video.