Hello beautiful people and welcome to this video.
We're going to be doing the final step of setting up your a buntu installation inside the virtual machine.
Though we should say that if you do get any errors in this process like you know it says the virtual
machine crashes just go over here in virtual box click on settings system and drag this bar a bit lower
down into the green.
Ok just that just to give your host computer or just a bit more memory in case it needs.
OK.
So just in case that happens but don't worry if it does.
Nothing's gone wrong just close it.
Reduce that bar down to the green and then try again.
OK.
But we're going to do now is we're going to we're going to open in virtual box we're going to click
start on our ability virtual machine.
And while this is going to do is it's going to open up an imaginary computer inside our computer.
So this is super awesome.
And this is the actual process that you would have to go through if you wanted to install a buntu for
real as the only operating system on an actual computer.
So what's opening up now is called a virtual machine.
It's an imaginary computer inside a computer that thinks you're installing an operating system on it
because we're booting from that live CD.
OK.
So all that imaginary disk file that we downloaded in the last video.
So what we're going to have to do now is we're just going to have to install a buntu on this imaginary
computer and it's really easy process as you can see.
It's opened up now and it's going to give us two options it's going to say try to install two.
I'm going to go ahead.
What you do is click install to but make sure you pick whatever language you would like from the side
here.
I'm going to keep it in English and then click install a buntu.
OK.
So with that it's going to give you some extra options here.
Take both of these boxes.
This one is going to allow it to update download and some updates when installing Kubuntu.
And this is going to install third party software such as Wi-Fi hardware MP3 players and other stuff
just to make you know your your experience a bit more complete and make your virtual machine you know
just have a few more features than it would otherwise.
So go ahead and take both those boxes and then click continue.
And then it's going to give us some other options to play with on the next screen.
This bit's taking a little bit of time.
There we go.
It's saying the computer currently has detected no operating systems.
Would you what would you like to do.
Well just click.
Just have erase disk and install buntu to go ahead and click Install now.
It's going to say do you want to write the changes just click continue.
That's perfectly fine.
And now it's going to ask you where in the world are you now.
This is just for timezone purposes and you can click on different areas depending on what you might
wear where you might be if you know you've got the US over here in the UK so I'm going to click there
and it's going to and actually I want to have London as my time zone.
So there we are it says London and we're going to click continue and now we're going to ask you for
your keyboard layout.
Mine's English UK so I'm going to I'm going to click English OK and that's going to be fine for me but
you can actually if I just go back sorry you can test your keyboard Leo by clicking detect keyboard
layout and typing one of these keys if I press y in there and then another one and then is at present
no it's not.
It'll figure it out for me.
Which keyboard I should be using.
And then it will help me out pick it pick it out or not but I can just also select it from the list.
It's up to you.
English is fine for me.
You just go ahead and pick whatever is good for you.
Then click continue.
And then it's asking you for your username so I'm going to put Ziyad as my username.
It's going to ask me for a computer name it can automatically generate that but I'm going to call my
VB for virtual box picking a user name Ziyad and then it's going to ask me for passwords I'm going to
enter a password is weak password don't judge me.
To a fantastic password.
So there we are we've entered that and it says require a password to log in and keep that checked and
that's all you really need to do.
But make sure you do remember this password because it will come very useful throughout the course.
And if you want to use your virtual machine and not be locked out so do remember that one.
Then click continue.
And now what it's going to do is it's going to go about installing all of a buntu onto this virtual
machine.
And it's telling can you know you've got some information about to hit as fast and full of new features.
The latest version of a buntu makes computing easier than ever.
Here are just a few cool new things to look out for.
And you can click on this arrow and it says find even more software say goodbye to having to search
the web for new software with access to software store.
You can install new apps with ease.
Just type in what you're looking for or explore categories such as science education and games all alongside
helpful reviews from other users.
Awesome.
You can take your music with you.
Buntu comes with the amazing Rhythmbox music player with advanced playback options.
It's simple to cue up the perfect songs and it works great with CDs and portable music player so you
can enjoy all your music wherever you go.
Wonderful and you can keep clicking through these things.
The stuff about photos.
Web browsing so it already comes with Firefox for example and it also comes with its own suite of office
software so basically similar software to Microsoft Word Microsoft Excel Powerpoint and so on.
Com for free.
They could also work with Microsoft Office files that's useful.
You've got other things they said accessibility options if you need any particular accessibility options.
When you use your computer they also are included as well.
You can have them.
It tells you about some help and support from the Ubuntu team.
So what this is doing is it's basically just going to install loads of software on your computer it's
going to do a full install of a bunch too and it might take a bit of time depending upon you know just
how quick your computer is installing stuff really.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to keep the video here and then I'm going to come back when this
installation has finished and to continue the rest of the way.
OK and I'm back and you can see that the installation is now complete.
It says you need to restart the computer in order to use the new installation so I'm going to click
restart now and that should shut down the virtual machine just like that and it says to remove the installation
medium.
Please remove the installation medium then press and do so I'm going to press enter.
And that should now start booting up the buntu virtual machine again but this time without having to
install it anymore us wait for this to open.
Very exciting and there we go.
It's now popped up and said hey here's my username which is Ziyad.
I can click on that I can enter my password and click enter or click sign in and it's going to show
me this.
This rather awesome looking hacker stuff.
And there we are.
We've now gone ahead and successfully installed a buntu on our virtual machines.
Isn't that awesome.
What we've got here we can you know you can see you've got the Firefox browser installed you've got
Rhythmbox which is like a music player.
You've got files which is like your file Navigator will be using this quite a bit in the course.
You've got folders installed here you've got software center which is going to be a way for you to download
Xserve software we won't use this directly in the course but it's there in case you wanted to browse
and have a look at.
You know you can browse through the old Add-Ons you can have a look out here and there's so much to
do.
You've got up here you've got different settings and stuff you can take a look at your settings and
really what I want you to do is I want you to have a play around with this stuff it works.
It's just a computer guys kind of thing.
Things are just laid out in a different way but it's it's not going to be too strange compared to what
you're already used to.
Things might have a few different names.
And one thing that's good is to show applications.
Button Down here which when you click that it will open up in a rather awesome way showing you some
applications that are installed that you can click on to have a lockout so you've got Thunderbird which
is like an email client videos which shows you videos games and here such as Margene.
You've got Liebreich office which is like Microsoft Office calculator because math and you've also got
text editors and loads of loads of really awesome things on here.
OK so one thing that we're going to be making a lot of use of of course is the terminal which is what
you guys came here to learn.
So with that all set up and once you've got yourself comfortable with this it should take you about
five minutes or so it's really easy to get used to.
What are we going to do in the next video is get you started learning how to use commands and when it
says here updated software has been issued Do you want to install it now.
Sure go ahead just go ahead and click Install now and wait for that installation process to complete
it should sort itself out on its own.
Ask you for your password.
You had to enter that to give it some permission to go ahead and do the installation and you should
have a fully updated and ready to go system for learning linux on.
And when you are ready all you've got to do every time you want to launch this is just head over into
virtual box and then just click start and it will boot up.
This this this modern computer.
So there you are you are completely ready to go.
So I look forward to seeing you in the next section of the course.
We're going to start you off by learning how to use the terminal comm way to show you gradual set I'll
see you in the next video.