Hello you beautiful people and congratulations for making it through the course.
So our journey together has taken you right from learning how to open the terminal and run commands
all the way to creating file archives writing automated scripts and managing thousands of pieces of
software using the package manager.
So you truly have come an incredibly long way and I'm incredibly proud of you.
Well done.
And I just wanted to shoot this video to say thank you very much for coming along with me on this journey
through that Linux command line and I hope that you've received some benefit from our journey together
and I wish you the very best in the future.
And if you do want to learn more do take a look at some of my other courses and keep an eye out for
information about more advanced courses to take your learning to the next level.
And in fact I'll be putting special discount coupon links for you in the resources section for this
video or somewhere around here.
For all my courses just to say thank you for being a student so go ahead and enroll in whatever you'd
like.
And if there's something in particular that you would like to learn or another course that you would
like me to create.
I always listen to suggestions so send me a message and I'll do what ever I can to make that happen.
And if you finish the course 100 percent.
You should soon receive a certificate of completion from you to me by email for you to print off and
put on your linked in profile or to show proudly to the world that you are now and Linux master.
And if you do have any troubles getting the certificate through do contact you to me support team on
support at you to me dot com and they'll sort it all out for you.
And other than that I wish you the absolute best and hope you have my utmost respect and gratitude for
trying to invest in your learning.
So good luck with everything and I hope to have the pleasure of meeting you again soon.