Hello and congratulations for making the decision to sign up to the cause and propel yourself towards
the next mastery.
Hi I'm Ziyad and I wanted to do a quick video to congratulate you for making the excellent decision
to sign up and I wanted to give you a quick introduction to what we'll be covering in the course.
So first we're going to get you all set up with Linux by walking you through step by step through an
installation of Linux on your own virtual machine.
Now doing it this way means that you can play around with whatever you like without risking anything
or damaging anything and anything can really go wrong.
Think of it as your perfect playground to the awesome skills that you'll learn in the course.
Then we're going to move on to learn all about the Linux terminal.
An incredibly powerful program that is your gateway to doing anything that you want on your Linux machine.
We'll discuss what the terminal is how to use it how to enter commands and clear up popular misconceptions
that may be floating around.
Now the important concepts that you'll learn in that section of the Course will lay the critical foundations
for everything that you'll do within an X command line and it will make it all start to make sense.
Well then move on to discuss the Linux file system and how to work with files that work working with
files is probably 99 percent of what we do on a on an everyday basis.
And so when something had to work with files effectively and efficiently using the command line is an
incredible ability to game.
Now in this section you'll have to create delete copy paste edit rename move find open search archive
and compress files and so much more and it'll make you able to do anything you want with files.
But with the efficiency of the command line it's going to be awesome.
We'll then move on to how to automate tasks using bash scripts so you had to write bash scripts and
how to schedule these scripts to run at certain dates and times.
So you can automate your daily workflow and finally you'll learn all about installing third party software
on your Linux machine.
You don't have to search for new software from the software repositories and how to manage your software
using software managers.
You'll also learn about open source software and what it means to be part of the open source community
as well as learning how to take source code and compile it into working programs.
Now by the end of this course you'll be comfortable using the Linux operating system and you'll wonder
why you haven't been using it all along.
And one thing I always aim for in my courses is to make the content on forgetable so I had to help cement
the learning.
You have quizzes to check your grasping the concepts and you also have some assignments for you to complete
to really test and improve your skills and there are also some cheat sheets summarizing the concepts
from the course so you don't need to take notes to sit back relax and practice the skills.
And rest assured that the important information is jotted down for you in professionally designed cheat
sheets for free to refer to whenever you want.
Now if you ever need any help feel free to ask questions in the questions area and when you feel you've
got immersed in the course please leave a review to encourage other students take the course so we can
make the joys of the Linux operating system accessible to everyone.
Other than that I wish you a very pleasant time learning Linux in the course and I bet you can't wait
to get started.
So let's jump right in and get you set up with your own Linux virtual machine.